<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The True loyalist wherein is discovered, First, the falsehood and deceipt of the solemn league and covenant, Secondly, that there is no salvation out of Christ, Thirdly, that the pope is the Anti-Christ, the man of sin, or the son of perdition, cum multis alias, &amp;c. / by a true loyalist.</title>
            <author>True loyalist.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1683</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 208 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 80 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A63550</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing T2756</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R31985</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12292509</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12292509</idno>
            <idno type="VID">58923</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A63550)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 58923)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1515:28)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The True loyalist wherein is discovered, First, the falsehood and deceipt of the solemn league and covenant, Secondly, that there is no salvation out of Christ, Thirdly, that the pope is the Anti-Christ, the man of sin, or the son of perdition, cum multis alias, &amp;c. / by a true loyalist.</title>
                  <author>True loyalist.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 156 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for the author, and are to be sold by John Crump ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>MDCLXXXIII [1683]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Union Theological Seminary Library, New York.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Catholic Church --  Controversial literature.</term>
               <term>Divine right of kings.</term>
               <term>Dissenters, Religious --  Controversial literature.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-11</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-11</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-01</date>
            <label>Judith Siefring</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-01</date>
            <label>Judith Siefring</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:58923:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:58923:1"/>
            <p>THE <hi>True Loyaliſt:</hi> Wherein is Diſcovered, <hi>Firſt,</hi> The falſhood and deceipt of the Solemn League and Covenant. <hi>Secondly,</hi> That there is no Salvation out of Chriſt. <hi>Thirdly,</hi> That the <hi>Pope</hi> is the Anti-Chriſt, the Man of Sin, or the Son of Perdition. <hi>Cum multis aliis,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>By a <hi>True Loyaliſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <bibl>1 Pet. 2.17. </bibl>
               <p>
                  <hi>Fear God, and Honour the King.</hi>
               </p>
               <bibl> 1 Sam. 8.8. &amp; 12.18.</bibl>
            </q>
            <q>
               <p>
                  <hi>Quiſquis Deum timet, etiam Regibus honorem habebit.</hi>
               </p>
               <bibl> Calvin.</bibl>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for the Author, and are to be Sold by <hi>John Crump</hi> at the <hi>Three Bibles,</hi> at the Lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle North-door in St. <hi>Paul</hi>'s Church<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yard.
<abbr>MDCLXXXIII</abbr>.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div n="1" type="part">
            <pb facs="tcp:58923:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:58923:2"/>
            <head>THE True Loyaliſt.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>PROV. XXIV. 21.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <q>
                  <p>My Son fear thou the Lord, and the King: And meddle not with<note n="*" place="margin">Heb. Chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers.</note> them that are given to change.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>KING <hi>Solomon,</hi> the Wiſe, having by woeful experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence ſeen much folly and vanity in all the paſſages of this life, even in hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane wiſdom it ſelf<note n="a" place="margin">Eccleſ. 1.</note>; is thought moſt fit by the Holy Ghoſt to become our Maſter of defence, and inſtructer therein; to arm us againſt all their aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaults, with many wiſe Counſels, and wholeſom inſtructions, in three Books, gradually: This his <hi>Proverbs,</hi> his <hi>Eccleſiaſtes,</hi> and his <hi>Canticles;</hi> anſwer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able to the three remarkable Periods of mans Age; his Youth, his Manhood, and his Old age. 1. In his Proverbs, or wiſe ſayings, he hath given us ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:58923:3"/>bitter pills, to purge out our amorous and youthful luſts; and many love-po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions too, to allure us unto good works, by that Beauty and Luſtre that is in ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue, and from the reward of well-doing: That our new Veſſels being ſeaſoned with Wiſdom when we are <hi>Ephebi</hi> and Young, may not taſte of the cask of folly when we are old<note n="b" place="margin">Prov. 22.6.</note>. 2. In his <hi>Eccleſiaſtes,</hi> or book of the Preacher, he hath diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered the perilous and painted Beauty of the world, the deceitfulneſs and ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phiſtry of Riches and Honour, and all things therein, together with the brevi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, uncertainty, and evil of a mans days; that when we are <hi>adulti,</hi> more ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, and confirmed in years, we may be moved thereby to deſpiſe and repu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diate the one, for its deformity and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſufficiency; and get the more ſolidity, by a ſerious reflection upon the vanity of the other. 3. In his <hi>Canticles, Epitha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lamium,</hi> or myſtical Love-ſong betwixt Chriſt and the Church, from the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſideration of natural and earthly things, he aſcends to the ſpeculation and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>templation of things Supernatural and Divine: That when we are Old, Aged, and well ſtricken in years, we may not grow the more earthly, the more we
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:58923:3"/>grow to the earth; but have our minds there in a ſpecial manner, poſſeſſed with Metaphyſical and Heavenly meditati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and fixed upon God and Chriſt, where the Soul (like <hi>Noahs</hi> Dove) can only find reſt and tranquillity. For as St.<note n="*" place="margin">Bernard <hi>in</hi> Canticis.</note> 
               <hi>Bernard</hi> hath taught us, in <hi>pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mo, pellitur ſuperfluus amor Sui: in ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cundo, vanus amor mundi: in tertio, prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribitur caſtus amor Dei.</hi> The <hi>Proverbs</hi> diſſwade us from <hi>Philautia,</hi> the fooliſh and ſuperfluous love of our ſelves: The <hi>Eccleſiaſtes</hi> diſſwades the vain &amp; worth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs love of the Vicious World: The <hi>Canticles</hi> perſwade the pure, chaſt and perfect love of God.</p>
            <p>So that theſe Books of <hi>Solomon</hi> being adapted to the three grand periods of mans age, none may think themſelves unconcerned, and plead want of dire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction: But all even from the days of their youth may remember their Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor<note n="c" place="margin">Eccleſ. 12.1.</note>, and as they grow in years grow in grace, always aſcending up higher and higher upon <hi>Jacobs</hi> Ladder,<note place="margin">2 Pet. 1.</note> from one vertue to another, till they come to glory.</p>
            <p>And accordingly, the Wiſe man hath directed this Proverb to all both young and old; to inſtruct the one, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mind
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:58923:4"/>the other of their duty of ſubje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction and obedience to the Lord,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Analogia nu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meri,</hi> the ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gular number for the Plural, by a <hi>Synecdo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che membri.</hi>
               </note> and the King, under a ſweet compellati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, but indefinite title, <hi>fili mi,</hi> my Son; whereby are meant all the Sons and Daughters of <hi>Adam,</hi> without diſcrimi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation.</p>
            <p>And, <hi>Secondly,</hi> as this Proverb is uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſal in its direction: ſo it contain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth a duty no leſs neceſſary to be per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed by all. For it is obſervable, that our Maſter uſeth this familiar and inſinuating title, <hi>fili mi,</hi> my Son, on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly here, and two and twenty times be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides in all his Proverbs; to ſhew that though his other Proverbs which only ſuppoſe this title, are in their proper Spheres very excellent for Wiſdom and inſtruction: yet thoſe Proverbs that are inforced immediately with this winning and alluring compellation, <hi>fili mi,</hi> My Son, are of nearer concern, and more important Leſſons for us to learn in his School of Wiſdom, or Righteouſneſs. And I may add too, that this Proverb, which we are now upon, doth ſeem (in regard of its great comprehenſiveneſs) to have an eminen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy above them all; as including in it (<gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>,<note place="margin">Eccleſiaſtes 12.13.</note> by way of excellency) the
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:58923:4"/>whole Duty of Man, all the ingredi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ents of a Chriſtian, to conſtitute the Eſſence or Being of a <hi>true Loyaliſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This will moſt clearly appear in the opening of its parts, which are theſe two, in general.</p>
            <list>
               <item>1. A Precept; <hi>My Son fear thou the Lord and the King.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>2. A Caution; <hi>and meddle not with them that are given to change.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <p n="1">1. For the Precept; <hi>My Son, fear thou the Lord and the King.</hi> And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in two things are very worthy our con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſideration.</p>
            <list>
               <item>1. A Conjunction of <hi>the Lord and the King.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>2. An Injunction of fear to them both. In the handling of which, order re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quires me that I firſt ſpeak of the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>junction of <hi>the Lord and the King.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <p>And they are very fitly and wiſely joyned together, in three things.</p>
            <p n="1">1. In regard of their Headſhip and Soveraignty; for <hi>Deus magnus &amp; immor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>talis eſt Rex, &amp; Rex parvus &amp; mortalis eſt Deus.</hi> God is a great and immortal King, and a King is a little and mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal God<note n="d" place="margin">Pſ. 82.6.</note>. Monarchy is Gods own Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment, he hath his Throne in the Heavens; and his Kingdom ruleth
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:58923:5"/>over all the Kingdoms of the World<note n="e" place="margin">Pſ. 103.19. Iſa. 66.1.</note>; where he hath ordained terrene Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narchs for his Deputies, and Viceroys, to rule his Church externally, in his ſtead; as he himſelf rules it inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nally by his Holy Spirit. And from hence he is emphatically ſtyled <hi>the King of kings, and Lord of lords</hi>
               <note n="f" place="margin">1 Tim. 6.15.</note>: And Kings <hi>nurſing Fathers,</hi> and Queens <hi>nurſing Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers</hi> to his Church<note n="g" place="margin">Iſa. 49.23.</note>.</p>
            <p n="2">2. In regard of the Prerogatives, which are annexed to their Headſhip and Soveraignty. The firſt whereof is Power and Authority; God in pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portion to his Grandeur and Headſhip over all the World, hath abſolute and Independent power in himſelf. In which reſpect he is here called by his proper name Lord, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, in the Ori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginal, the name of his Eſſence, and Majeſty; deduced <hi>ab</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>fuit,</hi> as be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a Being before, and the Original of all Beings: The ſame with <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>ero qui ero, I will that I will;</hi> or as in the Engliſh, <hi>I am that I am</hi>
               <note n="h" place="margin">Exod. 3.14.</note>, to ſhew the Soveraignty of his authority, and the incontroulableneſs of his will and pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er: So in like manner hath he given to earthly Monarchs power too<note n="i" place="margin">Rom. 13.1. John 19.11.</note> over his Church or people, in their particular
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:58923:5"/>Dominions, in proportion to their Vice<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerency under him, as their Maſter and Lord paramount. The Lord is abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lute both in power and ſupremacy, he is higher than the higheſt<note n="k" place="margin">Eccleſiaſtes 5.8. Pſ. 89.27.</note>, and <hi>who ſhall ſay unto him, What doſt thou</hi>
               <note n="l" place="margin">Job 9.12. Iſa. 45.9. Dan. 4.35.</note>? and the King is next him, he hath no ſupe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riour but the<note n="*" place="margin">The very Heathens, by the light of nature, did acknowledge this Doctrine, <hi>Marcus Aurelius</hi> ſays in <hi>Dion Caſſius,</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, of Imperial Authority, God only may be Judge: <hi>In excerptis Dio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nis Caſſii. &amp; vid. Herodotum</hi> l. 3. <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </note> Lord himſelf, to whom he is bound to give an account; he doth whatſoever pleaſeth him. <hi>Where the word of a King is, there is power:</hi> and who (but God) may ſay unto him, <hi>What doſt thou</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">Eccleſiaſtes 8.3, 4.</note>? And therefore King <hi>David</hi> ſaid unto God, <hi>Againſt thee, thee only have I ſinned.</hi> Pſ. 51.4.</p>
            <p n="3">3. As the Lord and the King are very fitly and wiſely joyned together, in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard of their headſhip &amp; prerogatives, Supremacy and power, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> ſo alſo in regard of their Election to their Kingſhip. The Lord to demonſtrate his abſolute Power and Supremacy, will be the Author both of his own Election, and his Vicegerents too. 1. Of his own he Elected himſelf King over<note n="n" place="margin">1 Sam. 12.12.</note> 
               <hi>Iſrael.</hi> The <hi>Iſraelites</hi> were Gods
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:58923:6"/>own choſen inheritance<note n="o" place="margin">Deut. 9.26. Pſ. 105.43.</note>, and therefore he choſe to be their King, to govern all their affairs, both in Church and State in a ſpecial manner. 'Tis true, he had even then his Viceroys under him; but they did not rule like the Kings of other Nations; the Lord himſelf did by them rule his peculiar people, after a pecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liar manner, as their King; till the days of <hi>Samuel;</hi> where all the Elders of <hi>Iſrael</hi> gathered themſelves together, and by a wilful, ſaucy, Traiterous, Rebellious, Diſloyal, ungrateful and obſtinate de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand of a King, to judge them like all the Nations<note n="p" place="margin">1 Sam. 8.5, 19.</note>, rejected him from ruling over them<note n="q" place="margin">1 Sam. 10.19.</note>. For though in that wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Act they caſt off <hi>Samuel</hi> alſo<note n="r" place="margin">1 Sam. 8.8.</note>, as being their Judge, and the Lords Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet and Viceroy; yet it was the Lord in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed, that therein was chiefly rejected, as being their only King and Soveraign, as well as the Lord their God: As <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>muel</hi> told them before, to ſtop them (if he could) from being obſtinate in deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring a change; and the Lord himſelf confirms it, when he ſaid to <hi>Samuel, they have not rejected thee, but they have rejected me that I ſhould not reign over them</hi>
               <note n="f" place="margin">1 Sam. 8.7.</note>. For which cauſe, that they might perceive and ſee that
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:58923:6"/>their wickedneſs was great, which they had done in the ſight of the Lord, in asking them a King; <hi>Samuel</hi> called un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Lord, and the Lord ſent ſuch ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rible thunder and rain upon their Har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veſt, that they were afraid it would have deſtroyed even them themſelves. And therefore all the people ſaid unto <hi>Samuel, Pray for thy Servants unto the Lord thy God, that we die not: for we have added unto all our ſins, this evil, to ask us a King</hi>
               <note n="t" place="margin">1 Sam. 12.17, 18, 19.</note>. This you ſee (without re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance) is the love God hath for them who fear not him, nor his Viceroy<note n="u" place="margin">1 Sam. 12.18.</note>, but deſire a Change.</p>
            <p>Yet ſince their mind was ſtill for Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narchy, (which all the Nations about them had choſen by the light of nature) the Lord granted them a King according to their Petition<note n="w" place="margin">1 Sam. 8.7.</note>, but only he would not grant them the liberty of Electing him themſelves;<note place="margin">The people cannot re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>move Kings, and ſet up Kings, without uſurping the Lords Preroga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive. Dan. 2.21.</note> for that is a Preroga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive ſo annexed to his Headſhip, that he could not poſſibly do it without in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trenching upon his own Royalty, and Supremacy, as he is King of Kings. We ſhould think it very unreaſonable if any ſhould deſire (without our ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointment) to have the choice of him that is to be our ſervant; how much
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:58923:7"/>more then is it unreaſonable for any to deſire to have the choice of him that is to be Gods Deputy and Viceroy? When<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as the diſtance between God and man is ſo great that it is beyond Compari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon. Therefore the Lord would not ſuffer his King to be the peoples Elect, but as at firſt he was the Author of his own Election: ſo now, 2. He would be the Author of his Vicegerents too: For though it be ſaid, <hi>Behold the King whom ye have choſen</hi>
               <note n="x" place="margin">1 Sam. 12.13.</note>. Yet that choice was only in regard of their wills to have a King, and the Election of him, if they could; and therefore it is ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded in the ſame Verſe, <hi>and whom ye have deſired:</hi> For behold, the Lord himſelf choſe him<note n="y" place="margin">1 Sam. 10.24.</note>, and appointed <hi>Samuel</hi> to anoint <hi>Saul</hi> for their King<note n="z" place="margin">1 Sam. 10.1. &amp; 12.1, 13.</note>. But though the Lord choſe them a King, yet he was ſuch a King as might be a Curſe to them, for their deſiring a Change; as is expreſſed in the manner of his Reigning over them<note n="a" place="margin">1 Sam. 8.11. &amp;c.</note>. And in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed though they might fooliſhly ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gine, that if they had had a King of their own Election, (as they alſo wickedly deſired) he might be the more plyable to their humors, it belonging to them, with as much right to remove him
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:58923:7"/>when they pleaſed; yet ſince they went ſo unadviſedly to work in asking a King (under the pretext of <hi>Samuels</hi> old age, and the male adminiſtration of his Sons<note n="b" place="margin">1 Sam. 8.5.</note>) without deſiring Gods choice and conſent, they could not expect (if they had believed God) that their King ſhould prove any better than a Tyrant<note n="c" place="margin">1 Sam. 8.18.</note>, for God foretold them by his ſervant <hi>Moſes,</hi> thus, <hi>When thou art come into the Land which the Lord thy God giveth thee, and ſhalt poſſeſs it, and ſhalt dwell therein, and ſhalt ſay, I will ſet a King over me, like as all the nations that are about me: Thou ſhalt in any wiſe ſet him King o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver thee whom the Lord thy God ſhall chooſe:</hi> (that is, in the ſenſe of the <hi>Targum</hi> of <hi>Ben. <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>zziel,</hi> Ye ſhall ſeek inſtruction of the Lord, and after that ye ſhall ſet a King over you.) <hi>One from among thy Brethren, ſhalt thou ſet King over thee: Thou mayeſt not ſet a ſtranger over thee, which is not thy Brother, Deut.</hi> 17.14, 15.</p>
            <p>But to this precept (you ſee) they had no regard; they would not take Gods choice and advice, nor ſtay his time and pleaſure, till <hi>David</hi> had chang<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed his Sheephook into a Scepter; who being a man after Gods own heart<note n="d" place="margin">1 Sam. 13.14.</note>,
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:58923:8"/>was the fitteſt to ſucceed him in the Government<note n="e" place="margin">1 Sam. 16.7.</note>, but they moſt arrogant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and preſumptuouſly aſſumed unto themſelves a Power of Electing whom and when they pleaſed: Becauſe they were the Elders of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> and particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lary of that chief Council of them, cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led the Sanhedrim, (inſtituted by God at the requeſt of <hi>Moſes</hi> for his aſſiſtance) they thought they might do any thing: For which cauſe, the Lord again com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plains of them in the Prophet <hi>Hoſea,</hi> mentioning their Crime in the Plural Number, for the clearer example to all Nations under the Sun: <hi>They have ſet up Kings, but not by me;</hi> (or according to the <hi>Arabick</hi> Verſion, they have Reigned from themſelves, and not from me.) <hi>They have made Princes, but I knew it not, Hoſea</hi> 8.4. that is, contrary to my Will, allowance, and approba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
            <p>Thus (you ſee) that it is abſolutely unlawful for any, either Elders, San<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hedrim or Parliament men, upon any pretence whatſoever, either to chuſe, or be choſen a King without Gods leave, counſel and advice, as he hath appoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, and directed in his word: How much more then is it unlawful to ſet
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:58923:8"/>up any other form of government beſides Monarchy, Gods own, both by Order, Precept and Example? Yet many (in this latter age of the World, now ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity doth abound, and get the upper hand<note n="f" place="margin">Mat. 24.12.</note>) have preſumed to do it. I need not trouble you with an inſtance of this, out of any Hiſtory, for its il<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luſtration; you know we have had a more eminent example of it already in <hi>Cromwell,</hi> that Arch-Traitor, and Uſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per; and thoſe Phanaticks and Chang<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, that ſet up the Idol, and worſhip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed it, than all the Hiſtories in the world can afford beſides, being put all toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther.</p>
            <p>But if the Ruler be not <hi>Tyrannus ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tulo,</hi> a meer Uſurper like him, and ille<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gally choſen; but one that having a juſt Right and Title to the Crown, en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treth into his Throne by the right door, and climbeth up not ſome other way; the ſame is no Thief, nor Rob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber<note n="g" place="margin">Joh. 10.1, 2.</note>, but may be ſaid to be as directly from God, as Monarchy is it ſelf; though he be otherwiſe never ſo much <hi>Tyrannus exercitio,</hi> as grand a Tyrant in practice as King <hi>Saul,</hi> or as much a Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then as King <hi>Cyrus</hi>
               <note n="h" place="margin">Iſa. 45.1.</note>: <hi>'Tis by God that Kings Reign,</hi> as well as by him that
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:58923:9"/>
               <hi>Princes decree Juſtice.</hi> Proverbs 8.15.</p>
            <p>There are no judgments, nor evil of puniſhments in any Nation or City un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the Sun, but the Lord hath a hand in them all<note n="i" place="margin">Amos 3.6. 2 King. 33.</note>. Therefore to bring about thoſe ends without putting himſelf to the expence of a Miracle, he not only (ſometimes) takes away Religious Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, and in their room permits Uſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pers; but alſo anoints bad Vicege<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents under him, as well as good: As is evident, by the examples of <hi>Saul, Nebuchadnezzar, Jehu,</hi> and others<note n="k" place="margin">Jer. 25.9. 2 King. 10.30.</note>, whom (though as ſuch) when they have once accompliſhed the ends for which they were ordained, he either takes away in his Wrath, as at firſt he gave them in his Anger<note n="l" place="margin">Hoſ. 13.11.</note>, or elſe re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerves them for a greater judgment to come; yet as they are his Vicegerents, appointed to execute his Wrath and pleaſure upon Offenders, he hath in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veſted them, both with a Soveraign Title to rule, and a Soveraign Power to maintain it. Headſhip and Prerogatives are ſo firmly united together in the Lord, and the King, that the one can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not poſſibly ſubſiſt without the other.</p>
            <pb n="15" facs="tcp:58923:9"/>
            <p n="1">1. From hence we may ſee the great abſurdity of <hi>Cromwell</hi> the Uſurper, (that Notorious Changer, Curſed Hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pocrite, and Deceiver) in ſepara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting Soveraign Title from Sove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raign Power, which the Lord in himſelf and the King hath thus firmly joyned together. The guilt of his Conſcience would not ſuffer him to aſſume the name of a King, No, nor his Diabo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lical policy neither; leſt he ſhould ſeem to favour that Kingly Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment which he had deſtroyed: But to maintain his Uſurpation of the Royal due, and the favour of his Fanaticks, he would change the name and be called their Protector: yet his ambition would not ſuffer him to neglect the uſurpation of the Kings Power: For which cauſe he and his, moſt abuſively granted the King to have the name of a King ſtill, if ſo be he would be ſo contented without the power; becauſe they knew, without that, the King would be (as was ſaid of <hi>Pompey</hi>) but <hi>magni nominis um<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bra,</hi> the ſhadow of a King with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the ſubſtance; yea, to be a titu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lary<note n="†" place="margin">
                  <hi>Joſep. Antiq.</hi> l. 15. telleth us, that <hi>Marcus Antonius</hi> being urged by his <hi>Dalilah, Cleopatra,</hi> to call <hi>Herod</hi> to an account, replyed, that it was not fair, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, to demand of a King an account of what was done in his Government; for ſo he would not be a King.</note>
               <pb n="16" facs="tcp:58923:10"/>King, would be a King no more in reality, than a King in a Play. Therefore it is obſervable, that <hi>Mephi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boſheth</hi> (like a True Loyaliſt) called <hi>David</hi> not only by the name of King, to ſhew his Soveraign Title to rule; but alſo by the name of Lord (ſaying <hi>My Lord the King</hi>) to ſhew his Sove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raign Power to command, 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 19.30.</p>
            <p n="2">2. From hence it alſo is, that (by our moſt wiſe and Royal Maſter) we are here enjoyned to fear the Lord and the King; becauſe power, the founda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of fear, belongeth to them both: To the Lord as God the great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt Supreme, and to the King as his Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter and Vicegerent.<note n="m" place="margin">Rom. 13.4.</note> Therefore St. <hi>Paul</hi> joyneth fear and power, ſaying, <hi>Wilt thou then not be afraid of the power? Rom.</hi> 13.3.</p>
            <p>And to ſpeak all in a word, The reaſon wherefore the fear of the Lord, and the fear of the King are here joyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed and enjoyned together, is, for an <hi>exegeſis</hi> or expoſition one of the other;
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:58923:10"/>to ſhew that he that is truly Godly, and fears the Lord, is alſo a True Loya<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſt, and fears the King; and that he is only a True Loyaliſt and fears the King, who is truly godly and fears the Lord: True Godlineſs and Loyalty, the fear of the Lord, and the fear of the King, like <hi>Hippocrates</hi>'s Twins live and die together. Godlineſs without Loy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alty is not true, but Phariſaical; and Loyalty without godlineſs is only no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minal, falſe and adulterate.</p>
            <p>Now as the fear of the Lord, and the fear of the King is the ſame in kind, though not in degree; becauſe the fear of the King is terminated in the fear of the Lord: So it is meant not of any legal, or ſervile fear, derived from the lower ſpring of Nature; (which it would be, if it were grounded only up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on their Power:) But of a pure filial and Evangelical fear, derived from the upper ſpring of grace; grounded not only upon power, but upon cordial love and duty. As the true Godli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſt fears to diſobey and diſhonour the Lord, not legally, only for the ſake of his power; but filially, out of pure love, as an obedient child fears
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:58923:11"/>a kind Father<note n="n" place="margin">Deut. 10.12. Gal. 4.7. Heb. 12.6, 7, 8, 9.</note> ſo the true Loyaliſt fears to offend his King, not ſlaviſhly, only for the ſake of his power, as the nominal Loyaliſt doth for fear of puniſhment; but Evangelically, out of a filial fear and perfect love to God. Which (as St. <hi>John</hi> ſaith) <hi>caſteth out</hi> all ſlaviſh and tormenting <hi>fear</hi>
               <note n="o" place="margin">1 John 4.18.</note>. In a word, the true Loyaliſt looks upon his King, not humanely, as one that hath only power and authority to ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rifie and puniſh him, if he do evil; but ſpiritually, and abſtractedly, as he is Gods Miniſter and Vicegerent, ordained for that very end: And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he fears and ſubjects himſelf to him of neceſſity, not only for Wrath, but alſo for Conſcience ſake<note n="p" place="margin">Rom. 13.4, 5.</note>.</p>
            <p>Thus you ſee the nature and quality of fear; which makes the difference between the true Loyaliſt and the falſe.</p>
            <p>But now we muſt conſider, that as a filial and Evangelical fear, (being as it were the Royal Head, the <hi>primum mobile,</hi> or firſt mover in all the Spheres of Religion<note n="q" place="margin">Pro. 9.10. Job 28.28.</note>,) doth in its progreſs pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce, 1. True honour to the King, and that both of eſteem and mainte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance; and, 2. With true honour, all
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:58923:11"/>the parts of obedience<note n="r" place="margin">Eccleſiaſtes 12.13.</note>: So theſe du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties and commandments are counter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feited by the Devil, Gods Ape; either by corrupting the hearts of his Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren with a ſervile fear, or by changing himſelf in them into an Angel of light: In all which the True Loyaliſt will alſo be diſcovered from the falſe, by the difference of their originals.</p>
            <p>For your better underſtanding whereof, take this for a general Rule: That the True Loyaliſt makes the fear of God the groundwork of all duties to his King; he eyes God in all, and doth all for his ſake, and to his glory: Whereas the counterfeit Loyaliſt doth in all only eye, either humane powers, or his own ſafety, ſiniſter ends, or vain glory.</p>
            <p>As, 1. The True Loyaliſt is one that honoureth his King, not only for the fear of his power and authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, and the Penal Laws of the Land, as the nominal Loyaliſt doth; but out of love and fear to God, becauſe ſo is his will and Commandment<note n="ſ" place="margin">1 Pet. 2.15.</note>, in which reſpect St. <hi>Peter</hi> hath joyned them both together, ſaying, <hi>fear God, honour the King</hi>
               <note n="t" place="margin">1 Pet. 2.17,</note>.</p>
            <pb n="20" facs="tcp:58923:12"/>
            <p n="2">2. Though a Kings Majeſty and Grandeur be the foundation of humane honour, as well as his power is of a ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vile fear; yet the True Loyaliſt ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours his King, not for the ſake of them alone, meerly as they are humane, as the Carnal Loyaliſt doth; but as his King receives them from God, (his only Lord and Maſter) and in that reſpect are impreſſes of the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine; Yea, and (in regard of his ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>premacy) Prerogatives too annexed to his headſhip.</p>
            <p n="3">3. The True Loyaliſt honoureth his King, not for any ſelf-intereſt, or by<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>end of his own, as the time-ſerving, ſelf-ſeeking, Jeſuitical Loyaliſt doth; but ſtill only for the Lords ſake, becauſe he is his Miniſter and Vicegerent.</p>
            <p>Laſtly, The True Loyaliſt honoureth his King, not in word only, as lip-ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and heart-hollow <hi>Phariſees</hi> honour the Lord<note n="u" place="margin">Mat. 15.8, 9.</note>, but <hi>ex animo,</hi> ſincerely, from his very heart, in deed and in truth,<note place="margin">1 John 3.18.</note> for duty and Conſcience ſake; becauſe God hath commanded him to <hi>give honour to whom honour is due</hi>
               <note n="w" place="margin">Rom. 13.7.</note>.</p>
            <pb n="21" facs="tcp:58923:12"/>
            <p>And no marvel; for thus the True Loyaliſt honoureth all his other Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernours, both in Church and State.</p>
            <p n="1">1. He highly eſteemeth in love all his ſpiritual Governours, both Biſhops and Paſtors of the Church; not for their perſons<note n="x" place="margin">Rom 2.11. James 2.9. Jud. 16.</note>, but for their works ſake; not becauſe they have the rule over him, but becauſe they are over him in the Lord; and are Ambaſſadors for Chriſt, to admoniſh, and <hi>beſeech</hi> him <hi>in his ſtead to be reconciled to God</hi>
               <note n="y" place="margin">2 Cor. 5.20. 1 Theſ. 5.12, 13. Phil. 2.29. Heb. 13.7, 17. Rom. 10.15.</note>.</p>
            <p n="2">2. He much honoureth too all Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrates and Civil Governours (according to their ſeveral orders and Degrees) whom his King hath put in authority under him in the State; not for their powers ſake, but ſtill for the Lords ſake, becauſe they have received their power from him, to execute his <hi>wrath upon evil doers, and for the praiſe of them that do well</hi>
               <note n="z" place="margin">Rom. 13.4. 1 Pet. 2.14, 16.</note>.</p>
            <p>How much more then doth he ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour his King, who is a perſon not only Civil, but Sacred too; Civil, in reſpect he is not to intermeddle with the Holy Function of a Miniſter, any more than King <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>zziah</hi> was to invade the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Office of a Prieſt<note n="a" place="margin">2 Chron. 26.18.</note>, or we are to
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:58923:13"/>meddle with them that are given to Change: But Sacred, in reſpect he is Gods Deputy and Vicegerent; or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dained under him Supreme Head and Governour over all both in Church and State; as well the higheſt of the Clergy, as the loweſt of the Laity; God himſelf always held the Scepter above the Miter to defend it; and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore King <hi>David</hi> calls himſelf expreſly the Lord of <hi>Zadok</hi> the High Prieſt<note n="b" place="margin">1 King. 1.33.</note>.</p>
            <p>Yea in a word, the True Loyaliſt conſiders that as his Lord God him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf is the common Father of us all<note n="c" place="margin">Mal. 1.6.</note>, ſo hath he appointed the King his Vicege<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent to be <hi>Pater patriae,</hi> the Father of his Country: And therefore he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpects him accordingly above all, as an obedient Son doth his Father; that ſo he may neither ſtand in the light of his own honour, by diſhonouring his Lord God, in contemning in his King the Image of his authority<note n="d" place="margin">1 Sam. 2.30.</note>; nor withſtand his promiſe of long life, either in this World, or the World to come, or both; by breaking the fifth Commandment.</p>
            <p>This is enough to let us ſee that True godlineſs and Loyalty, True Loyalty and goldineſs, the fear of the Lord,
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:58923:13"/>and the fear of the King go hand in hand together, both in the Affirmative, and in the Negative. 1. The conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence <hi>à majori ad minus</hi> is undeniable in the Affirmative, He that doth the greater duty in Religion, will not ſtick to do the leſſer; <hi>quiſquis Deum timet, etiam Regibus honorem habebit,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Pet. 2.17. 1 Sam. 8.8. &amp; 12.18.</note> (ſaith <hi>Calvin</hi>) he that feareth God, will al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo honour his King. And, 2. The conſequence <hi>à minori ad majus</hi> is as un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deniable in the Negative, He that re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſes to do the leſſer duty in Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, to be ſure will not do the greater; he that will not fear and honour his King, no man can be ſo ſottiſh to think that he feareth God. Therefore what St. <hi>John</hi> ſaith concerning our love to God and our brother<note n="e" place="margin">1 Joh. 4.20.</note>, I may as truly ſay of our fear to God and our King: If a man ſay I fear God, and diſho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noureth his King, he is a lyer, no leſs than a Quaker; for he that honoureth not his King, who is viſible; how can he fear God, whom no man can ſee and live<note n="f" place="margin">Exod. 33.20.</note>?</p>
            <p>From hence are juſtly condemned two ſorts of men amongſt us.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Thoſe that dare preſume to ſtile themſelves the Godly Party, and yet
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:58923:14"/>refuſe all Loyalty to their Prince: That pretend very much to fear the Lord, and yet are not afraid to diſhonour their King. And who are ſuch, but only our Phariſaical Puritans and Fanaticks? Time was (we know) when thoſe Godly-gulls and Holy-cheats made the deluded people of this Kingdom to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve that he did fear God the moſt, who did the leaſt honour his King; that he was the moſt godly who would offer the moſt affronts and indignities to his Prince: Nothing was counted with them a greater piece of Piety, than to ſtir up the people againſt their Soveraign; by raiſing jealouſies, and caſting abroad rude and ſcandalous Pamphlets almoſt every day to libel and diſgrace him: Which (as that Holy Martyr, King <hi>Charles</hi> 1. Himſelf ſaith in his Divine meditations,<note n="*" place="margin">ΕΙΚΩΝ ΒΑΣΙΛΙΚΗ</note> that Gol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den Manual) like ſparks in great con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flagrations, did fly up and down to ſet all places on Fire. Yea he was thought to be the moſt Religious, who was the beſt Incendiary to ſet a well ordered Kingdom in a Flame;<note place="margin">Hiſt. of <hi>Indepen.</hi> Compleat. Part. 1. <hi>p.</hi> 55.</note> and could cheat the giddy multitude the moſt into Rebellion: no Ambaſſador to him that was the greateſt Herauld
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:58923:14"/>of War, and like a <hi>Geneva</hi> Bull, could roar out loudeſt from the Pulpit, Up ye Fanaticks, Arm, Arm; ye are the only Godly party, who have as much right to Rob the King and his Loyal Subjects, as the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> had to ſpoil the <hi>Egyptians</hi>
               <note n="g" place="margin">Exod. 3.22.</note>, all that you can find is your own. But only you muſt not think that you (like ravening Wolves) can make a prey of their poſſeſſions, unleſs you hide the deſigns of your pride and cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>touſneſs under Sheeps clothing<note n="h" place="margin">Mat. 7.15.</note>. If therefore you have any lingering mind after the wages of unrighteouſneſs<note n="i" place="margin">2 Pet. 2.15.</note>, as we know you have, as any <hi>Balaams</hi> of us all; then you muſt <hi>deal wiſely</hi>
               <note n="k" place="margin">Exod. 1.10.</note>, imitate our Language and behaviour to the life; know no other godlineſs but your eſpouſed gain<note n="l" place="margin">1 Tim. 6.5.</note>, and make Religion but a ſtalking Horſe to Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bellion: regard not the voice of Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience, leſt it interrupt you; but yet be ſure to carry it always about you, that it may be ready to further your ſiniſter ends and proceedings, with its out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward ſhews and varniſh: Be ye as Hypocritical in raiſing a Rebellion againſt your King, as ambitious <hi>Abſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lom</hi> was when he raiſed a conſpiracy againſt his Father<note n="m" place="margin">2 Sam. 15.</note>; though like <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vid</hi>
               <pb n="26" facs="tcp:58923:15"/>he <hi>be a man after Gods own heart,</hi> yet pretend ye that there are ſome grievous abuſes in Church and State, which if you were made Rulers and Judges, your integrity would quickly remedy: that ſo your Godly party be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſtrengthned by the ſtoln hearts of others, you may accompliſh your am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitious and covetous ends the more aſſuredly, to the temporal ruin and downfal of your King and Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>O! Tell this not in Gath, nor pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh it in the ſtreets of Askalon: leſt the Daughters of Philiſtins rejoyce; leſt the Daughters of the uncircumciſed triumph</hi>
               <note n="n" place="margin">2 Sam. 1.20.</note>. For time was then too, when theſe curſed <hi>Cains</hi> and <hi>Amalekites</hi> did all of them combine together, and were <hi>not afraid to ſtretch forth united hands to deſtroy the Lords anointed</hi>
               <note n="o" place="margin">ver. 14.</note>. And yet forſooth, they pretended that it was out of fear to God, to promote his Cauſe, and his Glory. Yea, they thought they did God good ſervice to kill their King, and make him a glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious Martyr, for God and his Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try; as Chriſt our Prince of peace foretold his Diſciples of the like that
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:58923:15"/>was to happen unto them, to make them ſtable in their perſecutions<note n="p" place="margin">John 16.1, 2,</note>. For as theſe Rebels did this Barba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous, Villainous, and unparallel'd act, becauſe they had no ſaving know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of God the Father, and Chriſt God-man the Son<note n="q" place="margin">ver. 3.</note>: So our Martyred Soveraign, like King <hi>David</hi> in all his troubles, (though both had their fail<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings) demonſtrated himſelf to be a true Diſciple of Chriſt indeed; for notwithſtanding all the various modes whereby theſe proud and impudent wretches had him <hi>in great deriſion, yet he declined not from Gods Law</hi>
               <note n="r" place="margin">Pſ. 119.51.</note>.</p>
            <p>But the guilty Conſciences of theſe Parricides (the true ſeed of <hi>Corah</hi> and his Complices, <hi>two hundred and fifty Princes of the Aſſembly,</hi> all of them Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament men, of their own Election<note n="ſ" place="margin">Numb. 16.</note>,) told them that the murder of their Soveraign was not enough to keep thoſe Places, Dignities and Power, which before they had uſurped from him, unleſs they barred all his Heirs from ſucceeding: Therefore though they conſiſted of two juntoes, and were divided into two adverſe Factions, (the one <hi>Presbyterians,</hi> who (to uſe
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:58923:16"/>their own diſtinction) murdered the King in his Political Capacity; and the other, <hi>Independents,</hi> who mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred him in his natural:) Yet they moſt firmly agreed in making an Act<note n="*" place="margin">Hiſt. <hi>Inde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pend.</hi> Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleat. <hi>Part</hi> 2. <hi>p.</hi> 140. &amp; <hi>p.</hi> 241. &amp; <hi>Part</hi> 4. <hi>p.</hi> 22.</note> for the Dethroning of his Highneſs <hi>James</hi> Duke of <hi>York,</hi> and all the Roy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al Family, not ſparing ſo much as the Kingly Office it ſelf: Eſpecially therein, they united themſelves toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther againſt the next Heir to the Crown, (our now moſt gracious Lord and King) as unanimouſly, and as ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemnly as thoſe two deadly Enemies, <hi>Herod</hi> and <hi>Pilate,</hi> were made friends againſt Chriſt<note n="t" place="margin">Luk. 23.12.</note>: They hunted him from place to place for his life, as <hi>Saul</hi> King <hi>David, like a Partridge upon the Mountains</hi>
               <note n="u" place="margin">1 Sam. 26.20.</note>, moſt inhumanely ſaying (like the Husbandmen in the Parable<note n="w" place="margin">Luk. 20.14.</note>,) <hi>this is the Heir, come let us kill him, that the inheritance may be ours.</hi> Yet they had the impudence to pretend that all was but expedient for the good and welfare of the whole Nation, the Glory of God, the ſafety, and liberty of the people. <hi>Salus populi,</hi> is the common pretence of all Rebels; <hi>Caiaphas</hi> pretended the ſame for Crucifying Chriſt, <hi>it is expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dient</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>that one man die,</hi> (mean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:58923:16"/>Jeſus) <hi>and that the whole Nation periſh not</hi>
               <note n="x" place="margin">John 11.50.</note>. And <hi>Cromwell</hi> too pretended the like for the murder of our Soveraign, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs he die, the whole nation muſt pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh: but as that which was pretended to be ſo much for the ſafety of the <hi>Jews,</hi> brought a fearful deſtruction upon them: ſo this which was pretended to be ſo much for the Glory of God, and the Liberty of the People, hath been ſeen by woeful experience for twelve years together to have been the very bane and ruin of the Nation: When was there ever more ſlavery and bondage in the State? And when more Anarchy and confuſion in the Church? <hi>Munſter</hi> it ſelf ſaw but the Prologue to our Tragedy.</p>
            <p>But to maintain this their Uſurpati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, they ſtill perſiſted in their old Hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pocritical zeal, and re-inforced it too, with ſuch wonderful ſhews of godli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, that if it were poſſible they would have perſwaded the very Elect them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves that they were really a Godly Party, true fearers of God indeed<note n="y" place="margin">Mat. 24.24.</note>, the more they had a mind to diſhonour the King, the more they pretended to fear the Lord: How many Phariſaical pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, and ſuperſtitious Preachings were
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:58923:17"/>made to devour the Poſſeſſions of all True Loyaliſts, even to the houſes of poor Widows and the Fatherleſs<note n="z" place="margin">Mat. 23.14.</note>? How many ſad Countenances and Bul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruſh necks, to trumpet out the praiſe of their Saintſhip? And how many Hypocritical ſighs and groans too, to blow up all Royalty and Loyalty, and cheat the people into Rebellion? All which, either more or leſs, was evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent in moſt, but eſpecially in <hi>Cook,</hi> that Famous or rather Infamous Preacher, ſigher and groaner, and in <hi>Cromwell</hi> too, the Head of their Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bellion,<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Boſcobel:</hi> or the Compleat Hiſtory of his Sacred Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſties moſt mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raculous pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervation af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the Battel of <hi>Worceſter,</hi> 3 <hi>Sept.</hi> 1651. Part. 1. <hi>p.</hi> 18.</note> who (when at <hi>Worceſter</hi> fight) he had marched over <hi>Powick</hi> Bridge a conſiderable number of his men, to fight againſt his King; ſaid, (in his Hypocritical way) The Lord of Hoſts be with you: That ſo the poor ignorant and credulous Rabble (who knew no other cauſe but their pay, why they were gathered together, any more than the followers of <hi>Deme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trius</hi>
               <note n="a" place="margin">Acts 19.40.</note>, or thoſe two hundred that fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed <hi>Abſolom</hi> out of <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> in their ſimplicity<note n="b" place="margin">2 Sam. 15.11.</note>; thinking that it was Gods cauſe which they were ingaged in, might be the more animated in their Rebellion.</p>
            <pb n="31" facs="tcp:58923:17"/>
            <p>But it is no wonder that theſe Rebels and Whetſtones of Rebellion ſhould, thus diſhonour the King, when as (for all their ſpecious pretences) they were not afraid to diſhonour the Lord himſelf; not only indirectly, through the ſides of his Vicegerent; but imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diately and directly in himſelf: for time was then alſo, when they did moſt impudently prophane Gods San<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctuary, the Houſe of Prayer, <hi>the place where his honour dwelleth</hi>
               <note n="c" place="margin">Pſ. 26.8.</note>, they ſet up the abomination of deſolation in the Holy Place, where it ought not to ſtand<note n="d" place="margin">Mat 24.15. Hiſt. <hi>Independ.</hi> Compleat. <hi>Part.</hi> 1. <hi>p.</hi> 170.</note>. Sir <hi>William Brereton,</hi> Colo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nel General for the <hi>Cheſhire</hi> Forces, having given him the Arch-Biſhops Houſe and Lands at <hi>Croiden</hi> (with <hi>Caſhobery,</hi> and other Lands of the Lord <hi>Capels</hi> worth 2000 <hi>l. per an.</hi>) for ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice done and to be done, againſt the King and Kingdom, reformed the Chapel (there) into a Kitchin. This was a goodly reformation, fitting with his Stomach as well as his Religion. But <hi>O. Cromwell</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">Hiſt. <hi>Inde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pend.</hi> Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleat. <hi>Part.</hi> 2. <hi>p.</hi> 34, 35.</note> (in proportion to his ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>limity) therein went beyond him, when he and his reformed St. <hi>Pauls</hi> from the Church of God, to a Den of Thieves, Stable of Horſes, and Brothel
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:58923:18"/>of Whores: out of envy (I ſuppoſe) to the King, becauſe it was the Head and Royal Church of the Kingdom. And to cover his Prophaneneſs, he would moſt ridiculouſly ſay his Prayers a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt his Horſes: And <hi>Lambert</hi> and his crue did not come far behind him, when he threatened to pluck down Churches for Edification, as they actu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally did the Kings houſe at <hi>Holmby.</hi> And I may add too (what hereafter I ſhall have better occaſion to ſpeak of in their changing) that they then alſo thought it a great piece of Refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation, to diſhonour God publickly, not only by doing their Carnal and Worldly buſineſs in his Sanctuary; but alſo by being moſt irreverently and unmannerly covered (even before their betters) in his Holy Ordinan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces. And O! that I could not ſay, that even now time is, that this ſin of Prophaneneſs is ſtill extant in ſome, too many amongſt us; which without all doubt plainly declares (nothing more than) that they are ſtill infected with their old Common-Wealth principles. They are apt to complain of the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liques of Popery, becauſe they want Wiſdom to diſcern <hi>the precious from
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:58923:18"/>the vile</hi>
               <note n="e" place="margin">Jer. 15.19.</note>. But I wiſh we had not juſter cauſe to complain of the reliques of Fanaticiſm; there be too many dregs of it lye at the bottom of this Nation, which if they ſhould be once ſtirred, before they be refined, it is much to be feared, that they would quick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly diſcover themſelves on the top: We have Church Fanaticks as well as Church Papiſts amongſt us.</p>
            <p>You therefore, that are infected with the gangrene of Fanaticiſm, with the leven or doctrine of theſe Phanatical Scribes and Phariſees<note n="f" place="margin">Mat. 16.6, 12.</note>, it is behoofeful that you be very careful to purge it out from your Conſciences, by a timely true and unfeigned repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance; that you may not corrupt others with evil manners, but become a new Lump your ſelves<note n="g" place="margin">1 Cor. 5.7.</note>, to win and confirm thoſe in the truth that want it<note n="h" place="margin">Luk. 22.32.</note>. As Doctor <hi>Lee,</hi> Colonel <hi>Richard</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Boſcobel:</hi> Or the Compleat Hiſt. of his Sacred Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſties moſt mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raculous pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervation af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the Battel of <hi>Worceſter.</hi> Part. 1. <hi>p.</hi> 16.</note> 
               <hi>Ingolsby</hi> (who ſince his Converſion was created Knight of the <hi>Bath,</hi> at his Majeſties Coronation) and other real Converts have done in the ſame reformation. This is a thing not to be dallied with, but to be ſeriouſly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidered
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:58923:19"/>in time, and the rather becauſe evil habits are as hardly forſaken as eaſily taken; unleſs you take it for a thing indifferent (as ſome of your Predeceſſors have done) whether you are for ever happy or miſerable: Luke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warm Chriſtians, partly Fanaticks and partly Loyaliſts and Confor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſts; that like a trembling Needle between two Loadſtones incline to both and neither, are as loathſome to God as the <hi>Laodiceans</hi>
               <note n="i" place="margin">Revel. 3.14, 15, 16.</note>. You have ſometime taken an Oath to be conſtant to true Loyalty and Conformity, and what will you not fear your Oaths<note n="k" place="margin">Eccleſiaſtes 8.2.</note>? <hi>O remember therefore from whence you are fallen, repent and do the firſt Works,</hi> that God may have nothing againſt you<note n="l" place="margin">Revel. 2.4, 5.</note>. You cannot complan of any want of means for your recovery and reſtauration. You have the Scriptures, where the ſame God that hath taught you to fear him, hath alſo (in the ſame breath) taught you to fear and honour the King: and what will you not believe him? who is ſo much truth it ſelf by nature that he cannot lye<note n="m" place="margin">Tit. 1.2.</note>? and there he hath alſo taught you, that his worſhip cannot conſiſt without honour, nor the Churches of the Saints
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:58923:19"/>without peace and order. And what ſhould I mention what means you have alſo had from the examples of well ordered Churches, both Clergy and Laity, when as the King himſelf, Gods Miniſter and Vice<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerent, your head and Soveraign, hath not only eſtabliſhed the ſame accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to his Lords commandment; but hath alſo taught you by his own pious example, how to reverence Chriſt your Head by uncovering your heads in his Church, Holy Houſe or San<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctuary. And what will ye be worſe than all the World beſides? <hi>Regis ad exemplum totus componitur orbis.</hi> The whole world ſtrives who ſhall the moſt follow the example of Kings. I know indeed that the major part of men in the World, are more apt to follow them in bad examples than in good, becauſe they are not of God, but of the world, which lieth in wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>edneſs<note n="n" place="margin">1 Joh. 5.19.</note>. But I could heartily wiſh (if it were Gods good pleaſure) that even the whole world would imitate our King in this pious example, and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cordingly thoſe that are of his Domini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, ſhew their ſubjection to him, as he
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:58923:20"/>therein ſhews his ſubjection to the Lord.</p>
            <p>Not but the mode of paying reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence to God is indifferent (accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the various States, cuſtoms, and manners of Nations) before it be ordained in the Church as it would be indifferent whether we pay reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vence to God by putting off the Glove, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> (if there were any ſuch cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtom) or whether by putting off the ſhoes, as the <hi>Jews;</hi> or whether by putting off the Hat, as we Chriſtians. It is free for every Nation to do what they think fit in ſuch caſes, ſo long as they keep to Gods general rule of order and decency<note n="o" place="margin">1 Cor. 14.40.</note> (which binds now to uncover the head, and is therefore ordained) but as for the reverence it ſelf, it never was indifferent, but is always neceſſary to be expreſſed by ſome Rite or other, as being that without which Gods honour cannot ſubſiſt, which (as his word) is more durable than Heaven or Earth<note n="p" place="margin">Mat. 24.35.</note>.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Quorſum vero haec?</hi> from whence then is this diſobedience and prophaneneſs of theirs? You may quickly gueſs it;
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:58923:20"/>that it is either becauſe they read not the word of God at all; or if they read it, read it but curſorily in a canting tone, out of vain glory: Or ſuppoſe ſome think themſelves as lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned as the <hi>Jeſuits</hi> themſelves, yet that will but aggravate their torments in Hell<note n="q" place="margin">Luk. 12.48.</note>, and ſo much the more manifeſt their blindneſs and want of faith: For ſurely had they the eye of Faith, to behold God in his Temple, who is in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſible, they could not chuſe but re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verence and honour ſo great a Majeſty, and if their great knowledge in the Scriptures (which they pretend to) were ſanctified unto them, then they would never perſwade their ſeduced proſelytes to believe that that is Gods ſervice wherein he is the moſt diſho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noured, and that that is true Religion which conſiſteth in the contradiction of his Laws and Ordinances: For what ſaith St. <hi>James, If any man among you ſeem to be Religious, and bridleth not his tongue, but deceiveth his own heart,</hi> (that is, ſpeaketh againſt his own knowledge and Conſcience) <hi>this mans Religion is vain. But pure Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, and undefiled before God and the Father,</hi> (ſaith he) is this (not to make
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:58923:21"/>any, eſpecially your Queen a Widow, and her Heirs Fatherleſs, but) <hi>to vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſit the Fatherleſs and Widows in their affliction, and to keep himſelf unſpotted from the World.</hi> James 1.26, 27. Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion doth not licenſe men to ſpeak and do what they liſt; it hath its name <hi>à religando,</hi> from binding, <hi>quòd hoc vin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culo Deo religati ſumus,</hi> ſaith <hi>Lactan.</hi> Becauſe by it, as by a bond we are bound to God: Whereby all our mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers are bound to their good behavi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our: Our hands from being ſtretched forth againſt the Lords anointed<note n="r" place="margin">2 Sam. 1.14.</note>, our tongues from deſpiſing, or ſpeaking evil againſt him; the Spirit of God puts the brand of the Sons of <hi>Belial</hi> upon them that preſume to do it<note n="ſ" place="margin">1 Sam. 10.27.</note>, ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther by reproaching his footſteeps, or proceedings<note n="t" place="margin">Pſ. 89.51.</note>, or by controuling him in any of his ways or actions, <hi>who may ſay to a King</hi> (ſaith <hi>Solomon</hi>) <hi>what doſt thou</hi>
               <note n="u" place="margin">Eccleſiaſtes 8.4.</note>? And <hi>is it fit</hi> (ſaith <hi>Job</hi>) <hi>to ſay to a King, thou art wicked? And to Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, ye are ungodly</hi>
               <note n="w" place="margin">Job 34.18.</note>? and what ſhould I ſay more? our very hearts are bound by our Religion from curſing or wiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing evil to the Lords Vicegerent: <hi>Curſe not the King,</hi> (ſaith <hi>Solomon</hi>) <hi>no not in thy thought or Conſcience</hi>
               <note n="x" place="margin">Eccleſiaſtes 10.20.</note>.</p>
            <pb n="39" facs="tcp:58923:21"/>
            <p>Yet the Prophet <hi>Iſaiah</hi> ſpeaketh of a deſperate generation of men, that <hi>Curſe their King &amp; their God, and look upward</hi>
               <note n="y" place="margin">Iſaiah 8.21.</note>. Of whom the Prophet ſpeaketh this I dare not poſitively affirm: But this I may ſafely ſay, the words agree ſo exactly with theſe that ſtile themſelves the Godly Party, as if they were the very men pointed at in this Prophecy; for who have been more infamous than they, for <hi>Curſing their King and their God, and for looking upwards</hi> withal, to cover their wickedneſs with the vail of Hypocriſie? They are not only that proud and ſupercilious generation (which <hi>Solomon</hi> ſpeaks of) <hi>that have lofty eyes, and eye-lids lifted up</hi>
               <note n="z" place="margin">Prov. 30.13.</note>. But alſo that Rebellious Generation (which he ſpeaks of too) that curſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth both their Natural Father, and the King, the Father of their Country; and doth not bleſs their Mother, nor their Queen<note n="a" place="margin">ver. 11.</note>. Yea, and finally, that Hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pocritical generation, (which follows next) that are pure in their own eyes (from whence they are called Puritans) and yet are not waſhed from their filthineſs<note n="b" place="margin">ver. 12.</note>.</p>
            <pb n="40" facs="tcp:58923:22"/>
            <p>But O, ye Puritans, <hi>be not righteous over-much, neither make your ſelves over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe, why ſhould you deſtroy your ſelves</hi>
               <note n="c" place="margin">Eccleſiaſtes 7.16.</note>? I know a man cannot be too Righteous, or too wiſe, ſo long as he lives ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the rule of Gods word; but <hi>Omne nimium vertitur in vitium,</hi> every extream degenerates into a vice; if a man ſhoots at rovers in his Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, too much on the one hand by prophaneneſs, or too much on the other by ſuperſtition, he will never hit the mark: Much leſs if he be pure only in his own eyes, and make him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf <hi>over Righteous, and over wiſe;</hi> out of ſpiritual pride and vain glory, or on purpoſe to advance his own ends by deception: For ſo he will demon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate himſelf to be a perfect Emiſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of Satan, who when he intends to deceive the moſt, appears not as a Devil, but as an Angel of light<note n="d" place="margin">2 Cor. 11.13, 14.</note>.</p>
            <p>In a word therefore, <hi>Let him that thinketh he ſtandeth,</hi> (or in more ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of ſenſe, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, he that ſeems to himſelf to ſtand) <hi>take heed leſt he fall</hi>
               <note n="e" place="margin">1 Cor. 10.12.</note>, and you that have a name that you are alive, and yet are dead,
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:58923:22"/>as having been formerly ſeduced by their ſeeming ſanctity, and yet are ſtill infected with the leven of their Phanaticiſm, let me adviſe you once again (before it be too late) that ye purge it out by a true and timely repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance: And that ye be watchful for the future to ſtrengthen thoſe good and Loyal principles, which yet remain, and are ready to die; that your works may <hi>be found perfect before God</hi>
               <note n="f" place="margin">Rev. 3.1, 2.</note>. Have a care that you do not with-hold from God his due of reverence, leſt he de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroy you for defiling his Holy Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple<note n="g" place="margin">1 Cor. 3.17.</note>, much rather beware that you do not mock him<note n="h" place="margin">Gal. 6.7.</note> by with-holding from the King his due of fear and ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour, under a pretence of fearing him, leſt your portion at length be the ſame with the Hypocrites<note n="i" place="margin">Mat 24.51. Job 8.13.</note>. But as you have been taught by St. <hi>John</hi> in the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, concerning the love of God and our brother, forget not to fulfil this Royal and Loyal commandment in the Text, that he who feareth God, <hi>fear and honour the King</hi> alſo<note n="k" place="margin">1 Joh. 4.21.</note>. For as they that deſpiſe God, ſhall be lightly eſteemed, ſo he will honour them that honour him<note n="l" place="margin">1 Sam. 2.30.</note>.</p>
            <pb n="42" facs="tcp:58923:23"/>
            <p n="2">2. Thoſe are here condemned alſo, that would (forſooth) be counted great Loyaliſts, and yet are notorious Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bels againſt the Lord himſelf, <hi>the King of Kings:</hi> That pretend to be highly for the King, great honourers of his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty; and yet plainly ſhew by as highly debaucht lives and examples that they have no fear of God before their eyes<note n="m" place="margin">Pſ. 36.1. Rom. 3.18. Gen. 20.11.</note>. They never boaſt of their Loyalty more, than when they are elevated in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to ſo many petty Kings in their eſteem, or rather are really the greateſt Lords and Maſters of miſ-rule: They never pretend more ſtrongly to be for the King, than when they are moſt migh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty to drink Wine, and men of the greateſt ſtrength to mingle ſtrong drink<note n="n" place="margin">Iſa. 5.</note>: If a ſober man chance to come into the company of theſe Ranters and Ruffins, they will ſtraight cenſure him for a Round-head; and if he refuſe to drink the Kings health ſo deep and ſo of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten as they would have him, they will as readily cry out, God damn them, he is a Fanatick, though they ſee he doth not refuſe it in a ſober way as the Kings health, becauſe he honours the King; but only as a cup of exceſs, becauſe he alſo fears the Lord. Theſe are thoſe of
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:58923:23"/>whom St. <hi>Peter</hi> ſpeaks, who hold it not ſufficient that they have heretofore wrought the will of man, when they were Gentiles; but ſtill walk in laſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viouſneſs, luſts, exceſs of Wine, Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vellings, Banquetings, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> wherein they think it ſtrange that you (who accompliſh the end of Chriſts ſuffer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings, in walking according to the will of God) ſhould be ſuch enemies to your own preſent enjoyments, as not to run with them to the ſame exceſs of Riot, and therefore ſpeak evil of you<note n="o" place="margin">1 Pet. 4.1, 2, 3, 4.</note>.</p>
            <p>Where then is their great Loyal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty which they ſo much boaſt of? You ſee what goodly Loyaliſts they are: they have only the name of the Loyaliſts, and that's all; they want all the ingredients of a Chriſtian, which (as you have heard) conſtitute the being of a True Loyaliſt: <hi>The fear of the Lord and the King</hi> always go toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in the True Loyaliſt, as well as the True Godliliſt: It is vain for men to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend to fear God, without honouring the King; and it is as vain too, to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend to honour the King without fear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing God. The Loyalty of theſe proud
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:58923:24"/>Huffers and Hectors conſiſts only in Hypocriſie: That by the pretence thereof, they may either the better gain, or the more ſecurely hold ſome maintenance that they have by the Kings benefit. Or rather they pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend Loyalty, as the Hypocrite pretends the name of Chriſt<note n="p" place="margin">Mat. 7.22.</note>; and the Fanatick his Conſcience, that it may be a riſe for their ſins, and a vail for their impieties.</p>
            <p>And no marvel: for it is impoſſible (we ſee) that their Loyalty ſhould conſiſt in reality, any more than the Godlineſs of thoſe that ſtile themſelves the Godly party. The very Heathens, though ſome of them (I mean the wiſer ſort) ſeemed to be very Loyal and true to their King; yet their Loy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alty cannot be ſaid to be abſolutely true and firm, any more than their Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion: How much leſs then may we term the Loyalty of theſe ſwearing ſwaggerers true and firm, when as they profeſs themſelves to be Chriſtians, yea, and Proteſtants too; and yet live more diametrically oppoſite to the Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine of Chriſts Goſpel, than the very worſt of the Gentiles: Is it likely (think you) that they ſhould be ſuch great
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:58923:24"/>friends to their King, as they would make you believe, who are ſuch grand enemies to the Croſs of Chriſt<note n="q" place="margin">Phil. 3.18.</note>? No, certainly, they are as arrant enemies to their King, as any he hath: And that both in Proſperity, and in Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſity.</p>
            <p n="1">1. In proſperity, when the King ſits moſt peaceably upon his Throne, and they themſelves are in the very height of their mirth and jollity, even then they become his enemies, by pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voking, ſharpning and augmenting his adverſaries againſt him, through their evil examples: What do they but draw a Sword for Fanaticks to fight with againſt his Majeſty, by bringing a ſcandal upon Loyalty, through their debauchery and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phaneneſs? <hi>Chriſtopher Love</hi> in his Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bellious Sermon (in the year 1644.) made this his only objection to with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand the Treaty of Peace (made by our Martyred Soveraign) at <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>xbridge.</hi> Yea, as meer formaliſts by living con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to the doctrine they profeſs, they bring a ſcandal upon Religion, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by the Converſion of the Churches enemies is impeded: So theſe prophane Loyaliſts by living contrary to the Loy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alty
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:58923:25"/>they profeſs, do (even now adays) not only harden Fanaticks in their er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ror, and make them the more to glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry in their ſhame; but alſo give them occaſion childiſhly and tauntingly to object, that they dare not turn Loya<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſts for fear of prophaneneſs. And not only ſo, but others too, as they are drawn into Fanaticiſm by a form of Godlineſs: So they drive them from Loyalty, by laying a ſtumbling block before their weaker brethren<note n="r" place="margin">Rom. 14.13.</note>.</p>
            <p n="2">2. In adverſity, the Tryal of True Loyalty and friendſhip; as they do their King much injury in the Tavern: So they do him as little ſervice in the Field; for as ſoon as they ſee his power (the foundation of their Loyalty) to be once removed (or likely to be ſo) by his enemies; then (for all their former bravado's) inſtead of aſſiſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing him, and ſacrificing their dear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt intereſts for his life and preſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation, (as King <hi>Davids</hi> True and worthy Loyaliſts did for his<note n="ſ" place="margin">2 Sam. 18. &amp; 21. 1 Chron. 11.</note>;) they will either moſt Traiterouſly, Barba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rouſly and inhumanely take part with his enemies, and inſult upon him, like the Frogs upon the block in
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:58923:25"/>
               <hi>Aeſop</hi>'s <hi>Fables;</hi> or elſe in his greateſt need moſt daſtardly forſake him. This was too evidently ſeen in our late times of Rebellion, againſt our Martyred So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veraign, when ſome even of his own ſworn ſervants, and familiar friends too, (of a ſeemingly ſober deportment, in whom he truſted) did (like <hi>Judas</hi> againſt our Saviour<note n="t" place="margin">Joh. 13.18. Pſ. 41.9.</note>) moſt traiterouſly lift up their heels againſt him. Neither was his Son (our now Moſt Gracious Lord and King) ſerved much better at <hi>Worceſter</hi> fight by ſuch friendly gulls, and Loyal-cheats, when (for all their former great pretences to Loyalty) out of a ſlaviſh fear of Cruel Uſurpers, and Oppreſſers, they moſt Cowardly ſneak't in a corner, and forc't his Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſty (for want of aſſiſtance) to fight with a handful (as it were, and ſome of them diſloyal too) againſt a mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Therefore, O ye Prophane and ungodly Loyaliſts, (though God forbid any ſuch ſad times ſhould come again to try your Loyalty in; yet) it is behoofeful that you (as well as thoſe that call themſelves the God<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Party) purge out all your ſins by
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:58923:26"/>a true, timely, and unfeigned repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance, and holy reſolutions of better obedience, that your Hypocriſie and deception may alſo vaniſh, as well as theirs:<note place="margin">Mat. 12.41, 42.</note> Unleſs you mean to have the very Gentiles riſe in judgment againſt you, for being under the light of Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture better Loyaliſts than you, under the glorious light of the Goſpel: For all men are obliged even by Nature it ſelf, to venture their deareſt blood for the ſafety of their King: Our Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our himſelf (who came to fufil the Law of <hi>Moſes,</hi> and perfect the Law of Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture<note n="u" place="margin">Mat. 5.17.</note>) hath confirmed it for a never dying Maxim: <hi>If my Kingdom</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>were of this World, then would my Servants fight,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>John</hi> 18.36.</p>
            <p>And no marvel that it ſhould be thus; for the King (as he is Gods Vicegerent, and our Supreme head and Governour) is (as the men of <hi>Iſrael</hi> ſaid of King <hi>David</hi>) <hi>worth ten thouſand of us</hi>
               <note n="w" place="margin">2 Sam. 18.3.</note>; yea, more than us all, the very light of the Nation<note n="x" place="margin">2 Sam. 21.17.</note>. This proves that the King is, <hi>Major <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſis,</hi> contrary to that falſe, Childiſh, Fanatical, and Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monarchical diſtinction, that he is, <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jor Singulis, Minor <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſis.</hi> Be ye
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:58923:26"/>then as Loyal in your reſolutions as you are in your profeſſions, and as care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful of your Kings preſervation, as <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>biſhai</hi> and the men of <hi>Iſrael</hi> were of King <hi>David</hi>'s<note n="y" place="margin">2 Sam. 21.17.</note>: Leſt for your neglect of a duty of ſo high a concern, the great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of your Talent bring upon you a greater Curſe than that of <hi>Meroz,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Luke 12.48.</note> 
               <hi>Curſe ye Meroz</hi> (ſaid the Angel of the Lord) <hi>Curſe ye bitterly the inhab<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>nts thereof: Becauſe they came not to the help of the Lord, to the help of the Lord againſt the Mighty,</hi> Judges 5.23.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Though no pretence at laſt ſhall excuſe any Gainſaying and Rebellious people<note n="z" place="margin">Rom. 10.21.</note>, but all that deſpiſe domini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and ſpeak evil of Dignities, muſt without diſcrimination periſh in the Gainſaying of <hi>Core</hi>
               <note n="a" place="margin">Jud. 8. to the 22.</note>; yet be ye wary how ye offer any occaſion to your weaker brethren to be Revolters from their Loyalty, or obſtinate in their Fanaticiſm, by mixing your Loyalty with prophaneneſs; leſt you aggravate your Torments in Hell, by making your ſelves guilty of their ſin and pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment, as well as your own.</p>
            <pb n="50" facs="tcp:58923:27"/>
            <p>You have ſeen in, or from our late times of Rebellion, what confuſion and deſtruction our Old prophane Loy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aliſts brought upon their King and Country, by ſhaming ſo good a Cauſe which they owned: How they filled our Land like <hi>Rama</hi> with mourning, by their Curſing and Curſed Oaths<note n="b" place="margin">Jer. 23.10. Mat. 2.18.</note>; even bitter mourning, as the mourn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of <hi>Hadadrimmon</hi> in the Valley of <hi>Megiddon</hi>
               <note n="c" place="margin">Zech. 12.11. Mal. 3.5. Eccleſiaſticus 23.11.</note>: And finally, what <hi>Aegyp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tian</hi> Bondage and darkneſs they en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wrapped the whole Nation in, both Church and State; by moving Fana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticks (as was pretended) with their drunkenneſs and debauchery, to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinguiſh the light of <hi>England.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In a word therefore, take ye warn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in time, and follow their pernici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous examples no more, leſt you find death in your Pots indeed<note n="d" place="margin">2 Kings 4.40.</note>, the death of your Souls to all eternity<note n="e" place="margin">1 Cor. 6.9, 10.</note>. But manifeſt your Allegiance, by adorning your Loyalty with holy lives anſwera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to your profeſſions;<note place="margin">Tit. 2.10.</note> that thereby you may both remove all objections, and colours of Rebellion from any that watch for matter of advantage and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ception againſt you; and offer them as great an occaſion to imbrace True Loy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alty
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:58923:27"/>(if they will accept it) as they have from all True Loyaliſts, (if they were not wilfully blind and obſtinate) that ſo the more hearts being united to the <hi>Lord and the King,</hi> we may get the more ſtrength to reſiſt our Enemies, and the more ſecurely enjoy Peace a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt our ſelves, both in Church and State.</p>
            <p>Now, 2. As the True Loyaliſt, when he is in the place of a True Confor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſt, honours God not only with re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verence, but with his ſubſtance<note n="f" place="margin">Prov. 3.9. Mic. 4.13.</note>; ſo the True Conformiſt, when he is in the place of a True Loyaliſt, honours his King not only with due reſpect and eſteem, but alſo with maintenance: The ſame man in one reſpect renders unto God, the things which be Gods; and in the other, he renders unto <hi>Cae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſar,</hi> the things which be <hi>Caeſar</hi>'s<note n="g" place="margin">Luk. 20.25.</note>. Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er and thankſgiving he pays to God, as his immediate Rents and dues, Tythes and offerings mediately in his Stewards and Miniſters: But Tribute or Taxes, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> he renders unto his King, or <hi>Caeſar</hi> in a more ſpecial man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, as he is Gods Miniſter and Vice<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerent, and next under him his ſupreme
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:58923:28"/>Head and Governour. Therefore it is very remarkable that our bleſſed Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour (who pay'd Tribute himſelf, which his pretended Vicar refuſes to do) to ſhew the great neceſſity of this duty,<note place="margin">Dr. <hi>Boys</hi> up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nical Epiſtles and Goſpels. <hi>p.</hi> 163.</note> never did any miracle about ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour or money, except this one, of giving Tribute unto <hi>Caeſar,</hi> Mat. 17.27.</p>
            <p>The conſideration of this, moves the True Loyaliſt to pay his Tribute and Taxes, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> to his King, freely and vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luntarily, out of love and fear to God and his Commandments. Whereas the Nominal Loyaliſt, though he alſo pays Tribute and Taxes, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> to his King, as well as the True; yet he pays them unwillingly, and by conſtraint; out of fear of the Kings authority, and the Penal Laws of the Land: But the True Loyaliſt (I ſay) conſiders that his King is Gods Miniſter and Vicege<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent, appointed by him for the good of his Church; both as a rewarder for the praiſe of them that do well, and as a revenger to execute his wrath upon them that do evil: And therefore (as the Apoſtle hath taught him<note n="h" place="margin">Rom. 13.3, 4, 5, 6.</note>, he pays his Tribute and Taxes, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> with all ſubjection, not only for Wrath, but al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo for Conſcience-ſake.</p>
            <pb n="53" facs="tcp:58923:28"/>
            <p>By this you may perceive, that though the True Loyaliſt and the no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minal agree in this, that both of them pay Tribute and Taxes, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> to their King; yet in the mode and ends of their paying, they differ as much as a ſervile fear and a filial, yea, a Humane fear and a Divine; the fear of God, and the fear of man.</p>
            <p>How much then are Quakers and ſuch Godly gulls to blame, who (think<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing they do God good ſervice in reſiſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the higher Powers) chuſe rather to ſuffer impriſonment, or any afflicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on in the World, than to pay any Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bute or Taxes, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> at all? And glory in it too, and plead Conſcience for the ſame; as if God (the jealouſie of whoſe honour burneth like fire) was the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor of Rebellion againſt himſelf, and his own Laws. How great the judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of theſe blaſphemers and Rebels againſt <hi>the Lord and the King</hi> ſhall be, I cannot determine, becauſe it is unſpeak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able. St. <hi>Peter</hi> ſaith, <hi>If the righteous ſcarcely be ſaved, where ſhall the ungod<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and ſinner appear</hi>
               <note n="i" place="margin">1 Pet. 4.18</note>? Where then (ſay I) ſhall theſe appear? That fall ſo far
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:58923:29"/>ſhort of Nominal Loyaliſts, that in <hi>Statu quo,</hi> in the condition they are in, fall far ſhort of Heaven. The nomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal Loyaliſt hath ſomething in him that is good, more than his Eſſence or be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing; his profeſſion is good, (if his life were anſwerable) but the profeſſion of theſe is as Diametrically oppoſite to Religion, as their Loyalty; which conſiſteth only in Rebellion. Moreo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver the nominal Loyaliſt, though he pay his Tribute and Taxes, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> only out of a ſervile fear; yet by his out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward conformity and obedience he de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clares himſelf to be a member within the Pale of the Church, where he hath the means (which God hath ordained) to make him (if he be not wanting to himſelf) a True Chriſtian, and a True Loyaliſt in time: And not only ſo, but he alſo helps to preſerve the publick peace and ſafety of the Nation, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by he peaceably enjoys many tempo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral bleſſings, or at leaſt keeps himſelf ſecure from temporal puniſhments, as <hi>Ahab</hi> averted the temporal wrath of God, by outwardly humbling himſelf<note n="k" place="margin">1 Kings 21.29.</note>. But theſe Rebellious wretches are good for nothing; they are no better than the very Heathens and Publicans<note n="l" place="margin">Mat 18.17.</note>, they
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:58923:29"/>are good neither for their Souls, nor for their bodies; they are Sots as well as ſinners, not only ſpiritual fools, but natural and inconſiderate fools in the deepeſt Grain; they not only ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>communicate themſelves from the or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary means of True Loyalty and ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation, and break peace and unity both in Church and State by their diviſions, but they alſo diſturbe even their own quiet in this life, by bringing puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments upon themſelves, by and for their Rebellion.</p>
            <p>And how much are thoſe Publicans and Tax-gatherers to blame too, that make no more Conſcience to em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pty the Kings Exchequer, that they may fill their own Coffers; or ſome ways or other build up themſelves out of the ruins of the Kings Tribute, than theſe Holy-cheats do to pay it? <hi>Touch not mine Anointed</hi>
               <note n="m" place="margin">1 Chron 16.22.</note>, is a prohibition to hurt the King, not only in his Body, but in his Eſtate too: It is theft to ſteal the goods of any; but to cheat and rob the King of his Tribute, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> is a ſin no leſs than Sacriledge: For Tribute, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> belongs to the King, not as he is a perſon Civil, but Sacred,
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:58923:30"/>Anointed with Holy Oyl to be Gods Miniſter and Vicegerent<note n="n" place="margin">Rom. 13.4, 5, 6.</note>. And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore to rob Gods Clergy of Tythes, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> is alſo the curſed ſin of Sacriledge, becauſe the High Prieſt the Repreſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tative of them all,<note place="margin">Rom. 11.16.</note> was alſo Gods An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ointed, Anointed with Holy Oyl to his Sacred Function, as well as the King. <hi>Zech.</hi> 4.14. <hi>Theſe are the two anointed ones</hi> (or Sons of Oyl) <hi>which ſtand by the Lord of the whole Earth.</hi> This <hi>Targum</hi> expounds of <hi>Joſhua</hi> and <hi>Zoro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>babel,</hi> who were anointed, (the one for the Princely Government, the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther for the Prieſt-hood) with the ſelf-ſame Oyl<note n="o" place="margin">Numb. 35.25.</note>, and accordingly God him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf (with relation to the days of Chriſt) doth call this ſort of theft, Sacriledge. <hi>Will a man rob God,</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>yet he have robbed me: but yet ye ſay, wherein have we robbed thee?</hi> ('tis anſwered) <hi>in Tythes and offerings. Ye are curſed with a curſe:</hi> (that is, ſurely and greatly curſed) <hi>for ye have robbed me, even this whole Nation, Mal.</hi> 3.8, 9. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 9.14.</p>
            <p>'Tis Sacriledge then, (the curſed and damnable ſin of Sacriledge) to rob God in the Miniſters of his holy word and Sacraments: But how much ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:58923:30"/>to rob God in the King, his Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter and Vicegerent? Surely, if near<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of relation will make any diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, (as <hi>touch not mine anointed,</hi> goeth before <hi>do my Prophets no harm</hi>
               <note n="p" place="margin">1 Chron. 16.22.</note>) it muſt needs be the greateſt Sacriledge of all, next to the robbing God in himſelf, of his immediate Rents and dues of prayer and thankſgiving. Render therefore to all their dues, (eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pecially to God and <hi>Caeſar</hi>) <hi>Tribute to whom Tribute is due, Cuſtom to whom Cuſtom, Fear to whom Fear, Honour to whom Honour,</hi> Rom. 13.7.</p>
            <p>But, 3. and Laſtly,<note place="margin">The falſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceipt of the Solemn League and Covenant diſcovered.</note> as the true Loyaliſt is obedient to his King, in paying of him Tribute and Taxes, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> ſo alſo in all his other Laws and Ordinances: he ſtill con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiders that his King is appointed by God to be his Miniſter and Vicegerent, for the External government of his Church; and therefore out of love and fear to God, and obedience to his Laws, (in ſerving of whom the people have only perfect liberty<note n="q" place="margin">James 1.19. &amp; 2.12. 2 Cor. 3.17. Rom. 8.21.</note>) he moſt freely ſweareth fealty to him, to be true to him, and obedient: And accordingly he rejoyceth when the Oath of Allegi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance is impoſed upon him, and the
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:58923:31"/>whole Nation; becauſe it is for con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmation of Loyalty and ſubjection; that thereby there may be an end of all ſtrife, and all both in Church and State may enjoy Peace the more ſecure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly<note n="r" place="margin">Heb. 6.16, 17</note>: In which reſpect ſaith <hi>Solomon, I counſel thee to keep the Kings Command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and that in regard of the Oath of God</hi>
               <note n="ſ" place="margin">Eccleſiaſtes 8.2.</note>. The True Loyaliſt, though he would obey his Kings Commandment, (either actively or paſſively) without an Oath, his Conſcience being bound before by the Law of God; yet becauſe God wills ſuch an Oath for confirma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the lawleſs in outward obedience with the juſt and Loyal<note n="t" place="margin">1 Tim. 1.9.</note>, he the more willingly takes and keeps it, that ſo there may be an end of all ſtrife; for certainly he muſt be a notorious Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bel indeed, that will not keep his Kings commandment, in regard of his Oath, if he had no other obligation; for an Oath, if it be only in ſuch things which are not contrary to the will of God, is ſo Sacred and obliging a thing, that it bringeth the wrath and vengeance of God upon him that breaketh it<note n="u" place="margin">Joſhua 9.20. Numb. 5.21.</note>, and therefore ſaith <hi>Solomon,</hi> it is a ſnare to the man who devoureth that which is holy: (to wit, who taketh an holy
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:58923:31"/>Oath upon him) and after vows to make enquiry<note n="w" place="margin">Pro. 20.25.</note>. (to wit, whether his Oath, or Vow be any ways prejudicial to his Body or Eſtate, or not<note n="x" place="margin">Pſ. 15.4.</note>:) For which cauſe, when <hi>Joſhua</hi> and the Princes of the Congregation had made a Peace with the <hi>Gibeonites</hi> upon Oath, they durſt not break it; though it were ſo diſadvantagious, that the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> murmured againſt them, and their ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies had obtained the League by guile and craft<note n="y" place="margin">Joſhua 9.</note>: and when King <hi>Saul</hi> in a battel againſt the <hi>Philiſtines,</hi> had adjured the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> not to eat any food until the evening, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> they were no leſs careful to keep the Kings command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment in regard of their Oath; for not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding the raſhneſs of the adju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration, the greatneſs of their diſtreſs with hunger and confination; and the greatneſs of their temptation too, by the dropping of hony in a private wood: Yet no man would put his hand to his mouth, becauſe they fear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the Oath<note n="z" place="margin">1 Sam. 14.</note>.</p>
            <p>Now if an Oath be ſo Sacred and blinding, when it is only in things indif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferent, not contrary to the will of God: How much rather is it Sacred and ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liging,
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:58923:32"/>when it is for confirmation of ſuch holy things, which the word of God hath (before) bound us to ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve<note n="a" place="margin">Nehemiah 10.29.</note>? Let all be judge that have not ſhook hands with their rationality: I am ſure, theſe obligations are more firm, than <hi>Solomons.</hi> threefold Cord, which cannot quickly be broken<note n="b" place="margin">Eccleſiaſtes 4.12.</note>.</p>
            <p>But, 2. If the Oath be raſhly taken in ſuch things that be contrary to the word of God, I know then that there is none, (except he be more Infidel than the Devils themſelves<note n="c" place="margin">James 2.19.</note>) but will rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dily acknowledge that it is abſolutely unlawfull<note n="d" place="margin">Numb. 30.5, 8.</note>, and conſequently the ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligation to keep it, as abſolutely taken away: Yea, by the Law of contrapo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition, (if we will but allow Affirma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tives and Negatives to include or ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe one another) a man is as much obliged to break an unlawful Oath, as he is to keep one that is lawful in all things according to the word of God; becauſe as he cannot keep an unlawful Oath, without making his ſin exceeding ſinful: ſo by breaking of it, he manifeſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth his repentance; whereby, he makes a re-entry into Covenant with God, by a new ſtipulation.</p>
            <pb n="61" facs="tcp:58923:32"/>
            <p>How much then was <hi>Herod</hi> (that Fox<note n="e" place="margin">Luke 13.32.</note>) to blame when he promiſed upon Oath to give the Daughter of <hi>Herodias</hi> (for pleaſing him in a Dance) what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever ſhe would ask; and ſhe (being before inſtructed of her Mother) ſaid, <hi>give me here John Baptiſt's head in a Charger?</hi> For inſtead of putting her off, by telling her that his Oath ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed only ſuch requeſts as were law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful, he added ſin to ſin; for though the Hypocrite ſaid, <hi>He was exceeding ſorry; nevertheleſs for the Oaths ſake,</hi> (as he pretended) <hi>and them which ſat with him at meat, he commanded it to be given her</hi>
               <note n="f" place="margin">Mar. 14. Mar. 6.</note>.</p>
            <p>But how much more was <hi>Cromwell</hi> (that Fox) and his Park of Presbyteri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans and Independents to blame, when (to ſatisfie the having deſire of Mrs. <hi>Avarice,</hi> for pleaſing them with a dance, in the great Parlor of their large Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciences) they bound themſelves each to other by a Solemn, yet damn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able League and Covenant, to deſtroy our Nation and her Religion, and to root out all order and Government both in Church and State? <hi>Herod</hi> played
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:58923:33"/>only the Tyrant; but theſe were not only Tyrants, but Uſurpers too: be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides, though they agreed with him in ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral circumſtances of their cruelty and Hypocriſie; yet they much out-ballan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced him in the mode and hainouſneſs of their Oath and Villany: For whereas <hi>Herods</hi> Oath conſiſted only of a plain piece of cruelty againſt a ſingle per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, their Covenant was taken for the deſtruction of a whole Kingdom; and like the Turkiſh <hi>Alcoran,</hi> conſiſted of a Hoch-poch of principles, not only bad, but ſome ſeemingly good too to cover the bad, and their evil deſigns with the vail of Hypocriſie. And accordingly, herein it was notoriouſly contradictory to its ſelf; it pretended great Loyalty to preſerve and defend the Kings Majeſties Perſon and authority; and withal to extirpate Epiſcopacy, and Church Government: Which could not poſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly be, without deſtroying the Kings Authority; becauſe they were upheld by the Kings Authority. This was ſo evident, that they preceived it them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, and therefore were reſolved to contradict themſelves further, and al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo deſtroy the Kings Majeſties perſon too: The Presbyterians Preacht him
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:58923:33"/>upon the block, and the Independents beheaded him and the whole Nation. And accordingly, when it had once ſtrengthened them (the end for which it was taken) by tying the Populacy faſt to their parties, under the terrour of perjury; then they quickly<note n="*" place="margin">Hiſt. <hi>Inde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pend.</hi> Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleat. Part. 1. <hi>p.</hi> 139.</note> caſt it aſide, and called it an Almanack out of date. Yea, and puniſhed too many for attempting to keep it. And no mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vel, for their Covenant (which they had ſo raſhly and unadviſedly taken) pretended ſo much for the honour and happineſs of the Kings Majeſty, and his Poſterity; that they ſaw they could not poſſibly keep it, without its con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tradicting them in their pulling down of Monarchy, and the eſtabliſhing of their Oligarchy or Tyranny: For<note n="*" place="margin">Hiſt. <hi>Inde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pend.</hi> Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleat. Part 1. <hi>p.</hi> 113.</note> which cauſe, their Grandees, that they might alſo the better hinder their Vote, that they would not alter the ancient form of Government by King, Lords, and Commons, from taking effect, cauſed the Antimonarchical book written by <hi>Parſons</hi> the <hi>Jeſuit,</hi> 1524. (un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the feigned name of <hi>Doleman</hi>) to be publiſhed, though they knew it was condemned by Act of Parliament, 35 <hi>Eliz.</hi> But it is no wonder that they
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:58923:34"/>ſhould not care for former Acts of Parli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, when as they did ſo lightly eſteem of their own, as well as of their National Covenant: Wherein, though they alſo pretended to be great Reformers from Popiſh ſuperſtition; yet you ſee (as the ſame Author obſerves) that they can joyn intereſts with <hi>France,</hi> Doctrine with the <hi>Jeſuits,</hi> to carry on their de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign, and reduce us to the condition of <hi>French</hi> Peaſants and Slaves, under the Kingdom of the Saints.</p>
            <p>And the truth is, though the great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt part might do what they did, not out of malice, but rather (as our Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyred Soveraign charitably ſpeaks of them, in his ΕΙΚΩΝ ΒΑΣΙΛΙΚΗ) out of miſapprehenſion of things, or miſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation; yet it is notorious that moſt of the Chief and Heads of them acted againſt their own knowledge and Conſcience, no leſs than <hi>Herod</hi> did in beheading of <hi>John</hi> the <hi>Baptiſt;</hi> for as <hi>Herod</hi> knew and acknowledged that <hi>John</hi> was a juſt man and an holy, and had done nothing worthy of death; but only a ſpleen he had againſt him, for telling him that it was not lawful for him to have his Brothers Wife, whom
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:58923:34"/>he had married: So theſe Covenanters knew not only that they had bound themſelves by a ſolemn Oath (with hands lifted up to the moſt high God) to preſerve and defend the King, but alſo that he was ſo juſt a man &amp; an holy, that they could find nothing of any moment to ſtuf out their black charge againſt him: They knew that he comported<note n="*" place="margin">Hiſt. <hi>Inde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dend.</hi> Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleat. Part 2. <hi>p.</hi> 218.</note> himſelf in his afflictions with ſuch ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mired temper, prudence and conſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy; that many even of his engaged E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemies themſelves became his Converts thereby, ſpeaking Panegyricks in his praiſe: Particularly, <hi>Harry</hi>
               <note n="†" place="margin">Hiſt. <hi>Inde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pend.</hi> Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleat. Part 2. <hi>p.</hi> 15.</note> 
               <hi>Martyn</hi> making a ſpeech in the Houſe upon the Debate, touching Kingly Government, whether a King, or no King? gives this judgment of him, that if they muſt have a King, he had rather have had the laſt than any Gentleman in <hi>England;</hi> he found no fault in his perſon, but in his Office.</p>
            <p>And yet for all this, like <hi>Herod</hi> too they could pretend to do what they did for their Oaths<note n="*" place="margin">Hiſt. <hi>Inde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pend.</hi> Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleat. Part 2. <hi>p.</hi> 242. <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </note> ſake: Eſpecial<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, in their compliance with the bloody <hi>Iriſh</hi> Papiſts; though by their Oath they were ingaged ſo much to the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary,
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:58923:35"/>to defend the King and his po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterity, and to root out Popery. But their minds were ſo bent to ruin Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narchy, and the Proteſtant Religion, meerly to raiſe themſelves, and ſupport their own faction; that they did not conſider what they ſaid or did: And their Oath beſides was ſo intricate, and full of contradiction, that they could not tell what to make of it: And therefore they ſometimes rejected it, and ſometimes pretended it, in their Hypocriſie, for the ſake of thoſe parts in it which they thought the moſt fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voured their deſigns, according to their own vain whimzies, and Fanatical ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginations; as<note n="*" place="margin">Hiſt. <hi>Inde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pend.</hi> Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleat. Part 1. <hi>p.</hi> 79 &amp; 80.</note> 
               <hi>Marſhal</hi> that Turn-Coat Prieſt, (having always a ſpecial care to ſide himſelf with the prevailing Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty) in a Sermon at <hi>Margarets Weſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minſter</hi> cried up Presbytery and the Covenant, whenas before (to ingrati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ate himſelf with the Independents) he had as much ſlighted both in the Army: for otherwiſe, their facino<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous acts ſhewed that they feared an Oath no more than <hi>Herod</hi> did in be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heading <hi>John</hi> the <hi>Baptiſt:</hi> If they had feared an Oath, their Oath of Allegi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance and Supremacy, (as they ought
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:58923:35"/>to have done) yea, and their own Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant too; then inſtead of murder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing their King, they would have kept his commandments: But the truth is, as <hi>Herod</hi> perpetrated his wicked act, not for his Oaths ſake, but for <hi>Herodi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as</hi> ſake; or rather for his and her en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vy, and their luſts ſake: So theſe ſilly Reformers did what they did, not for their Oaths ſake, but for their Oligar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chy or Tyrannies ſake; or rather for their Pride, their Envy, their Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>touſneſs, and all their luſts ſake.</p>
            <p>Now, what ſhould I ſpend time in confuting theſe unworthy men, in their contemning and deſpiſing the holy orders of Epiſcopacy and our Church Government; by joyning them in their Covenant, with Popery, Superſtition, Hereſie, Schiſm, Prophaneneſs, and whatſoever is contrary to ſound Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine, and the power of Godlineſs? When as the<note n="†" place="margin">
                  <hi>Burton</hi> of the Wars in <hi>England, Scot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> and <hi>Ire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land.</hi> p. 65.</note> Biſhops. (not only) im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed an Oath (as an Anti-Covenant) called <hi>&amp;c.</hi> (<hi>Et caetera</hi>) againſt the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troduction of any Popiſh Doctrine in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Church, and the ſubjection of it to the Uſurpations and ſuperſtitions of the See of <hi>Rome;</hi> but alſo you have
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:58923:36"/>ſeen already how they contradicted themſelves therein, by joyning in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſts with the Papiſts, and Doctrine with the <hi>Jeſuites,</hi> to root out Monar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chy and Proteſtancy, giving them a tole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration of their Religion, and the poſſeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Proteſtants Eſtates for their Hire. Yea, and you have ſeen too, how the God of order him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf hath confuted them in the Text; commanding all <hi>to fear the Lord and the King,</hi> together; he that feareth the Lord, (let him pretend what he will) will alſo fear and honour his King.</p>
            <p>Yet notwithſtanding all this, they want not Diſciples and Followers to this very day; (as well as other Sects and Schiſms;) there be too many a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt us, that have took no heed to the Leven of theſe Scribes and Phari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſees; not only of the Laity, but alſo of the Clergy. Which is a thing much to be admired at, that men that profeſs ſo much learning and Religion too, ſhould betray ſo much weakneſs in their judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, and perverſneſs in their wills; as to be zealous of keeping that Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant, which they know is ſo contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dictory
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:58923:36"/>in its ſelf, that a man cannot poſſibly keep it without breaking of it. I know you would ſcorn to be called fools; but I am ſure that your Maſters (if they had meant honeſtly) ſhewed far more wiſdom, when (upon the conſideration of its contradicting them in pulling down of Monarchy) they caſt it aſide, and called it an Almanack out of date; and puniſhed too many for attempting to keep it. And what will you follow your Maſters only where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in they were vicious, and not in their repentance? Though God forbid but that yours ſhould be real and ſerious: For then others need not,<note place="margin">Tit. 3.1, 2, 3.</note> you would call your ſelves fools a thouſand times over and over, yea, mad, that you ſhould ever be ſo wicked, raſh and unadvi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, as to juſtifie the abominable pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedings of thoſe Covenanters we read of <hi>Pſal.</hi> 83. Who although like your Maſters, they were men of ſeveral In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſts and Religions; yet bound them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves each to other by the like ſolemn, yet damnable League and Covenant againſt God and his Church: Or like the Kings of the Earth and their Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theniſh Subjects againſt the Lord, and againſt his Anointed<note n="g" place="margin">Pſal. 2.</note>.</p>
            <pb n="70" facs="tcp:58923:37"/>
            <p>But thanks be to God,<note n="*" place="margin">Dr. <hi>Lees</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cantation Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon, or his <hi>Corhumiliatum &amp; contritum,</hi> for taking the ſolemn League and Covenant. Printed 1663.</note> ſome have conſidered themſelves already, recant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed and conformed; as the foremention<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Dr. <hi>Lee,</hi> &amp;c. And others too like <hi>Agrippa,</hi> have been almoſt perſwaded; but their Oath they ſay, ſticks in their conſciences; they are afraid to conform, for fear of that. I would to God their Oath of Allegiance, obedience, and Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>premacy, had ſtuck in their Conſciences as much before: then they would have been True Loyaliſts, and True Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formiſts ſtill, and not ſo ſhameful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly have broken the commandments of the Lord and the King: But ſuch is the deceitfulneſs of ſin, (the greateſt myſtery in iniquity) that men by nature do eaſily forſake the good, and cleave to the evil; where they ſtick ſo faſt, that they cannot poſſibly return from thence to the good again, without the concur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent help of Gods grace, and the Om<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nipotent hand of a Deity. Yet our hope and deſire is, that God (in his good time) will open their eyes, and looſe them from this bond of iniqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty; that they may be not only almoſt, but altogether ſuch as St. <hi>Paul</hi> was, except his bonds<note n="h" place="margin">Acts 26.28, 29.</note>.</p>
            <pb n="71" facs="tcp:58923:37"/>
            <p>And laſtly, as all ought to have a ſpecial care how they ſin againſt the light of their Conſciences, (and yet pretend Conſcience for the ſame) leſt they incur the greateſt Damnation: So let none be ſo wicked and abſurd to reject Repentance and Conformati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on for fear of ſhame; (as proud per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons are too apt to do.) For that is another great deceitfulneſs of ſin, and colluſion of the Devil, for men to think that to tend to their ſhame and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grace, which purchaſes them the great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt honour and eſteem. St. <hi>Aug.</hi> got more honour by his confeſſions and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tractations than by all his other wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tings beſides. Nor did this learned Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctor get ſo much eſteem by any thing that ever he did, as by this his Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon of recantation. Whereas if he had been ſtill obſtinate in ſo wretch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed an Oath, and had ſcorned to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form, he knew he ſhould but increaſe his ſhame and diſhonour; and that not only temporal, but eternal too: for Chriſt himſelf ſaith, that as he that confeſſes him before men, ſhall be confeſſed of him before his Father which is in Heaven: So he that de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies,
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:58923:38"/>or is aſhamed of him, and of his words, in this adulterous and ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful generation; of him alſo will he be aſhamed, when he cometh in the glory of his father, with the holy Angels<note n="i" place="margin">Mat. 10.32, 33. Mark 8.38.</note>.</p>
            <p>The True Loyaliſt conſidering this, ſticks to his Oath of Allegiance and Supremacy, the more ſtedfaſtly; and in regard thereof is the more afraid to break his Kings commandment; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it is made, not for man and his luſts ſake, but for the Lord and his ſake<note n="k" place="margin">2 Chron. 19.6.</note>. Therefore (as Saint <hi>Peter</hi> hath exhorted him) he freely ſubmits himſelf <hi>to every ordinance of man for the Lords ſake: Whether it be to the King, as Supreme, or unto Governours, as un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to them that are ſent by him, for the puniſhment of evil doers, and for the praiſe of them that do well;</hi> yet he willingly ſubmits himſelf, (either a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctively or paſſively) becauſe ſo is the will of God, that with well doing he may put to ſilence the ignorance of fooliſh men<note n="l" place="margin">1 Pet. 2.13, 14, 15.</note>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. Actively, by obeying his King, not only in ſuch things which are al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:58923:38"/>commanded by the Lord, in his word: but alſo in all other things which are not contrary to it: Let things be never ſo indifferent in themſelves, neither made ſimply good or bad by the command or prohibition of God, but hang meerly upon the State of times, and the various cuſtoms, and manners of Nations; yet when they are once commanded, and made the Laws of the Land, he pays obedience to them, as to things not indifferent; becauſe otherwiſe his Kings Power and Prerogative would in effect be nullified, contrary to the Law of God, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructive to Chriſtian Government and Magiſtracy. Wherefore (left in the very act he ſhould diſobey, not man, but God himſelf<note n="m" place="margin">1 Theſ. 4.8.</note>) He is neceſſarily ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject, <hi>not only for wrath, but alſo for Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience ſake</hi>
               <note n="n" place="margin">Rom. 13.5<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note>
            </p>
            <p>And indeed thoſe things which in themſelves are indifferent, muſt needs become good and neceſſary, when they are once made the Laws of the Land; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe therein they alſo tend to our good and welfare, both in Church and State.</p>
            <pb n="74" facs="tcp:58923:39"/>
            <p n="1">1. In the State, if there were no Laws, there would be no living; the weakeſt then would always go to the Wall. Yea, men would then be like fiſh in the Sea, the greater would evermore devour the leſs, the ſtrongeſt arm and the longeſt Sword would always carry it; the paſſions of men would then ſet them in as great a combuſtion, as when <hi>Phaeton</hi> rode the Sun: happy therefore is that Nation that hath binding Laws in it, to curb our corrupt and irregu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar paſſions; but thrice happy is that Nation that hath Governours in it en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dued with ſuch a ſpirit, as makes them willing to execute thoſe Laws: for other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe, were there never ſo good Laws, and the King or Supreme Governour ſhould have never ſo great a deſire to have them executed; yet ſeeing with other eyes, and handling with other hands than his own, he cannot always have his will fulfilled, (excepting on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in Supreme cauſes, where he ſits as immediate Judge himſelf) with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the concurrent help of inferiour Governours: For which cauſe, though the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> in the Wilderneſs were a more collective body than other Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, yet <hi>Jethro, Moſes</hi> Father-in-Law
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:58923:39"/>(ſeeing how he toiled in judging them alone) adviſed him to chuſe inferiour Governours, to judge the ſmaller mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, and to bring the greater unto him: and not only ſo, but ſuch men too, as were rightly qualified for their Office; <hi>able men, ſuch as fear God, men of truth, hating Covetouſneſs</hi>
               <note n="o" place="margin">Exod. 18.</note>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. In the Church, if there were no or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinances, there would be no order; and if no order, no unity in Gods ſervice, nor ſtedfaſtneſs in the Faith<note n="p" place="margin">Col. 2.5.</note>. Yea, though there muſt be Hereſies, or Sects a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong us, (as our Apoſtle ſpeaks)<note n="q" place="margin">1 Cor. 11.19.</note> yet if men ſhould have no Ordinances to contain them in order, but be per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted to live as they liſt themſelves, as they were when there was no King in <hi>England,</hi> like as when there was no King in <hi>Iſrael</hi>
               <note n="r" place="margin">Jud. 17.6.</note>: There would be ſo many the more Diviſions and Confu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions in the Church, whereby the more Tumults and Troubles would be rai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed in the State. For the welfare of the State is imbarked in the welfare of the Church; no Chriſtian State can poſſibly be ſound and well, when the Chuch is ſick and ſhattered into Schiſms, any more than <hi>Hippocrates</hi>'s Twins can live or die aſunder. This
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:58923:40"/>hath been too evident in all ages of the Church, eſpecially in theſe lat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter times, now ſo many falſe Prophets have riſen among us; and love (which is the bond of Peace) is waxen ſo cold, that iniquity doth abound, and get the upper hand<note n="ſ" place="margin">Mat. 24.12.</note>, particularly, in our Independent Congregations, and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Schiſmatical and Heretical Aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blies among us; who under pretence of ſerving God in their private Meet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings, have many times and often made ſecret Conſpiracies, and Treacherous Combinations againſt the State; that they may the better ſerve themſelves, and ruin the Church. Wherefore Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority being warned by their former miſchief, hath ſince moſt prudently (eſpecially in times of apparent dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger) took order for the ſuppreſſion of Conventicles and diviſions in the Church, that there may be no more ſuch evil conſequences in the State; but that all things being rightly or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered according to Gods preſcripti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on<note n="t" place="margin">1 Cor. 14. ult.</note>, we may have only peace, which God is the Author and appro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver of, as in all the Churches of the Saints<note n="u" place="margin">ver. 33.</note>
            </p>
            <pb n="77" facs="tcp:58923:40"/>
            <p n="2">2. Paſſively, by ſuffering his Kings will to be done on him, if it be unlaw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful, and may not be done by him. For the true Loyaliſt knows that as obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience to God, muſt be preferred be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore obedience to man<note n="w" place="margin">Act. 4.19.</note>: ſo he is com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded to <hi>be ſubject to the higher pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers</hi>
               <note n="x" place="margin">Rom. 13.1.</note>, which in ſuch a caſe cannot be without ſuffering: and therefore he is obedient, not only Actively, by doing his Kings Commandment when it is for the truth; but alſo Paſſively, by enduring it patiently when it is againſt the truth: as is evident in the exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of <hi>Shadrach, Meſhech,</hi> and <hi>Abed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nego,</hi> who did obey King <hi>Nebuchadez<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zar,</hi> not only actively, when he had given them Rule over the Province of <hi>Babylon;</hi> but alſo paſſively, (without the leaſt ſhew of Rebellion) when he commanded them to fall down and worſhip the Golden Image which he had ſet up<note n="y" place="margin">Dan. 3.</note>. And indeed where did you ever read of any Godly Martyrs or Martyr, that when he might not obey his King actively, yet refuſed to ſubmit himſelf to him paſſively? I am ſure the examples of the Apoſtles will teach you the contrary, and all
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:58923:41"/>the perſecutions of the Church. <hi>Luther</hi> therefore (that great Reformer of our Religion) when in his Reformation he was oppoſed by Authority, would ſay, That he had rather obey than work Miracles, if it were in his power: for obedience is due to Kings, not as they are men, but as they are powers or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dained of God, to be his Miniſters and Vicegerents. And ſo accordingly, <hi>Juli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an</hi> the Apoſtate's Souldiers, though they would not worſhip Idols at his com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand, becauſe God will not give his glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry to another, nor his praiſe to Graven Images<note n="z" place="margin">Iſa. 4.8.</note>; yet when he led them againſt an enemy, they obeyed him moſt rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dily: <hi>Diſtinguebant dominum tempora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lem à domino aeterno, &amp; tamen ſubditi erant propter dominum aeternum,</hi> ſaith <hi>Auguſtine;</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Auguſt.</hi> in Pſal. 124.</note> they had underſtanding in them to diſtinguiſh their temporal Lord from their eternal, and Religion too, to ſubject themſelves to their tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poral, for the ſake of their eternal. All power is from God, and alſo for God: let the Prince inveſted therewith abuſe it never ſo much for himſelf, as if it were his own; yet God can ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tract the greateſt good out of the great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt evil, and order it to his glory: and
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:58923:41"/>therefore the True Loyaliſt never uſes a Sword againſt his King, but a Buck<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler; never reſiſteth the Power, but is always ſubmiſſive (either actively or paſſively) not only for Wrath, but al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo for Conſcience ſake.</p>
            <p>If St. <hi>Paul</hi> indeed had ſaid, Let every ſoul be ſubject to Chriſtian and ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuous Powers, there might have been ſome Plea for Rebellion; but (to take away all ſcruple) he ſaith, to Powers indefinitely, in that they be Powers, as St. <hi>Peter</hi> expreſly, <hi>not only to the good and gentle, but alſo to the froward</hi>
               <note n="a" place="margin">1 Pet. 2.18.</note>.</p>
            <p>Sith then we are obliged by the Doctrine of St. <hi>Peter,</hi> and St. <hi>Paul,</hi> to ſubmit our ſelves to all Powers in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>definitely, let them be never ſo wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed and Tyrannous; how much rather ought we to fear and obey thoſe that are Peaceable and Religious, Defen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders of the Faith, and Nurſing Fathers to the Church? Whenas to ſuch there doth belong a double honour; an honour as they are Gods Miniſters, and Truſtees, and an honour as they are fearers of God, their Lord, and So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veraign<note n="b" place="margin">Pſ. 15.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note>. This is the glory of a Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:58923:42"/>this gives Vertue free ſcope, and makes True Loyalty the more opera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive.</p>
            <p>Yet we muſt remember that obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence and ſubjection is a thing ſo highly neceſſary, that it is enjoyned to all Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers indefinitely, not only the good, but the bad too. 1. In regard of the Predi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate, becauſe obedience unites men to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether, and makes them Victorious; it is the very ſtrength and bulwork of a Nation. 2. In regard of the Subject, becauſe wicked and Tyrannous Princes ſerve no leſs for our Tryal, than good ones for our Conſolation: and who would not be happy, eternally happy? <hi>Bleſſed is the man</hi> (ſaith St. <hi>James</hi>) <hi>that endureth temptation: For when he is tryed, he ſhall receive the Crown of life, which the Lord hath promiſed to them that love him</hi>
               <note n="c" place="margin">James 1.12.</note>.</p>
            <p>And accordingly, to ſhew the great neceſſity of this duty, the Lord himſelf (by his Apoſtle) hath here enforced o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedience to it, with two ſuch moving arguments, as they eminently compre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hend all.</p>
            <pb n="81" facs="tcp:58923:42"/>
            <p>The firſt may ſerve for an uſe of ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour, to fright all Fanaticks from Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bellion; for it is taken from the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding great danger of them that reſiſt the Powers: becauſe <hi>the Powers that be, are ordained of God. Whoſoever there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore reſiſteth the Power, reſiſteth the Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinance of God: and they that reſiſt, ſhall receive to themſelves damnation</hi>
               <note n="d" place="margin">Rom. 13.1, 2.</note>; in the vulgar Latine it is, <hi>acquirunt ſibi damnationem,</hi> they do acquire or pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaſe to themſelves damnation, to ſhew that Rebels above all Malefactors do the moſt worthily receive damnation; for what can a man receive into his poſſeſſion more worthily, than that which he receives by purchaſe? More<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>over to ſhew the great intereſt and propriety they have in damnation, they are ſaid not only to receive it, but to receive it to themſelves: they ſhall receive to themſelves damnation; and that both Temporal and Eternal.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Temporal, the very provoking a King to anger, incurreth death, without his mercy and Clemency. <hi>The fear</hi> or Wrath <hi>of a King</hi> (ſaith <hi>Solomon</hi>) <hi>is as the roaring of a Lyon: he that pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voketh him to anger ſinneth againſt his
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:58923:43"/>own Soul:</hi> That is, offendeth againſt his own life, hazzards and jeopards it<note n="e" place="margin">Pro. 20.2. &amp; 19.12.</note>. Yea, <hi>the Wrath of a King</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>is as the meſſengers of Death, without the wiſdom of the Wiſe to pacifie it</hi>
               <note n="f" place="margin">Pro. 16.14.</note> How much rather then doth that Curſed Traiter deſerve Death, (even that terrible and igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minious death the Laws of <hi>England</hi> have aſſigned him,) that hath ſo little fear of God before his eyes, as not to be afraid to ſtretch forth his hand to deſtroy the Lords anointed? Murder is a crying ſin, it cryeth for vengeance, vengeance<note n="g" place="margin">Gen. 4.10.</note>; but <hi>Regicide,</hi> what ſhall I term it? it is a Roaring ſin, it roareth louder than all the Diabolical voices in <hi>Plu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tarch</hi> did together, for the Ceſſation of their Oracles, upon the coming of our Saviour; for by Murder one ſingle perſon may be deſtroyed only, but by <hi>Regicide,</hi> the murder of a King, ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny times a whole Nation, even all the Members of a body Politick periſh in his ruine; as the body Natural doth by the loſs of the Head, from whence the Metaphor is drawn.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Eternal, and that moſt proper in this place; for though the word <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> here for damnation, make no difference between
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:58923:43"/>that condemnation which is Tempo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral, and that which is Eternal; the judgment of man in this life, and the judgment of God in the life to come<note n="h" place="margin">Rom. 2.2. Compared in the Orig. with Luk 23.40.</note>; yet the reaſon wherefore damnation here, is pronounced againſt them that reſiſt the Powers, being becauſe in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſting them, they reſiſt the Ordinance of God, doth plainly ſhew that it is chiefly meant, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, of eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal judgment. Scripture and Order requires that a ſin againſt God, be puniſhed with damnation eternal, and a ſin againſt man, as man, only with Temporal; and a Rebel ſins a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt both: He ſinneth againſt man, in that he reſiſteth the power of his King, as he is a man: He ſinneth a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt God, in that by reſiſting the Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er of his King, he reſiſteth the Ordinance of God. And therefore (as the word ſignifieth) he is guilty of both ſorts of puniſhment, not only Temporal, but chiefly Eternal; as is evident in the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample of <hi>Corah</hi> and his Accompli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, who becauſe in being gathered to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether againſt <hi>Moſes,</hi> and againſt <hi>Aa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ron,</hi> they were gathered together againſt the Lord; they were not per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted to die the common death of
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:58923:44"/>other men, but the Lord made a new thing, cauſed the Earth to open her mouth, and ſwallow them up quick into Hell<note n="i" place="margin">Numb. 16.</note>.</p>
            <p>The 2. is an uſe of comfort, both to draw Rebels to Loyalty, and to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courage True Loyaliſts therein; for it is taken <hi>ab utili,</hi> from the great good that flows from the Miniſtry of the King, to the bodies and ſouls of them that are obedient and do good: he is the Miniſter of God to thee for good<note n="k" place="margin">Rom. 13.3, 4.</note>; be thy Prince good or bad, (there is no exception in this reſpect) he is ſtill the Miniſter of God to thee for good; <hi>Si honus,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Auguſt.</hi> Serm. <hi>6.</hi> de verbis Dom. ſecundum Mat.</note> 
               <hi>nutritor eſt tuns;</hi> (ſaith St. <hi>Auſtin</hi>) <hi>ſi malus, tentator tuus eſt;</hi> if thy Prince be wicked and Tyran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nous, he is thy temper to exerciſe thy patience; whereby he becomes the cauſe of thy eternal good, by thy tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poral evil: But if he be good and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligious, a true defender of the Faith, he is thy Nurſe, yea, a nurſing Father to the whole Church; whereby he be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comes the Miniſter of God to thee for thy greater good, both Temporal and Eternal.</p>
            <pb n="85" facs="tcp:58923:44"/>
            <p n="1">1. For thy praiſe, <hi>do that which is good, and thou ſhalt have praiſe of the ſame</hi>
               <note n="l" place="margin">Rom. 13.3.</note>. Governours are ſent by the King, <hi>not only for the puniſhment of evil doers, but for the praiſe of them that do well</hi>
               <note n="m" place="margin">1 Pet. 2.14.</note>. Yea, if thou beeſt good and obedient, thy King, by the influ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence of his good Government, will not only promote his own honour<note n="n" place="margin">1 Sam. 2.30.</note>, but will be the Miniſter of God to thee for thy praiſe in all: fear thou the Lord and the King, and thou ſhalt have no need to praiſe thy ſelf; the lips of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, even ſtrangers ſhall give thee praiſe enough<note n="o" place="margin">Pſa. 15.4. Pro. 27.2.</note>: Yea, thy very enemies ſhall be at peace with thee<note n="p" place="margin">Pro. 16.7.</note>.</p>
            <p n="2">2. For thy profit, both in Church and State. 1. In the State, to protect thy body and eſtate, from the rage of ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies and adverſaries, both within and without the Common-Wealth; that thou mayeſt enjoy thy <hi>Meum</hi> and <hi>Tuum</hi> with the more peace and ſecurity. 2. In the Church, to defend thy Faith in its integrity; both by the aſſiſtance of god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Preachers, and learned Antagoniſts in the cauſe of Chriſt; and by a ſtrong fence of right Order and Diſcipline;
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:58923:45"/>that thou having no letts nor hinde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rances in thy Religion, mayeſt not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly have temporal happineſs, but alſo eternal: Therefore St. <hi>Paul</hi> exhorts us very earneſtly to make <hi>ſupplicati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, Prayers, interceſſions, and giving of thanks,</hi> not only <hi>for all men</hi> in ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral, but <hi>for Kings</hi> in a ſpecial man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, <hi>and for all that are in authority; that we may lead a quiet, and peacea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble life in all godlineſs and honeſty: for this is good</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>and accepta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble in the ſight of God our Saviour: Who will have all men to be ſaved, and come to the knowledge of the truth</hi>
               <note n="q" place="margin">1 Tim. 2.1, 2, 3, 4.</note>: To wit, by the means of wiſe and Religious Princes, ſuch as was <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantine</hi> the Great, that great Favourer of Religion, and Defender of the Faith.</p>
            <q>No Salvation out of Chriſt.</q>
            <p>
               <hi>Be wiſe now therefore O ye Kings: be inſtructed ye Judges of the Earth</hi>
               <note n="r" place="margin">Pſa. 2.10.</note>. Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider, that as you have your power, not from your ſelves, or from your Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects, but from God: ſo not for your ſelves, to ſatisfie your own luſts, car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal ends and intereſt; but alſo for God, to rule his people, nurſe his Church,
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:58923:45"/>and contain it in order. This is the end for which all Kings are ordained; the care of the Church is their great <hi>Depoſitum,</hi> the very burden of their charge<note n="ſ" place="margin">Iſa. 44.28. &amp; 49.23.</note>.</p>
            <p>But alas! all have not obeyed the Goſpel of Chriſt<note n="t" place="margin">Rom. 10.16.</note>: The <hi>Turks</hi> and <hi>Jews</hi> do yet ſtand out, and the fulneſs of the Gentiles is not yet come in<note n="u" place="margin">Rom. 11.25.</note>: though no people are found ſo Barbarous, but they will have ſome form of Religion or other to acknowledge a God by; as all <hi>India,</hi> Eaſt and Weſt, ſheweth: Yet many Kings of the Earth, and Heathen Rulers are ſo far from embra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing Chriſt and his Goſpel, that they ſtill ſet themſelves, and <hi>take Counſel together, againſt the Lord, and againſt his Anointed, ſaying, Let us break their Bands aſunder, and caſt away their Cords from us</hi>
               <note n="w" place="margin">Pſa. 2.2, 3.</note>.</p>
            <p>Eccleſiaſtical Hiſtory will inform you, that almoſt all ages of the Church have felt the rage of their perſecution<note n="x" place="margin">
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>Acts 4.</note>. But let them go on, they are left with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out excuſe; all have heard the glad tidings of Salvation; the ſound of the Goſpel hath gone out into all the Earth,
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:58923:46"/>and the words of it unto the ends of the World<note n="y" place="margin">Acts 2. Rom. 10.18. Pſal. 19.4.</note>. Neither let them dream that Salvation can be had in any thing out of Chriſt and his Goſpel. They indeed ſeeing through the glaſs of their puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, the curſed nature of Original ſin to be ebullient in their members, do with much Zeal and Devotion wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip God ignorantly in ſome Idol or other<note n="z" place="margin">Acts 17.23.</note>, thinking by their childiſh Ido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latry, and vain Incenſe and Oblations, either to expiate their ſin, and the ſad effects thereof, or to win Gods favour unto them<note n="a" place="margin">1 Kings 18.</note>. But alas! they are ſo far from doing of that, that robbing God of his due honour by their Idol-worſhip, they ſo much the more provoke him to anger againſt them<note n="b" place="margin">Jer. 11.17.</note>: It is as vain a thing for them to imagin that they cane be ſaved by the works of their own hands, as to conceit that they were made by them, or are preſerved; com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon reaſon teaching them (if their underſtanding were not darkned<note n="c" place="margin">Epheſ 4.18.</note>) That the former is as impoſſible to be done as the latter, without the Omnipo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent hand of a Deity: for Gods infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nite juſtice being wounded by ſin, deliverance from it is a new Creati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and a Reſurrection from Death
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:58923:46"/>and Damnation to life again; and therefore cannot poſſibly be effected by any thing, but by Chriſt, God, as well as man; and man too, as well as God; for both thoſe Natures, Divine and Humane, muſt neceſſarily be in the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of him who is our Redeemer, or elſe a peace could never have been conclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded between God and man: If he had not been God, he could not have ſatisfied the infinite juſtice of God, by fulfilling all righteouſneſs for man<note n="d" place="margin">Mat. 3.15.</note>, which man as man (by reaſon of his finiteneſs, and imperfect holineſs) could never do for himſelf: And if he had not been man, the ſatisfaction could not have been made in the ſame nature which ſinned, without which the ſatisfaction had been null, for want of mutuality.</p>
            <p>You ſee then that Salvation from the Wrath of God, cannot poſſibly be ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained by any vain and Anger-provo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king worſhip, which you perform, but only by Chriſt and his Mediatorſhip; God dwelling in our fleſh, perfect God, and perfect man. And therefore the Word of God (than which there is no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing ſo rational,) doth impute our Salvation only to Chriſt, neither is
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:58923:47"/>there Salvation in any other, <hi>for there is none other name under Heaven given among men, whereby we muſt be ſaved</hi>
               <note n="e" place="margin">Acts 4.12.</note>. And St. <hi>John</hi> ſaith, <hi>He that believeth on the Son, hath ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting life: and he that believeth not the Son, ſhall not ſee life: but the Wrath of God abideth on him</hi>
               <note n="f" place="margin">John 3.36. &amp; 17.3. Heb. 2.3. 1 John 5.10.</note>.</p>
            <p>O therefore as you tender your ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting Peace, delay no longer to kiſs the Son of God, Chriſt Jeſus our only Lord and Saviour<note n="g" place="margin">Pſal. 2.12.</note>, not with a <hi>Judas</hi>'s kiſs to betray him<note n="h" place="margin">Mat. 26.48.</note>; but with the mouth of Faith and obedience in token of ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage<note n="i" place="margin">1 Sam. 10.1.</note>, that he was Anointed to be your Lord and King by God the Father<note n="k" place="margin">Pſa. 89.27. Revel. 1.5. Phil. 2.8, 9.</note>; leſt by your infidelity ye periſh from the Way, the Truth, and the Life<note n="l" place="margin">John 14.6.</note>.</p>
            <p>And you O Chriſtian Kings that are already eſtabliſhed in the Faith, and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brace Chriſt and his Goſpel, (the only means of your Salvation) accompliſh ye the end of your Ordination: be ye true defenders of the Faith, and Nurſing Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers to the Church; that Chriſt may defend you from your enemies, and nurſe you in your Kingdoms: mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt your wiſdom by ſcattering the wicked in judgment, and bringing the
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:58923:47"/>Wheel over the ungodly, that the Lord may eſtabliſh your Thrones in righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs<note n="m" place="margin">Pro. 20.8, 26. &amp; 25.5.</note>; Let Chriſt rule in your hearts by Faith<note n="n" place="margin">Epheſ. 3.17. Col. 3.15.</note>, that you may rule his people the more faithfully: Pay ye True Loyalty and ſubjection to Chriſt your Lord and Maſter, that your Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects may the more chearfully pay you yours: In a word, have a care of in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſing your accounts, by negligence in your charge<note n="o" place="margin">Luk. 12.48.</note>: But crown your Sacred Office with Chriſtian examples, that at laſt you may exchange your cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruptible Crowns for Crowns of glory.</p>
            <p>But Laſtly, we muſt not forget, that if a King ſhould be wanting in his duty to fear the Lord; yet our duty is ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vertheleſs to fear the King: let him be what he will, that can be no excuſe to us; we muſt not forſake the Lord, for his ſake; but ſtill be ſubject unto him, for the Lords ſake. Wickedneſs in a King may bring deſtruction upon him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, but we know (from what hath been ſaid before) that it can be no plea for Rebellion. Yea, ſuppoſe a King ſhould be a notorious enemy, not only to the Lord, but to our ſelves too; yet for all that, we muſt not Rebel,
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:58923:48"/>but ſtill be ſubject and obedient: <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vid</hi> (a man after Gods own heart) when he was a Subject to King <hi>Saul</hi> (that remarkable Tyrant and Rebel againſt God) gives us in this a very fair example; for when the evil ſpirit of King <hi>Saul</hi> roſe up againſt him, and that ſo violently, that he ſought to ſmite him even to the Wall with his Ja<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>velin; and though afterwards he decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red his malice to be as great as <hi>Davids</hi> innocency, both by hunting him from place to place, like a Partridge upon the Mountains; and deviſing all the ways he could beſides to take away his life<note n="p" place="margin">1 Sam. 19.9, 10, &amp;c.</note>; yet (when he had him at his mercy, even at ſuch times when he came to at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tach him<note n="q" place="margin">1 Sam. 24. &amp;c. 26.</note>) he would by no means Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bel, lift up his hand or his heel againſt him; no, nor ſuffer thoſe that were about him to do it; though they much incited him thereunto, alledging that the day was come, in the which the Lord ſaid he would deliver his enemy into his hand. But alas! they ſavour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed not the things that be of God<note n="r" place="margin">Mat. 16.23.</note>, the Lord delivered him into his hand, not that he ſhould kill him, but only to try his Loyalty, whether he would kill him or not; and ſo the words fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:58923:48"/>interpret it, <hi>that thou mayeſt do to him as it ſhall ſeem good unto thee</hi>
               <note n="ſ" place="margin">1 Sam. 24.4, 5.</note>. And ſo accordingly he proved himſelf a True Loyaliſt indeed, the more he fear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the Lord, the more he feared the King; he cut off but the skirt of <hi>Sauls</hi> Robe, and his heart ſmote him, much leſs durſt he kill him<note n="t" place="margin">Pſal. 4.4.</note>. <hi>Satan</hi> for all his great policy could not prevail with him to do that; he ſaid unto hismen, <hi>The Lord forbid, that I ſhould do this thing unto my Maſter, the Lords anointed, to ſtretch forth mine hand againſt him, ſeeing he is the Anointed of the Lord: With theſe words</hi> David <hi>ſtaid his ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants, and ſuffered them not to riſe againſt Saul</hi>
               <note n="u" place="margin">1 Sam. 24.5, 6, 7.</note>. And when <hi>Abiſhai</hi> (for the ſame reaſon) would have killed him in the Wilderneſs of <hi>Ziph; Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vid</hi> was aſtoniſhed at his boldneſs and impudency, and forbad him with great indignation, ſaying, <hi>Who can ſtretch forth his hand againſt the Lords Anoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, and be guiltleſs</hi>
               <note n="w" place="margin">1 Sam. 26.</note>? But behold! inſtead of ſatisfying a revengeful na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture upon his enemy, he ſo pacified his wrath by yielding, that he even inforced tears from his eyes<note n="x" place="margin">1 Sam. 24.16, 17, &amp;c.</note>: made him promiſe him that he would do him no more harm, yea, confeſs his own fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, and bleſs him<note n="y" place="margin">1 Sam. 26.21, &amp;c.</note>.</p>
            <pb n="94" facs="tcp:58923:49"/>
            <p>This is ſo exactly according to what his Son <hi>Solomon</hi> hath taught us, <hi>Eccle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiaſtes.</hi> 10.4. that he may ſeem to have borrowed his Wiſdom and Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſel therein, from this very ſtory: the words are theſe, <hi>If the Spirit of the Ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler riſe up againſt thee, leave not thy place, for yielding pacifieth great offences. If the Spirit of thy Ruler riſe up againſt thee,</hi> let it be for what cauſe it will, yet for all that, thou muſt not leave thy place and rebel, to make him yield by conſtraint: but keep thy order and ſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion ſtill<note n="z" place="margin">1 Cor. 7.20, 24.</note>, and endeavour to pacifie him by yielding. This is the duty of us all, how great then is the ſin of them that leave their places, and riſe up againſt their Ruler, when his ſpirit is calm and ſedate? and by their Rebellion inforce him aftewards to riſe up againſt them, and yet refuſe to pacifie him by yielding, though themſelves have been the cauſe of his provocation? Fanaticks themſelves may be Judge, but withal let them repent, leſt by their pride and obſtinacy they alſo pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voke Gods anger againſt them. And in a word, let us all be as careful always to diſcharge out duty to the
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:58923:49"/>Lord and the King, that we may not make our ſelves for ever miſera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble by Rebellion; but that as Kings on Earth dye like men, ſo we in heaven may live like Kings<note n="a" place="margin">Pſal. 82.7. Revel. 5.10.</note>.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="2" type="part">
            <pb n="96" facs="tcp:58923:50"/>
            <head>Part II.</head>
            <p>NOw Secondly, that we may obtain this heavenly and Royal inheritance of the True Loyaliſt, and avoid the everlaſting perdition of Rebels, <hi>So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lomon</hi> alſo gives us a ſeaſonable cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, to <hi>meddle not with them that are given to change;</hi> for by Changers here are meant Rebels, ſuch as neither fear the Lord nor the King, but under an hypocritical pretence of being great Zelots in Religion, pride themſelves in nothing more than to rebel, and change the Laws and Ordinances of them both. And ſo accordingly, the Jews<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Weems Chriſt. Synag.</hi> Of Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil perſons, <hi>parag.</hi> 1. <hi>cap.</hi> 6. Sect. 7. <hi>p.</hi> 1 59.</note> termed them <hi>Shonim,</hi> Rebels; becauſe they varied from the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands of the Lord and the King. And hence came that Sect called <hi>Haſhonim,</hi> who taught that no King ſhould be acknowledged upon earth
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:58923:50"/>but God only. Such were the dege<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>generate <hi>Eſſens,</hi> who thought it im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piety to be ſubject to any man: and to come home to our ſelves, ſuch are our degenerate Papiſts, and Fanaticks too, they both make diviſion between the fear of the Lord and the fear of the King; as if theſe Changelings were wi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſer than the wifeſt who hath joyned and enjoyned them together. Yea, and that which is worſe, they are not a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fraid to make the fear of God, the reaſon of their Rebellion againſt the King. O what muſt one day be the judgment of theſe Brothers in blaſphe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my, <hi>Vox faucibus haeret,</hi> it is unex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſible! Yet we may gueſs at it by that terrible one, which befel <hi>Cora</hi> and his rebellious fraternity<note n="b" place="margin">Numb. 16.</note>; for they re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſemble them exactly, who under a pretence of being an holy aſſembly, men that greatly ſeared the Lord, ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thered themſelves together againſt <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes,</hi> and againſt <hi>Aaron</hi>
               <note n="c" place="margin">Ver. 3.</note>: and yet did moſt ſhamefully contradict themſelves therein, for in the very act they were gathered together againſt the Lord<note n="d" place="margin">Ver. 11.</note>; becauſe in reſiſting them, they reſiſted his Ordinance: For which cauſe the Lord made a new thing, cauſed the
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:58923:51"/>Earth to open her mouth, and ſwallow them up quick into Hell:<note n="e" place="margin">Ver. 30.</note> and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded his Servant <hi>Moſes</hi> too, to ſpeak unto the reſt of the Congregation, who were not Confederates with them in the rebellion, to depart from the tents of theſe wicked men, and to touch no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing of theirs, leſt they were conſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med in all their ſins.<note n="f" place="margin">Ver. 26.</note>
            </p>
            <p>Now, for this very reaſon it is, that <hi>Solomon</hi> hath here joyned and enjoyned the fear of the Lord and the King toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther; that conſidering by this example, that it is impoſſible for them to fear the Lord, without fearing the King, they might no more be ſo impudently wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, to rebel againſt their King, and yet pretend Religion for the ſame, and the fear of God.</p>
            <p>And, 2. For the ſame reaſon, he alſo giveth us this ſeaſonable caution, to <hi>meddle not with them that are gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven to change,</hi> or not to be of their party who enterpriſe any alteration from Kingly Government, and vary from the Laws and Statutes of the Lord and the King; leſt (by confederation with them in their Rebellion) we be
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:58923:51"/>alſo conſumed in all their ſins: <hi>for their calamity</hi> (ſaith he, in the verſe following) <hi>ſhall riſe ſuddenly, and who knoweth the ruine of them both?</hi> Both Changers from the fear of the Lord, and Changers from the fear of the King.</p>
            <p>And both the Papiſts and Fanaticks are notorious Changes from them both; for though it be true, they do as un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brotherly daſh one againſt another in their opinions, as <hi>Manaſſes</hi> and <hi>Ephra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>im:</hi> Yet they are as firmly agreed to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether againſt the King, or rather the Lord and the King, as they were a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt <hi>Juda;</hi>
               <note n="g" place="margin">Iſa. 9.21.</note> for their Combination againſt the King, is only that in his de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction, they may the better build up themſelves out of the ruines of Gods Government and his Church: And therefore it comes to paſs, that as Chriſt, the Head of the Church,<note n="h" place="margin">Eph. 5.23.</note> was crucified between two Thieves;<note n="i" place="margin">Mat. 27.38.</note> ſo the King, his Vicegerent, for the ſake of his Church, is Crucified between theſe two Malefactors: by the Papiſts on the one hand, and by the Fanaticks on the other.</p>
            <pb n="100" facs="tcp:58923:52"/>
            <p>I begin with the Papiſts, not only becauſe they are thought to Witch ride the Fanaticks into Rebellion; but be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they are the moſt antient Chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers: They were the firſt, that chang<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the Truth of God into a lie.<note n="k" place="margin">2 Theſ. 2.</note> How oft hath Anti-Chriſt and his Satanical Emiſſaries attempted to change our Religion into their abominable Idola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try, and to warp it again from its pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitive rule of reformation, with their ſuperſtitious vanities, and how oft too have they attempted to bring our Necks again, under the yoke of their intollerable Tyranny; that they might make a prey of the ſat of our Land, to feed the unſatiable appetites of their Avarice, Pride, and Luxury? They that have read <hi>Fox's Acts and Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>numents,</hi> and other Eccleſiaſtical Hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtories, cannot be ignorant of what doleful Tragedies they have acted upon this Theatre of <hi>England:</hi> How often the Whore of <hi>Babylon</hi> and her brood have endeavour'd to drown our Church with the blood of Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyrs: though (contrary to their ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pectation) God made their blood to fructifie more Flowers in his Garden,<note n="l" place="margin">Cant. 4.1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. &amp;c.</note>
               <pb n="101" facs="tcp:58923:52"/>than the wild blood of the <hi>Danes</hi> is ſaid to have bred Weeds<note n="*" place="margin">Theſe weeds (they ſay) having (at ſome time in the year) a bloody juice in them, (like the <hi>Indian</hi> Tree <hi>Anatar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dion</hi>) and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing moſtly ſound in ſuch places where the <hi>Danes</hi> are thought to be ſlain, are ſaid by the vulgar to have ſprung from their blood, and accordingly called <hi>Danes</hi> Weed. Howſoever, <hi>Sanguis mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyrum Semen eſt Eccleſiae.</hi>
               </note> in this Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. Nor how many deſperate ſtabs they have made at the breaſt of our Princes; nor deadly blows at the heart of the State; nor how much life and vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gor they have put into many Inſurre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions and Rebellions in the bowels of the Kingdom: Their deſperate deſign in Eighty Eight to cut us all off, root and branch, from being a Nation, that the name of a reformed Church in <hi>England</hi> might be had no more in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membrance,<note n="m" place="margin">Pſal. 83.4.</note> did not a little proclaim their inveterate malice againſt us: But their Treachery in the Gunpowder Plot, to blow us all up at one blow, did manifeſt it to the very life; for that (as one obſerves) was the very Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter-piece of all the Policy of <hi>Rome</hi> and Hell. O mercileſs cruelty! No Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon like to that, unleſs it were the Treaſon of Satan againſt the State of man in Paradiſe, to blow up all man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kind in <hi>Adam,</hi> the repreſentative of it, at once.</p>
            <p>But I am not a renewing any Hiſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, to make them the more famous for infamy; neither need I, they are fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:58923:53"/>enough for that already: my buſineſs is only to remind you of ſome chief remarks of their helliſh Treaſons and Maſſacres, that you may be the more wary for the future how you meddle with theſe Changers; for not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding all their former fruſtrati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons and diſappointments, their malice againſt us is as uncapable of diſheart<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, as <hi>Balaam</hi> was in his attempts of curſing <hi>Iſrael:</hi> Let God appear never ſo often againſt them, let the Angel of the Lord ſtand with a drawn Sword in his hand, they will on yet again.<note n="n" place="margin">Numb. 22.2 Pet. 2.15, 16.</note> This was but lately<note n="*" place="margin">An. Dom. <hi>1678.</hi>
               </note> too apparent in their horrid Treaſon, and murderous attempts againſt the Sacred perſon of our now moſt gracious Soveraign Lord King <hi>Charles</hi> the Second, of e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver bleſſed memory, next under God and his Chriſt our Saviour and Prince of peace.</p>
            <p>And as their malice begets cruelty; ſo their cruelty ſeldom of never goes without craſt: The Churches enemies are <hi>Serpentina Soboles,</hi> the ſeed of the Serpent. And as the way of a Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent upon a Rock is unknowable,<note n="o" place="margin">Prov. 30.18, 19.</note> ſo are their ways too of undermining the
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:58923:53"/>Church,<note n="p" place="margin">Neh. 4.11. Exod. 1.10.</note> craft and cruelty are their chiefeſt Engines of miſchief, not one, but both; they exerciſe craft for the ſake of their cruelty, that it may wound the deeper and the more aſſuredly: <hi>in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>genium ſuperat virès,</hi> Policy makes the Sword of malice cut keener than ſtrength doth: Therefore as the Devil when he intends to be the greateſt <hi>Abaddon</hi> or <hi>Apollyon,</hi> a deſtroyer,<note n="q" place="margin">Revel. 9.11.</note> ever joyns Reynolds tail to his Lyons skin:<note n="r" place="margin">Eph. 6.11.</note> So his Auxiliaries, thoſe that fight under his Banner, when they in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend the moſt miſchief againſt the Churches peace and welfare, ever add craft to their cruelty. And ſo accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ingly theſe Emiſſaries of Satan and Anti-Chriſt did in their forementioned plot againſt his Sacred Majeſty, when they murdered<note n="*" place="margin">The Tryal of Sir <hi>Edmond<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bury Godfrey</hi>'s murderers, at the Kings-Bench-bar, at <hi>Weſtminſter,</hi> on <hi>Munday</hi> the <hi>10th</hi> of <hi>Feb. An. Dom</hi> 1679. Where, upon full evidence they were convicted, and received ſentence ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cordingly, on <hi>Tueſday</hi> the next day ſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loveing. Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted 1679.</note> Sir <hi>Edmundbury God<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>frey,</hi> one of his Majeſties moſt Loy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al Juſtices; for they perpetrated that crying ſin leſt their helliſh Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon ſhould be diſcovered by their own confeſſions, which that worthy Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate had lately taken from them: and the rather, becauſe they did as greatly hate him for his great ſincerity in the True Proteſtant Religion, as for beng ſo active and induſtrious in the diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:58923:54"/>of their Plot. O man! or Prophet ſhall I term thee, (for thou didſt fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tel that thou ſhould'ſt be the firſt Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyr, and I hope thou ſhalt be the laſt though our Religion will not ſuffer us to be ſo wicked, ſilly and ridiculous to worſhip thee as a Saint; yet thy name is to be ever honoured for thy True Loyalty and Fidelity to the Lord and the King. Neither was their craft leſs ſeen in the mode of his murder: One while they dog'd him into the fields: Another while they ſent people to ſpie when he came abroad, that they might follow him into ſome dark Alley, or other obſcure and unfrequented place, and there diſpatch him. And though their expectation was ſplit in that, yet their craft and cruelty was ſtill the ſame; for as he was coming from a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout St. <hi>Clements</hi> Church towards his own houſe, near <hi>Charing-Croſs,</hi> (about 7 or 8 a Clock at night,) notice being given them of his approach near to <hi>Som<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t</hi>-houſe, they met him at the back gate, and that under a pretence of part<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a fray, (a counterſeit ſcuffle being made between two of them, a Prieſt and another, for the purpoſe,) for know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that he was a man always careful
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:58923:54"/>to keep the peace, and puniſh them that broke it, they thought it a very apt means to train him into the yard, where (the fray parting of its ſelf) they moſt cowardly ſtrangled him, on a ſuddain, before he had time to put himſelf into a poſture of defence leſt through his valiantneſs he ſhould have put them all to the rout. And now having killed his body, in the next place (to wave ſuſpicion from them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves) they endeavour to kill his re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putation, and lay the blame of this foul murder upon himſelf; for as ſoon as opportunity had given them the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veniency to carry him forth, they caſt him into a Ditch; where they left him, with his Gold and Silver in his pocket, and his own Sword thruſt through him: But laid his Glvoes, Stick, and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther things upon the bank; that ſo the world might conclude, that he was male-contented, and had laid violent hands upon himſelf; and his relations to ſave his Eſtate, had run him through. Though all that knew him, knew that he was not at all troubled in mind, or diſcontented, but only at their villany; for fear their helliſh treaſon ſhould not be diſcovered ſoon enough, before
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:58923:55"/>it had taken effect to the ruine of his King and Country. Yet when this was firſt noiſed abroad, there was ſuch ſtrangeneſs in the report, that (till ſuch time as providence had diſcovered their treachery) it filled the whole Nation with wonder, and amazement, and ſet all True Loyaliſts at a ſtand. O how did the Lord for a while ſeem to favour the proceedings of theſe bloody Aſſaſſinates! <hi>The children of this world</hi> (ſaith our Saviour) <hi>are in their Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rations wiſer than the Children of light.</hi>
               <note n="f" place="margin">Luke 16.8.</note> But alas! their greateſt wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom is but fooliſhneſs with God:<note n="t" place="margin">1 Cor. 1.8.</note> for thanks be unto his mercy, he quick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly fruſtrated the tokens of theſe Liars, and made theſe Diviners mad he tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned their wiſemen backward, he de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroyed their wiſdom, and made their knowledge fooliſhneſs:<note n="u" place="margin">Iſa. 44.25.</note> He cauſed theſe Changers to bring up birds<note n="*" place="margin">Dr. <hi>Oates</hi> Mr. <hi>Bedlow,</hi> and Mr. <hi>Cole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man.</hi>
               </note> to peck out their own eyes. He ſuffered Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tan to delude them with pride<note n="†" place="margin">They were ſo far from contri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, that they made a Narrative of the murder, and gloried in it as a moſt Conſcientious, Charitable, and Heroick act, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> purſuant to the Decrees of the Council of <hi>Lattran.</hi>
               </note> and ſelf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conceitedneſs for a while, that he might change their glory into the greater
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:58923:55"/>ſhame,<note n="w" place="margin">Hoſea 4.7.</note> he took them in their own craftineſs like <hi>Haman,</hi>
               <note n="x" place="margin">Eſther 7.10.</note> and made their Counſel to carry them headlong, like <hi>Achitophel</hi>'s to the Gallows.<note n="y" place="margin">2 Sam. 17.23. Job 5.13.</note>
            </p>
            <div type="subpart">
               <head>The Pope the Antichriſt.</head>
               <p>But this puniſhment was but tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poral, which they did moſt deſervedly receive as they were Changers from the fear of the King; there is a ſadder be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hind, an eternal one, as they were alſo Changers from the fear of the Lord: not only in that they reſiſted his Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance, in reſiſting the power of his Vicegerent; but alſo in that therein they ſought the ſubverſion of all his o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Doctrine and Diſcipline, in this his Church of <hi>England,</hi> as well as others: For theſe Changers were the Emiſſaries of the Pope, the Lords greateſt Adver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary and Opponent; and therefore not unfitly termed (by our Apoſtle) <hi>the man of Sin:</hi>
                  <note n="z" place="margin">2 Theſ. 2.3.</note> Nor by St. <hi>John the Anti-Chriſt.</hi>
                  <note n="a" place="margin">1 John 2.18.</note> There be indeed (ſaith he) many other Anti Chriſts in the World; every Heathen is ſuch an An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ti-Chriſt; he confeſſeth not that Jeſus Chriſt is come in the fleſh.<note n="b" place="margin">2 John 7.</note> The <hi>Turk,</hi> every falſe Religion, and every Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tick
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:58923:56"/>is alſo ſuch an Anti-Chriſt; for though many of them do Hiſtorically, and Diabolically confeſs that Jeſus Chriſt is come in the fleſh.<note n="c" place="margin">Mat. 4.11. James 2.19.</note> Yet they doctrinally deny him<note n="d" place="margin">Mat. 10.33.</note> by being a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhamed to confeſs,<note n="e" place="margin">Mark 8.38.</note> or by believing in him contrary to his word, the ſaving of the Soul:<note n="f" place="margin">Heb. 10.39.</note> but there is a great deal of difference between theſe Anti-Chriſts, and the <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. The Anti-Chriſt, the man of Sin, and the Son of perdi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion: This great Anti-Chriſt doth not only reſiſt Chriſt in his Doctrine, like theſe Anti-Chriſts, but he goeth be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond them; he is empatically the Liar, he denyeth both the Father and the Son,<note n="g" place="margin">1 Joh. 2.22.</note> and reſiſteth them alſo in their Divine and incommunicable headſhip and prerogatives. 1. In their headſhip, he ſitteth in Chriſts Chair,<note n="h" place="margin">Ezek. 37.22. John 10.16. Eph. 4.5, 6.</note> and makes himſelf his univerſal Vicar, and Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop; another head with him to over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſee the government of his Church, Which is a thing repugnant even to common reaſon it ſelf, it inferring both redundancy, and defect in his head<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip. 1. Redundancy or ſuperfluity, there being heads ſufficient already, beſides the Pope, for external polity. 2. Defect becauſe an humane head is
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:58923:56"/>too little for ſo great a body, as the univerſal Church; for it is impoſſible (as Biſhop <hi>Jewel</hi> ſpeaks in his Apolo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gy) that any mortal ſhould conceive or comprehend in his mind the whole Church, to govern it; it being of ſo large extent, and divided by Seas into ſo many Countries, therefore the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture maketh Chriſt alone the Head of the Church.<note n="i" place="margin">Eph. 5.23.</note> Head over all things, (not ſome things only, but all things) to the Church.<note n="k" place="margin">Eph. 1.22.</note> Yet, 2. under this poor and groundleſs pretence, this deceiver of Nations doth reſiſt him alſo in his Divine and incommunicable preroga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tives, that are inſeparably annexed to his headſhip. He uſurpeth all Chriſts power and Prerogatives over his Church: he as God, ſitteth in the tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of God, ſhewing himſelf that he is God;<note n="l" place="margin">2 Theſ. 2.4.</note> and what mortal is there but the Pope that doth all this? He moſt proudly, impudently, and abſurdly unites two diſtinct Offices, the Kingly and the Prieſtly, in himſelf, which is his due alone, who is firſt a King, then <hi>a Prieſt for ever after the Order of Mel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chizedeck,</hi>
                  <note n="m" place="margin">Heb. 7.</note> he oppoſeth and exalteth himſelf above all that is called God, or that is worſhiped;<note n="n" place="margin">2 Theſ. 24.</note> he maketh himſelf
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:58923:57"/>King of Kings, he taketh upon him to ſet them up, and put them down at pleaſue. And he uſurpeth Chriſts Prieſtly Office too, he alſo maketh himſelf the Prince of Paſtors, the Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop of Biſhops, yea, the great Biſhop of Souls: He equalizeth his humane traditions to the word of God; he pleads infallibility, and makes his word <hi>de fide</hi> in Controverſies; and he takes upon him too to forgive ſins, and produce a Pardon. All which (every one know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth, that knoweth the Scriptures) are the Royal and incommunicable Prero<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gatives of the Father and the Son. And what ſhould I ſay more? <hi>Panormitan,</hi> one of the Popes hired Proctors, (as Biſhop <hi>Jewel</hi>
                  <note n="*" place="margin">Defence of the Apol. Part 2. <hi>p.</hi> 95.</note> obſerves) ſaith, <hi>Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtus &amp; Papa faciunt unum conſiſtorium, &amp; excepto peccato, Papa poteſt, quicquid Deus ipſe poteſt.</hi> Chriſt and the Pope make one Conſiſtory, and keep one Court: and ſin only excepted, the Pope can do, whatſover God himſelf can do.</p>
               <p>Now conſider this, and then judge whether the Pope be not the <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, the very Anti-chriſt, the man of Sin in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed? for what is more <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> to Chriſt than ſin? I am ſure that he of all ſinners
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:58923:57"/>is the greateſt Changer of the ſear and Ordinances of the Lord and the King. I be not afraid to publiſh this; for before the great and terrible day of the Lord do come, (which cannot be long, God knows when) <hi>the man of Sin</hi> muſt be revealed:<note n="o" place="margin">2 Theſ. 2.2, 3.</note> His pride which at firſt raiſed him, ſhall in the concluſion give him a fall as low as perdition. The King of <hi>France</hi> (as we hear)<note n="*" place="margin">The <hi>London Gazitte,</hi> Pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhed by Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority, <hi>Paris.</hi> March 28. <hi>A. D.</hi> 1682.</note> hath begun lately to effect it; he hath by a perpetual and irrevocable Edict (which was regiſtred in Parliament the 23 inſtant) approved and confirm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the opinion of his Clergy againſt him, in four very important points. 1. That the King is Independent in things Temporal; that he cannot be Depoſed, nor his Subjects Abſolved of their Allegiance for any cauſe what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever. 2. That a General Council is a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove the Pope, purſuant to the Decrees of the Council of <hi>Conſtance.</hi> 3. That the Power of the Pope is to be limited by the Ancient Canons; and that he cannot do any thing to the prejudice of the Ancient uſages, and the liberties of the <hi>Gallican</hi> Church. 4. That the Deci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions of the Pope in points of Faith; are not infallible without the conſent of the
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:58923:58" rendition="simple:additions"/>Church. By this he hath ſhewed a moſt excellent example, for all other Kingdoms and Principalities to demo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh the Popes pride, and ſupremacy. Whereby without all doubt, he hath purchaſed more honour, than all his Predeceſſors have done before him: And we hope in God, <hi>who hath the Kings heart in his hand,</hi>
                  <note n="p" place="margin">Prov. 21.1.</note> that he will perſevere, and purchaſe to himſelf yet more and more, by a gradual Refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation of all his Antichriſtian Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrines, according to the Primitive pat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tern of our Church of <hi>England.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>For 3. Anti-Chriſt deformed the Church by degrees; and 'tis not likely he ſhould be reformed without degrees: had a time to fall away, he was not formed all at once; the myſtery of ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity did at firſt only begin to work.<note n="q" place="margin">2 Theſ. 2.3, 7.</note> Yet he will tell you that he had his beginning from the Holy Apoſtle St. <hi>Peter,</hi> but marvel not at that, for he is <hi>the man of Sin,</hi> he treads in the ſteps of his Father <hi>Lucifer,</hi>
                  <note n="r" place="margin">Iſa. 14.13, 14.</note> he was devoid of the truth from the beginning: And accordingly by St. <hi>John</hi> (as you heard before) he is called a Liar.<note n="ſ" place="margin">1 John 2.22.</note> Nor marvel that his followers have credited
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:58923:58"/>him in that report for <hi>his coming is after the working of Satan, with all Power, Signs, and lying Wonders, to deceive them into unrighteouſneſs: To whom, becauſe they received not the love of the truth, that they might be ſaved, the Lord hath ſent ſtrong deluſion, that they might be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve a lie, to their damnation.</hi>
                  <note n="t" place="margin">2 Theſ. 2.9, 10, 11, 12.</note> For the truth is, from the firſt Plantation of Chriſtianity in <hi>Rome,</hi> till the time of <hi>Gregory</hi> the Great, Biſhop of <hi>Rome,</hi> (not Anti-Chriſt, but St. <hi>Gregory</hi>) when <hi>John</hi> biſhop of <hi>Conſtantinople</hi> uſurped the title of Univerſality, there was no ſuch thing as the name of an Univerſal Biſhop heard of to be in <hi>Rome,</hi> (&amp; I ſuppoſe no where elſe in the World) as plainly ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pears by an Epiſtle which this St. <hi>Greg.</hi> ſent to this <hi>John</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Conſtantinople,</hi> to reprove him for uſurping that proud and wicked title of Univerſality; his words are theſe, <hi>Nullus</hi>
                  <note n="†" place="margin">
                     <hi>Gregory lib.</hi> 4. Epiſt. 36.</note> 
                  <hi>unquam prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deceſſorum meorum hoc tam prophano vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cabulo uti conſenſit:</hi> There was never any of my predeceſſors that would be called by this prophane title. And in another Epiſtle<note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>Gregory lib.</hi> 4. Epiſt. 38.</note> (having reſembled him to <hi>Lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cifer</hi>) he ſaith thus unto him, <hi>Tu quid Chriſto, <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſalis Sanctae Eccleſiae capiti, in extremi judiciies dicturus examine, qui
<pb n="114" facs="tcp:58923:59"/>cuncta ejus membra tibimet conaris <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſalis appellatione ſupponere:</hi> What anſwer wilt thou make in the Tryal of the laſt judgment, unto Chriſt, the Head of his Univerſal Church; that thus by the name of Univerſal Biſhop, ſeekeſt to bring under thee all the mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers of his body? No wonder then, if Anti-Chriſt and his Crue, have endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voured to ſuppreſs his works. But to come nearer home, <hi>Eleutherius</hi>
                  <note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>Fox's Acts and Monu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments,</hi> p. 146. And <hi>Iſaacſons</hi> Appen. of the Plantation &amp; Encreaſe of Chriſtianity, in the Iſle of Great <hi>Britain.</hi>
                  </note> (who became Biſhop of <hi>Rome</hi> A. D. 177.) in a Letter to <hi>Lucius,</hi> the firſt Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an King, (who began his Rule over the <hi>Britains,</hi> A. D. 170.) upon his pious requeſt for inſtructions in Chriſtianity, acknowledgeth him to be Gods only Vicar in his own Kingdom. And indeed if no ſuch Teſtimonies could have been produced, it muſt needs be a very Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſtian thing, ſo much as to conceit that the holy Apoſtle St. <hi>Peter</hi> ſhould be ſo wicked, as to break any Canon of the Apoſtles, who made ont,<note n="*" place="margin">Canon 36.</note> that no Biſhop under pain of deprivation, ſhould dare to intermeddle beyond his own bounds, in anothers Province, as being no ways ſubject to him.</p>
               <pb n="115" facs="tcp:58923:59"/>
               <p>St. <hi>Peter</hi> then is free from giving be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning to Anti-Chriſt, nor will the Primitive Biſhops allow him his Supre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>macy: Where then will he fix? What, in <hi>Lucifer?</hi> His coming is after the working of Satan, from him he de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rives his Pedegree. The times were pure at firſt, Anti-Chriſt then only began to work, he roſe in his myſterie f iniquity by degrees; firſt above Biſhops, then above Patriarchs, then above Councils, then above Kings, then above Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures; then at laſt, ſeeing he could mount no higher, he as God, ſits him down in the Temple of God, ſhewing himſelf that he is God.</p>
               <p>I need not plead that time cal's me away to other things, this is enough to convince any rational man, that the Pope is really the <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, the ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Anti-Chriſt, <hi>the man of Sin,</hi> and the Son of perdition. Who then would be a Papiſt? ſurely none, but thoſe <hi>whom the God of this World hath blinded:</hi>
                  <note n="u" place="margin">2. Cor. 4.4.</note> I know that there is no Religion in the World, hath ſo great a Decoy in it, to make Carnal men to profeſs it, as Popery hath; it is more ſelf plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing, and gives fuller reins to fleſh and
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:58923:60"/>blood, than any other; but nothing mor doth manifeſt it to be from <hi>the man of Sin.</hi>
                  <note n="*" place="margin">Richard Bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton <hi>of the Wars in</hi> Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land, Scotland <hi>and</hi> Ireland. <hi>p. 49.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Mervin</hi> Lord <hi>Audly</hi> and Earl of <hi>Caſtlehaven</hi> doth give us a ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry remarkable inſtance in this: He was educated in the Proteſtant Religion, but turned Papiſt, to have the more liberty to commit wickedneſs: in which he grew to ſo great an height, that (in the year 1631.) being condemned by his Peers for Rape and Sodomy, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> he impudently declared in the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence of ſome Lords, that as others had their ſeveral delights, ſome in one thing, ſome in another; ſo his delight was in Damning Souls, by enticing men to ſuch acts as might ſurely effect it. And marel not, that ſome of them have more art to hide their wickedneſs; for Satan himſelf is transformed into an Angel of light.<note n="w" place="margin">2 Cor. 11.13, 14, 15.</note>
               </p>
               <p n="1">1. Therefore let us beware of theſe falſe Prophets, and deceitful workers, that are thus notoriouſly give to change from the fear of the Lord and the King; leſt we be alſo inſerted with them into the family of Anti-Chriſt, and adopted the Sons of perdition.</p>
               <pb n="117" facs="tcp:58923:60"/>
               <p n="2">2. Let us remember to render unto God, due praiſe and thankfulneſs for all his former benefits,<note n="x" place="margin">Pſal. 103. Pſal. 68.19.</note> wherewith he hath continually loaded this undeſerv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Nation, in many wonderful delive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rances of our King and Country from their reſtleſs and unwearied Craft and Cruelty; leſt our ingratitude hold his hand from bleſſing us with future mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies: For <hi>qui non eſt gratus datis, non eſt dignus dandis;</hi> He that is not thank<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful for benefits already received, is not worthy to receive any more.</p>
               <p>Laſtly, Let us not forget to pray un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to God moſt earneſtly, that he will ſtill confound all their plots and ſtratagems, and maugre all their malice, ſtill pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tect his Majeſty under the ſhadow of his Wings;<note place="margin">Pſal. 57.1.</note> that he our King may en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joy a long, and proſperous Reign over us; and we his Subjects may lead a quiet and peaceable life under him, in all godlineſs and honeſty: For happy is that people that is in ſuch a caſe: Yea, <hi>happy is that people, whoſe God is the Lord.</hi>
                  <note n="y" place="margin">Pſ. 144.15.</note>
               </p>
               <pb n="118" facs="tcp:58923:61"/>
               <p n="2">2. For the Fanaticks, they bring up the Reer; yet they march not far be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hind: Yea, time was when they went before; and diſquieted the Nation with this evil, (the greateſt under the Sun) Folly was ſet in great dignity, and the Rich and Honourable were detruded into low places: Thinkers and Coblers, and ſuch like heaved themſelves upon the Horſes of their Princes, and made them walk as ſervants upon the earth<note n="z" place="margin">Eccleſiaſtes 10.6, 7. Pro. 19.10. &amp; 30.22.</note>. Neither was this the height of their am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bition; they fulfilled Mother <hi>Shipton</hi>'s <hi>Prophecy</hi> before the time: they called a Parliament of High ſhoes, to raſe the Palace with Hob-nails; and tread down all Royalty and Loyalty: They pluck't the King from his Throne, and ſet upon it no better than a Brewer. Yea, they were tickled ſo much with pride and Covetouſneſs, that they did not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly attempt as the Papiſts did, but they actually made their King a Martyr. <hi>Et quid non mortalia pectora cogis Auri ſacra fames?</hi> And what wickedneſs is there, that the love of money doth not tempt the hearts of men unto? Covetouſneſs is rightly ſtiled the root of all evil; the King being gone, they quickly chang<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed
<pb n="119" facs="tcp:58923:61"/>Monarchy (Gods own Government) into Oligarchy; whereby they made the Common wealth our Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>woe; both by changing the order of nature into Anarchy and Confuſion, and giving reins to their licentiouſneſs to play <hi>Rex's</hi> both in Church and State.</p>
               <p>As, 1. Having cantonized<note n="*" place="margin">Hiſt. <hi>Inde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pend.</hi> Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleat. Part 1. <hi>p.</hi> 89.</note> the Kingdom amongſt themſelves, (<hi>Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deaux</hi> the Poſt-maſter being King of the <hi>Weſt-Saxons</hi>) and murdered their King to maintain their unjuſt poſſeſſions, they make a re-entry (as it were) up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on what they had formerly uſurped, to lay the faſter hold: and make new di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſions too of the beſt places and prefer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments in the Nation: They impriſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the Gentry, and reduced<note n="†" place="margin">Hiſt. <hi>Inde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pend.</hi> Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleat. Part 1. <hi>p.</hi> 65.</note> them to the condition of conquered Slaves, they plundered, and left them almoſt quite naked, and enforced free quarter from all, and would not ſuffer any to be Maſter, ſo much as of his own Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mily. Yea, theſe <hi>Harpyes,</hi> theſe <hi>Ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>canthropi</hi> poſſeſſed themſelves of the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heritance and Eſtates of all, whom they at pleaſure would make a De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>linquent, not ſparing ſo much as the
<pb n="120" facs="tcp:58923:62"/>Dead<note n="*" place="margin">Hiſt. <hi>Inde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pend.</hi> Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleat. Part 1. <hi>p.</hi> 128, 129, 130.</note> from Sequeſtration; as it fareth with the head, ſo with the members; when they had once deſtroyed the King, they make all true Loyaliſts both Clergy and Laity take up their Croſs, and follow him, as he did his Saviour. Not unlike the ſavage <hi>Tartars,</hi> who when their great <hi>Cham</hi> dies, caſt ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of his deareſt friends after him.</p>
               <p>For, 2. Theſe <hi>Lord-Danes,</hi> (with the vulgar <hi>Lurdanes,</hi>) killed their King, not only for the ſake of his Inheritance, and his Nobles, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> but alſo for the ſake of the Churches Patrimony. For all their fine words and fair ſpeeches, they ſerved not the Lord Jeſus, but their own belly<note n="a" place="margin">Rom. 16.17, 18.</note>. The Presbyterians have much to anſwer for this: For tho' they knew<note n="*" place="margin">They could not chuſe but know it, (if Envy and Covetouſneſs had not blinded their eyes) it being not only evident by Gods general rule, 1 Cor. 14.40. the perpetual Law of Order, which ſaith <hi>Ariſtole</hi> is <hi>ipſa ratio,</hi> rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon it ſelf: but alſo throughly proved (over and over) both by other Scriptures, and Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity.</note> that Epiſcopacy was the Primitive Government, yet they made the world believe that they could not endure the order and title of a Biſhop. And why ſo? The reaſon is, becauſe it was not ſutable to their changing; they muſt have ſome hypocriti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal pretence or other, or elſe they could
<pb n="121" facs="tcp:58923:62"/>not have changed. <hi>Oliver Cromwell</hi> taught them an example, he (as you have heard) would not be called a King, no, by no means; yet he would be more than a King: So theſe; though they would not have the name of a Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop, no, by no means; yet they would have been more than Biſhops, if they could: for as ſoon as the King (their Protector) was once removed, they actually took poſſeſſion of as much lands and livings of theirs as they could. No Biſhop, no King, was the wiſe ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of King <hi>James:</hi> and no King, no Biſhop, hath been ſeen to be as true as that. But the torrent of their Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>touſneſs did not ſtop here, it alſo waft<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed them over into the faireſt Vine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yards of the inferior Clergy; which (if they, the right owners, demonſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted themſelves to be True Loyaliſts, men that feared the Lord and the King, by refuſing to take their unreaſonable, and abominable League and Covenant) they took into their poſſeſſion, as readi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and as jollily, as <hi>Ahab,</hi> when he took poſſeſſion of the fair Vineyard of <hi>Naboth</hi>
                  <note n="b" place="margin">1 King. 21.19.</note>.</p>
               <p>But 3. The licentiouſneſs, Anarchy
<pb n="122" facs="tcp:58923:63"/>and confuſion of theſe Changers is moſt perſpicuous in the ſubverſion of the Churches Diſcipline, and all Gods Laws and Ordinances therein; for as diſorder in the firſt Wheel of a Watch or Clock, makes confuſion in all the reſt: ſo Monarchy (Gods own Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment) being once changed into Oli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>garchy and Tyranny, there quickly followed a change of all Gods other Laws and Ordinances in the whole ſphere of Religion and Government: <hi>uno errore conceſſo, mille ſequuntur.</hi> As when <hi>Cain</hi> had once killed <hi>Abel,</hi> the wickedneſs of the Old World began to flow in apace, like ſo many Waves one upon the neck of another<note n="c" place="margin">Gen. 6.</note>: So theſe Blunderbuſs <hi>Zamzummims</hi>
                  <note n="d" place="margin">Deut. 2.20.</note>, when they had once deſtroyed the Lords Anointed, grew deſperate, over Shoos over Boots, (as they ſay) they did not care what they did; they became men of Gigan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tick-like wickedneſs, Rebels againſt Heaven, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>fighters againſt God;</hi> they turned themſelves in the next place directly againſt the Lord himſelf, and his Church: they took as much delight to oppoſe God in the order and government of his Church, as Satan doth to fiſh in troubled Waters. Their
<pb n="123" facs="tcp:58923:63"/>new modelled Common-wealth muſt have a new faſhioned Religion to up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold it.</p>
               <p>As, 1. They oppoſed God in his order, by changing the primitive Government of his Church by Epiſcopacy, into a new invented one of their own, called Presbytery: Engliſh <hi>Athenians</hi> all for novelties; they thought themſelves ſuch perfect workmen in Gods Vineyard, that they ſcorned to be guided by Gods general rule of decency and order<note n="e" place="margin">1 Cor. 14.40.</note>; they made a <hi>Lesbian</hi> rule of their own, called a Directory, for the publick worſhip of God, appointed (contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry to their knowledge<note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>Marſhal,</hi> (one of <hi>Cromwels</hi> Journey-men Prieſts,) decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red againſt all uſe of Common-Prayer by others, and yet mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried his own Daughter with the ſame Book, and a Ring, and gave for reaſon, that the Statute Eſtabliſhing that Litur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gy was not yet repealed, and he was loth to have his Daughter Whored, and turned back up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on him for want of legal mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riage. Hiſt. <hi>Independ.</hi> Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleat. Part 1. <hi>p.</hi> 80.</note> and conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence) to be uſed inſtead of our Common-Prayer, in oppoſition to Gods command to glorifie him with one mind, and one mouth<note n="f" place="margin">Rom. 15.6.</note>. And (as our martyred Soveraign ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerveth in his 'ΕΙΚΩΝ ΒΑΣΙ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ΛΙΚΗ) they alſo ſet forth old Catechiſms, and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſions of Faith new dreſt: importing as much (ſaith he) as if there had been no
<pb n="124" facs="tcp:58923:64"/>ſound and clear doctrine of faith in this Church, before ſome four or five years conſultation had matured their thoughts touching their firſt princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples of Religion. Moreover, as <hi>Jero<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boam</hi> (anſwerable to his Idolatry,) made Prieſts of the loweſt of the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, which were not of the ſons of <hi>Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vi</hi>
                  <note n="g" place="margin">1 Kings 12.31.</note>: So theſe Changers from the fear of the Lord and the King, (anſwera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to their confuſion,) ſilenced the true Clergy of God, and choſe the very ſcum of the Nation to preach in their room; in oppoſition to the Lords De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cree and Ordinance, <hi>that no man taketh this honour unto himſelf, but he that is called of God, as was Aaron</hi>
                  <note n="h" place="margin">Heb. 5.4.</note>. Yea, they hated Gods Clergy ſo vehement<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, that they contradicted them even in their very appearel; they preached in Cloaks, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> in oppoſition to their orderly and Canonical veſtments. And what ſhould I ſay more? They ſlighted Gods Ordinances ſo much, that they firſt cauſed the Banes of Marriage to be cryed in the Market-place, and then the parties to be married by Juſtices of the Peace, in private houſes; in oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition to Gods Miniſters, at Church. O what muſt one day be the judgment
<pb n="125" facs="tcp:58923:64"/>of theſe hare-brain'd wretches! That ſet no more by Gods Ordinances; eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pecially, that contemn the holy State of Marriage, ſo honourable in all<note n="i" place="margin">Heb. 13.4.</note>, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtituted by God himſelf in Paradiſe<note n="k" place="margin">Gen. 2.24. Mat. 19.5, 6.</note>, the emblem of Chriſt and his Church<note n="l" place="margin">Eph. 5.32. Rev. 19.7.</note>, yea, honoured by Chriſt, our Saviour with his firſt miracle<note n="m" place="margin">John 2.11.</note>. <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>zziah,</hi> for all he was a King, a perſon not only Civil, but Sacred too; yet came (we know) to a very fearful end, for inva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding the Prieſts Office<note n="n" place="margin">2 Chron. 26.</note>. Judge ye then, what muſt be the end of inferior Magiſtrates.</p>
               <p>But this is not all, they did alſo moſt irreverently receive the Sacrament, ſitting, in oppoſition to St. <hi>Pauls</hi> moſt reverent geſture of kneeling<note n="o" place="margin">Eph. 3.14.</note>. Though even common reaſon teach them, that ſo great a duty, and ſublime a myſtery muſt in proportion have the humbleſt geſture: Eſpecially, when as every man that expects to be exalted with Chriſt to glory, muſt bow the Knee at his very name; in Commemoration, that God for his wonderful humility upon the Croſs, <hi>hath highly exalted him, and given him a name above every name</hi>
                  <note n="p" place="margin">Phil. 2.8, 9, 10.</note>. But alas! Their minds were
<pb n="126" facs="tcp:58923:65"/>ſo bent upon their malice and changing, that they had not the leaſt regard to Scripture, or reaſon: Or if they had, it was only to Crucifie them, as the <hi>Jews</hi> our Saviour, becauſe they judged them to be againſt their profit; or at leaſt to rack them, till they ſpoke the ſenſe of their own vain and fooliſh imaginations.</p>
               <p>And therefore theſe Enthuſiaſts run on deſperately, without any fear or wit in their changing; they proceed farther, and deſpiſe God next in his Church, his holy-houſe or Sanctuary; which, though it be a place command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed him to be ſeparated, (as his day) from all common uſages, and appropri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ated to him by a ſolemn dedication<note n="q" place="margin">Exod. 25.8.</note>: yet they put no difference between it and their own common and prophane dwellings, as we are commanded to do<note n="r" place="margin">1 Cor. 11.22.</note>. They changed their private houſes into publick meeting places, under a pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence of godlineſs, and turned the houſe of God into a place of merchandiſe, and a Den of Thieves, with their carnal buſineſs: in oppoſition to Gods Laws in the Old Teſtament<note n="ſ" place="margin">Dut. 12.4, 5. Levit. 19.20.</note>, and in oppoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion too to Chriſts Laws in the New<note n="t" place="margin">Mat. 21.13. John 2.16.17.</note>;
<pb n="127" facs="tcp:58923:65"/>who both by precept and example hath confirmed the relative holineſs of the Temple under the Law, and the reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence due unto the ſame, to be in our Churches, to all ſucceeding Generati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, now, and for ever, <hi>Mark</hi> 11.17. <hi>Is it not written, my houſe ſhall be called of all Nations the houſe of Prayer? but ye have made it a Den of Thieves.</hi> Mark the words: Chriſt doth not ſay, my Houſe (in the preſent tenſe) is called of all Nations the houſe of Prayer; for that could not be, becauſe the Gentiles were not then converted: But behold! <hi>Is it not written, my Houſe</hi> (in the future tenſe) <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>ſhall be called of all Nations the houſe of Prayer?</hi> not only of the <hi>Jews,</hi> but of the Gentiles too, when they are once converted, and eſtabliſhed in the Faith: When the hedge of ſeparation between <hi>Jew</hi> and <hi>Gentile</hi> is broken down, and God ſhall be worſhipped in all places, or Nations, even now, and for ever, in all circumſtances, and va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rieties of time and Nation, to the end of the World.</p>
               <p>Yet notwithſtanding this, they would juſtifie themſelves in their pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phanation, moſt impudently and blaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phemouſly affirming that the
<pb n="128" facs="tcp:58923:66"/>Church, or houſe of God hath no more holineſs in it than a Barn or a Stable. And for confirmation, theſe blind Phari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſees would therein alſo diſhonour God in his holy Ordinances, both in prayer, and preaching. For, 1. though in the time of Divine ſervice, they would ſeem to honour God by being uncover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in prayer; yet at other times they would deſpiſe it, and prefer preaching above it. And, 2. in Preaching they did no leſs contradict themſelves, for though they did ſo much extol it above prayer, yet as ſoon as the Text was de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>livered, they would moſt irreverent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly put on their Hats, and be covered: as if Preaching or Propheſying were not Gods Ordinance, as well as Prayer; becauſe that Prayer is the principal<note n="*" place="margin">Though preaching may ſeem to be more prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipal than prayer, in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard that in preaching God ſpeaks to man, and in prayer man to God; yet prayer is the princpal, in two reſpects: 1. In regard that in prayer man ſpeaks to God by the mediation of God, Chriſt, God-man; where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as in preaching God ſpeaks to man, only by man, like our ſelves. 2. In regard of the frequency of the duty commauded: wherefore Gods houſe is called the houſe of prayer, not of preaching.</note>. I am ſure St. <hi>Paul</hi> hath taught us to honour Chriſt our Head, by uncover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing our heads in both, Prayer or Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheſying or Preaching<note n="u" place="margin">1 Cor. 11.3, 4.</note>. For the word for Propheſying in the Original doth ſignifie either Propheſying or Preaching
<pb n="129" facs="tcp:58923:66"/>indifferently; Propheſying is but a mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raculous Preaching, and Preaching an ordinary Propheſying: and no marvel, for God is eſpecially preſent in all his Ordinances, in one as well as another; all are his, without exception. Be not deceived, God is not mocked<note n="w" place="margin">Gal. 6.7.</note>: He will not be ſerved by piecemeals, he will have all, or none<note n="x" place="margin">Mat. 23.23. 1 Theſ. 5.23.</note>; he that honours God in one duty, and not in another, diſhonoureth him in all<note n="y" place="margin">James 2.10.</note>. Yet for all this, theſe proud Clowns did therein add prophaneneſs to prophaneneſs; they would not ſtick to diſhonour even man himſelf, for the Lords ſake: For while the Sermon was in delivering, they would be covered before their Betters, though in the very act their Betters themſelves were uncovered: But as ſoon as the Sermon was ended, then they would put off their Hats, and do obey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſance to their Superiors; as if man were to be reſpected more than God; or as if God (the jealouſie of whoſe honour burneth like fire) was beſt ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved when he is the moſt diſhonoured: Or elſe perhaps alſo for joy that the Sermon was ended, for many times they would depart, before the Bleſſing was pronounced.</p>
               <p>But from whence came this blind de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>votion
<pb n="130" facs="tcp:58923:67"/>of theirs, this prophaneneſsin the very abſtract? You have heard it alrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, from infidelity: God is a Spirit in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſible, and can only be ſeen by the eye of Faith<note n="z" place="margin">Heb. 11.1, 6.</note>. Which eye theſe wanting, it is not to be admired, that they ſhould neglect the honour of his infinite and adorable Majeſty, which they could not ſee, but only Hiſtorically: Eſpecially, being ſeduced therein, by the pernici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous doctrine and examples of Old <hi>Oli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>livers</hi> Journey-man Prieſts; who cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tivated their judgments, teaching them by an implicit faith, <hi>jurare in verba ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtri,</hi> to pin their opinions upon their ſleeves.</p>
               <p>And as they taught theſe this, &amp; other helliſh leſſons how to change from the fear of the Lord and the King: So they boaſted<note n="*" place="margin">Hiſt. <hi>Iude<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pend.</hi> Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleat. Part 2. <hi>p.</hi> 149. and <hi>p.</hi> 150.</note> that they had many Agents in <hi>France,</hi> who under colour of Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chandiſe, vented their Anti-Monarchical and Anarchical Tenets among the poor Peaſants and Hugenots, which they alſo bragged, proſpered well there, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>O what muſt one day be the judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of ſuch prophane men! the judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of theſe blind guidesfor fanataciz<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the blind multitude, muſt without all doubt be very much the greateſt, as having not only their own ſins to an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer
<pb n="131" facs="tcp:58923:67"/>for, but the ſins of their Audi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors<note n="a" place="margin">Mat. 5.19.</note>: yet their judgment ſhall be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like in this, they ſhall both fall into the Ditch<note n="b" place="margin">Mat. 15.14.</note>: They both diſhonoured the Lord here, both in his Sanctuary, and in his Ordinances; therefore neither of them both ſhall have the honour at laſt, to come within the true <hi>Sanctum San<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctorum,</hi> the ſeat of the bleſſed<note n="c" place="margin">1 Sam. 2.30.</note>.</p>
               <p>But I muſt remember, that my buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs is not to ſtand upon the confutati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the errors of theſe Changers: nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther need I, they are ſo notoriouſly bad, that they confute themſelves: but on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to give you ſome inſtances of the ſad effects of their changing, that ye may be as cautious for the future how ye meddle with theſe Changers, as the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer: for you have ſeen how they firſt oppoſed the Lord in the King, and how they next oppoſed him, in almoſt all his other Laws and Ordinances; ſhuck the very foundation of our Church, and put all things therein out of frame. Yea, they baniſhed and contemned even the Lords-Prayer it ſelf; becauſe (as our Martyred Soveraign ſaith in his divine meditations<note n="*" place="margin">ΕΙΚΩΝ ΒΑΣΙ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ΛΙΚΗ</note>) it is the warrant and Ori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginal pattern of all ſet Liturgies in the Chriſtian Church. And what ſhould I ſay more? They taught for doctrines
<pb n="132" facs="tcp:58923:68"/>the commandments of wicked men, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſieging God (as it were) with affronts and indignities, meerly out of ſpite to the True Loyaliſt and Conformiſt, becauſe they had uſed thoſe Divine Laws and Ordinances before out of love and fear to the Lord and the King.</p>
               <p>Now, that they might uphold this new Religion of theirs, (anſwerable to their new faſhioned Common-Wealth) from being caſt down, by the great viſibility of thoſe evils which they committed in their changing, they co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered them ſo artificially with a form of Godlineſs, that the rude multitude were ſo far from diſcovering them, that they believed all that they ſaid to be Goſpel: And accordingly, they were as obedient unto them, as that rabble of the <hi>Eſſens</hi> among the <hi>Jews</hi> were to <hi>Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>das</hi> of <hi>Galilee</hi>
                  <note n="d" place="margin">Acts 5.36, 37.</note>, or rather as many o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers among them alſo were to the Old Scribes and Phariſees; for the truth is, theſe pretended Reformers, though in ſome things they do far exceed the Pha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſees in hypocriſie, yet in many things (which occaſion offers to ſpeak of now more fully and together) they do re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſemble them ſo exactly, that you would think that the ſouls of the Phariſees were entred into their bodies, by a
<pb n="133" facs="tcp:58923:68"/>
                  <hi>Pythagorean</hi> Tranſmigration. The Pha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſees were the moſt ſtrict and preciſe Sect of the <hi>Jews,</hi> they deſired to be counted more holy than any, the only Saints upon earth, and did accordingly ſeparate themſelves from the reſt of the Church, and from thence they were called Phariſees. Yet they were only outwardly ſo, their inward parts burnt altogether with deceit and hypocriſie; they were like unto whited Sepulchres, beautiful without, and within full of uncleanneſs<note n="e" place="margin">Mat. 23.27, 28.</note>. They were great Zea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lots in Religion, yet they were blind, their zeal was without knowledge, it conſiſted chiefly in perſecuting Chriſt and his Church<note n="f" place="margin">Phil. 3.6.</note>: They were great pretenders to righteouſneſs, the only Puritans of that age. They were men of a ſad Countenance, they would faſt often, and ſhew great Auſterity. And ſometimes too they would ſeem very charitable, and give much Almes to the Poor: but their evil ends robb'd their holy actions of their reward: for they did not do them for conſcience ſake, that they might glorifie God, and lay up for themſelves Treaſures in heaven; but only in policy, for their covetouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, and vain glory's ſake; that they might have the better excuſe at other
<pb n="134" facs="tcp:58923:69"/>times to lay up for themſelves the more Treaſures upon Earth, and get the greater ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plauſe in being ſeen of men, <hi>Mat.</hi> 6. They were alſo great Enthuſiaſts; like <hi>Cromwell,</hi>
                  <note n="*" place="margin">When <hi>Cromwell</hi> (contrary to his vows and proteſtations made to the King) kept him cloſe priſoner in <hi>Carisbrook</hi> Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle; he affirmed the ſpirit would not let him keep his word. When contrary to the publick faith, they murdered him; they pretended, they could not reſiſt the motions of the ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit. <hi>Sua cui<expan>
                           <am>
                              <g ref="char:abque"/>
                           </am>
                           <ex>que</ex>
                        </expan> Deus ſit dira libido.</hi> This Hobgoblin ſerves all turns, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Hiſt. <hi>Independ Compleat.</hi> Part 3. <hi>p.</hi> 23.</note> and the five lights<note n="†" place="margin">Hiſt. <hi>Independ.</hi> Part 2. <hi>p.</hi> 152, 153.</note> of <hi>Walton,</hi> they pretended (eſpecial<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſuch of that Sect as were Scribes) to have great skill in the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, and new revela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of the Spirit. And like<note n="*" place="margin">Sunday after <hi>Eaſter-day,</hi> ſix Preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers militant at <hi>White-Hall</hi> tryed the patience of their hearers, one calling up another ſucceſſively; at laſt the Spirit of the Lord called up <hi>Oliver Cromwell,</hi> who ſtanding a good while with lifted up eyes, as it were in a Trance, and his neck a little in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clining to one ſide, as if he had expected <hi>Mahomets Dove</hi> to deſcend and murmur in his Ear; and ſending forth abundantly the groans of the Spirit, ſpent an hour in prayer, and an hour and an half in a Sermon. In his prayer he deſired God to take off from him the Government of this mighty people of <hi>England,</hi> as being too heavy for his Shoulders to bear: An audacious, ambitious, and hypocritical imitation of <hi>Moſes.</hi> It is now reported of him, that he pretendeth to inſpirations; and that when any Great or Weighty matter is propounded, he uſually retireth for a quarter or half an hour, and then returneth and delivereth out the Oracles of the ſpirit: ſurely the ſpirit of <hi>John Leyden</hi> will be doubled upon this man. Hiſt. <hi>Independ. Compleat.</hi> Part 2. <hi>p.</hi> 153, 154.</note> 
                  <hi>Cromwell</hi> too they were much for preaching, but they ſaid and did not; they would not undergo any bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then of ſelf-denial, themſelves, but they made them to hang very weighty and
<pb n="135" facs="tcp:58923:69"/>grievous to be born, on the ſhoulders of their Auditors, <hi>Mat.</hi> 23. Moreover, they lenghtened out their prayers with vain repetitions, thinking to be heard for their much babling: And made long prayers too, both out of vain glory, to be ſeen of men; and for a colour, to hide their oppreſſion, in devouring the Houſes or Eſtates even of the Fatherleſs and Widow. For prevention of which our Saviour teaches his Diſciples and us how to pray, in a ſhort pithy and ſet form of Prayer, <hi>Mat.</hi> 6. and <hi>Luke</hi> 11. Beſides, they were ſuperſtitiouſly zea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous in keeping the <hi>Sabbath,</hi> and often quarrelled with our Saviour for break<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing it, though it were only in works of mercy and neceſſity: And yet they were as great prophaners of the Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, they made Gods houſe a houſe of Merchandiſe, and a Den of Thieves; for which they were as ſharply reprov<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by our Saviour, in that they would offer to mock God in his Law, which joyneth them together, commanding us to reverence his Sanctuary, as well as to keep his Sabbaths<note n="g" place="margin">Levit. 19.30.</note>. And they made a conſcience too of ſmaller matters, as of Ceremonies; but omitted the weigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tier matters of the Law, as judgment, mercy, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> And what ſhould I add
<pb n="136" facs="tcp:58923:70"/>more? they were alſo Proud, and Cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſorious, great juſtifiers of themſelves, and condemners of all others<note n="h" place="margin">Luke 18.10.</note>
               </p>
               <p>With theſe, and ſuch like ſpecious and hypocritical ſhews of holineſs, they ſo blinded the rude multitude, that their word was to them of as great authority, as <hi>Ariſtotle</hi>'s <hi>ipſe dixit</hi> among his Scho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lars: and therefore when the Officers were ſent to attach Chriſt, though they were convinced by his invincible ſayings that they ought to become Chriſtians, yet they durſt not follow him without the approbation of the Phariſees; for that was the rule given to reſtrain them, <hi>have any of the Phari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſees believed on him</hi>
                  <note n="i" place="margin">John 7.48.</note>? And no marvel, for Satan himſelf when he would be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>witch, puts on <hi>Samuels</hi> Mantle<note n="k" place="margin">1 Sam. 28.14.</note>; he is transformed into an Angel of light, when he would deceive the ſim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple: Therefore it is no great thing if his Miniſters alſo be transformed as the Miniſters of Righteouſneſs, whoſe end ſhall be according to their works, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.14, 15.</p>
               <p>But Firſt, before God made their end anſwerable to their own works, he uſed them as a Rod to ſcourge us for ours: We were a ſinful Nation, a peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple laden, and hardened with iniquity;
<pb n="137" facs="tcp:58923:70"/>God did ſtrive to win us by all means and mercies, no leſs than he did with the Old Word<note n="l" place="margin">2 Pet. 2.5.</note>, but nothing would ſerve the turn, therefore being weary (as it were, with ſtriving<note n="m" place="margin">Gen. 6.</note>,) he that can bring the greateſt good out of the great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt evil, ſeeing that our ſins were now fully ripe, finiſhed, and come to an height by an horrid Regicide and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bellion, made uſe of theſe Changers to execute his wrath and Vengeance upon us; that ſo (as our martyred Soveraign ſaith moſt piouſly, and judiciouſly in his Divine Meditations<note n="*" place="margin">ΕΙΚΩΝ ΒΑΣΙ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ΛΙΚΗ</note>) he might reap that glory in our calamity, which we robbed him of in our proſperity. 1. By ſuffering them to martyr our King, (as the good King <hi>Joſiah</hi> was taken away by a violent death, for the ſins of <hi>Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dah</hi>
                  <note n="n" place="margin">Lam. 4.20. (in the vulgar Latine it is <hi>captus eſt in pec catis noſtris</hi>) compared with 2 Chron. 35.25.</note>: that ſo his ſervant and Vicege<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent being removed, (who like <hi>Moſes</hi> ſtood in the Gap between the ſins of his people and Gods judgments) he might the more freely power out the vials of his wrath upon us: Therefore we find that the want of a King, (eſpecially ſuch a King as ours) is threatned by God as a grievous calamity, and inflicted for the puniſhment of a peoples wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>edneſs. Now they ſhall ſay, we have no King, becauſe we feared not the
<pb n="138" facs="tcp:58923:71"/>Lord; what then ſhall a King do to us<note n="o" place="margin">Hoſ. 10.3. 1 Sam. 12.25.</note>? The remotion of our King was but the beginning of our ſorrows; for, 2. Behold! then the Lord, the Lord of Hoſts did alſo take away from three flouriſhing Kingdoms the ſtay and the ſtaff, the whole ſtay of Bread, and the whole ſtay of Water; all our Lands and livings; our Mighty Men, and our Men of War, our Judges, our Clergy, our Prudent and our ancient; our ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourable men, our Counſellers, our cunning Artificers, and our eloquent Orators. And then alſo he gave Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren to be our Princes, and Babes to rule over us. And then too he ſuffered us to be oppreſſed, every one by his Neighbour; and our childiſh Rulers to behave themſelves proudly againſt the Ancient, and the Baſe againſt the Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourable<note n="p" place="margin">Iſa. 3.</note>. And what ſhould I ſay more? Our <hi>Mount Sion</hi> was alſo then deſolate, and Foxes walked upon it. And finally, all our joy too was then turned into mourning; ſo that then well might be renewed that lamentati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on which the Church made for <hi>Joſiah, the Crown is fallen from our Head: Woe unto us that we have ſinned!</hi> Lam. 5.15, 16, 18.</p>
               <pb n="139" facs="tcp:58923:71"/>
               <p>But now Secondly, God having (for twelve years together, ſuffered them (as our Martyred Soveraign propheti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cally ſpeaketh in his Divine Meditati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons<note n="*" place="margin">ΕΙΚΩΝ ΒΑΣ ΙΛΙΚΗ.</note>) to be deluded with the proſperi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of their wickedneſs, made their end according to their own works indeed; for (bleſſed be his mercy) having (for ſo long time) uſed them, as a rod of correction to humble us for our ſins, in the School of his ſevere judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments,<note place="margin">Pſa. 89.32. Prov. 22.15.</note> that we might be ſure to learn Righteouſneſs<note n="q" place="margin">Iſa. 26.29.</note>; out of indignation to ſee his Laws ſo trampled upon and deſpiſed, he ſtraight throws the rod in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the fire, and in deſpite of all their ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lice, <hi>poſt varios caſus, poſt tot diſcrimi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na rerum,</hi> ſtretches forth his hand of Providence upon our now moſt Graci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Soveraign Lord King <hi>Charles</hi> the Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond, (the ſame hand, which before had preſerved him in all his various trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles and misfortunes) and brings him in again, (and that in peace, both as a <hi>manifeſto</hi> of his own good pleaſure, and of his Vicegerents being a Prince of Peace) and reſtores him to his own in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heritance, his fathers Crown, Throne and Scepter: That he might execute his wrath upon theſe rebellious Chang<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers; reſtore us to our antient Laws,
<pb n="140" facs="tcp:58923:72"/>and Liberties; and ſet all things to rights again, both in Church and State.</p>
               <p>All which (thanks be to God) by his good Government he hath accordingly done. And in order to the latter, (which was the principal end of his Reſtauration) he hath moſt juſtly pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed ſome of the chief offenders with Death, for example to the reſt, whom he did not utterly deſtroy; but in obedience to his Lords command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment<note n="r" place="margin">Prov. 20.26.</note>, moſt wiſely ſcatter up and down the Nation, for a greater Curſe<note n="ſ" place="margin">Mat. 15.14. Hoſ. 4.17.</note>: as <hi>Cain</hi> for murdering his brother <hi>Abel,</hi> became a Fugitive and a Vagabond in the Earth; and driven from the face or preſence of God, or (<note n="†" place="margin">Buxtorf. <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </note> as the Original words for Vagabond and Fugitive do ſignifie) accurfed, or Excommunicated from the ſociety of his Church<note n="t" place="margin">Gen. 4.12, 14.</note>. Or as the <hi>Jews</hi> (who were Typified therein) for Crucifying Chriſt, the Lord of Glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, are to this day accurſed and ſcattered abroad (as ſo many Vagabonds) over the face of the Earth<note n="u" place="margin">Mat. 27.25. James. 1.1.</note>: ſo theſe rebel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lious Changers, and Fanaticks, e for murdering his Vicegerent, King <hi>Charles</hi> the Firſt, our glorious Lord, are Accurſed and Excommunicated from the ſociety of Gods people, or his
<pb n="141" facs="tcp:58923:72"/>Church; and juſtly diſperſed into ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral parts of the Nation, according to their various Factions, Sects and Schiſms.</p>
               <p>And, 2. As they are thus ſcattered up and down the Nation, for a Curſe and a Judgment unto themſelves: ſo they are ſuffered to dwell amongſt us, no leſs for a bleſſing unto us. 1. To ſet us off, and make us ſhine the brighter, as the Foil doth the Diamond; for the manifeſtation of the True Loyaliſt and Conformiſt; <hi>there muſt be hereſies a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong you,</hi> (ſaith the Apoſtle) <hi>that they which are approved may be made ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſt among you</hi>
                  <note n="w" place="margin">1 Cor. 11.19.</note>. 2. To try and prove us, as the <hi>Canaanites</hi> were left with <hi>Iſrael</hi> in the Land of Promiſe, <hi>to be Pricks in their Eyes, and Thorns in their Sides,</hi> to make them ſtick the cloſer unto God<note n="x" place="margin">Numb. 33.55. Joſh. 23.13. Judg. 2.3.</note>. Finally, to make us ſavour our peace with perpetual delight and complacency; that as the peace which we now enjoy, was at firſt ingratiated<note n="*" place="margin">Deſiderata diù magis pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>t.</note> unto us by a long deſire: ſo it may ſtill continue in the ſame perfection, by having ſuch examples a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong us, to remind us of our former bondage and tribulation.</p>
               <pb n="142" facs="tcp:58923:73"/>
               <p>Well then, ſince we have ſuch a perfect peace, and order in all things both in Church and State, that I may ſay (with a ſafe conſcience) that our condition (as far as I can poſſibly under ſtand;) is more happy than any Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons under the Sun; let us be wiſe, and keep our ſelves well, while we are well, (if we know when we are well) in the fear of the Lord and the King: and no more diſturb our own quiet, by med<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dling with them that are given to change.</p>
               <p>In which words we muſt obſerve this difference, that it is one thing to change, and another thing to be given to change: the firſt denotes only a ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gle act, and if it proceed no farther, it is moſt commonly a remarkable ſign of a mutation from the worſe to the better; our Lord himſelf, (who changes not<note n="y" place="margin">Mal. 3.6.</note>) did thus change the Law into the Goſpel, legal Types and ſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dows into good things to come<note n="z" place="margin">Heb. 10.1.</note>. And with the Law, he alſo changed the cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtoms which <hi>Moſes</hi> delivered, into the cuſtoms of the Gentiles<note n="a" place="margin">2. Cor. 17. Rev. 21.5.</note>: as for exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, he not only changed the Judaical cuſtom of falling down to worſhip, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to ours of bowing, but (to ſhew the
<pb n="143" facs="tcp:58923:73"/>ſublimity of the Goſpel above the Law, the earthlineſs of the one, and the hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venlineſs of the other<note n="b" place="margin">Gal. 4.9. Col. 2.14.</note>: He alſo chang<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed their cuſtom of diſcalceation or put<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting off the Shooes, or Sandals in token of reverence when they went to the houſe of God<note n="c" place="margin">Ec leſiaſtes 5.1. Exod. 3.5. Acts 7.33.</note>, into ours of putting off the Hat, or uncovering the head, in to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken of honour to Chriſt, our Head<note n="d" place="margin">1 Cor. 11.3, 4.</note>.</p>
               <p>For theſe words (which are too of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten miſtaken by the weak) do clearly expreſs Chriſts will in this change, though St. <hi>Paul</hi> did then only begin to effect it; (as all Reformations are wrought by degrees) for there was no ſuch cuſtom as this, of uncovering the head, eſtabliſhed as yet among the <hi>Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rinthians,</hi> nor in any of the Churches of God<note n="e" place="margin">Ver. 16.</note>: the only cuſtom then extant, to pay reverence by, to God in his Sanctua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry and Ordinances, was that of diſcal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceation among the <hi>Jews;</hi> from whom the <hi>Corinthians</hi> (they being then in St. <hi>Pauls</hi> abſence frequently among them, to ſupplant the new founded truth,) had without all doubt learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed this cuſtom to put off their Shooes, whilſt their heads at the ſame time were covered in their holy Aſſemblies. Wherefore St. <hi>Paul</hi> (to make way for
<pb n="144" facs="tcp:58923:74"/>a thorough Reformation) as before he had commended them for keeping Chriſts Ordinances, as he delivered them<note n="f" place="margin">Ver. 2.</note>: ſo now having reproved them for diſhonouring of Chriſt their Head, in being covered, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> in their holy Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſemblies, leſt he ſhould marr all again by his ſeverity, doth endeavour to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>move from them all matter of conten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, by leaving them to their own choice of theſe cuſtoms, Whether they would give God reverence by the cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtom of uncovering the head, which was to take place; or whether by the cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtom of diſcalceation, or putting off the Shooes, which as yet was not laid aſide, he left them to their own freedom: he had rather indeed that they would have accepted of the former, yet as the caſe now ſtood, he did not much matter whether, ſo long as God as yet had his due honour in either. And for the ſame reaſon too he took <hi>Timothy</hi> and Circumciſed him, becauſe of the <hi>Jews</hi>
                  <note n="g" place="margin">Acts 16.3.</note>. And ſo alſo, though he was free from all men, yet (the Church being but yet in its Infancy) he became ſervant to all, both <hi>Jew</hi> and <hi>Gentile,</hi> that he might gain the more unto Chriſt<note n="h" place="margin">1 Cor. 9.19. to ver. 24.</note>.
<pb n="145" facs="tcp:58923:74"/>But now the Church is ſetled, and grown to a perfect man, we muſt <hi>ſtand faſt in the liberty wherewith Chriſt hath made us free, and not be entangled again with the yoke of Bondage:</hi> We muſt no more uſe the Judaical cuſtom of diſcal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceation, and cover our heads in Gods houſe and Ordinances, nor any more be Circumciſed; if we do, behold, (as the ſame Apoſtle hath alſo taught us) Chriſt ſhall profit us nothing<note n="i" place="margin">Gal, 5.1, 2.</note>: For ſo we ſhall be debtors to the whole Law<note n="k" place="margin">Verſ. 3.</note>, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequently concluded under its Curſe, eternal wrath<note n="l" place="margin">Gal. 3.10.</note>. This change therefore was good, ſuperlatively good to thoſe that have intereſt therein<note n="m" place="margin">2 Cor. 3.6.</note>: God is to be ever bleſſed, in that the Prieſthood being changed, there was made of neceſſity a change alſo of the Law, <hi>Heb.</hi> 7.12.</p>
               <p>And, 2. Time was too when we changed the Romiſh Religion into ours, according to the Primitive rule of Reformation<note n="n" place="margin">Mat. 19.8.</note>, becauſe they had firſt changed it from the unerring rule of Gods word: Therefore there was a neceſſity of this change alſo; leſt other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe by not coming out of her, we partake of her ſins, and receive of her Plagues, <hi>Rev.</hi> 18.4.</p>
               <pb n="146" facs="tcp:58923:75"/>
               <p>But the ſecond, to be given to change, is always a true ſign of a mutation from the better to the worſe: Neither doth it at any time denote a ſingle act only, but always an evil habit or diſpoſition of mind: it is a product of the natural man, which is always greedy of no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>velties. And ſuch were our Changers: they were taken with novelties (as our martyred Soveraign<note n="*" place="margin">ΕΙΚΩΝ Β ΑΣΙΛΙΚΗ.</note> again moſt wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tily obſerveth) like Children with ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bies, very much, but not very long: they were poſſeſſed with the evil ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of Fanaticiſm, and therefore muſt needs be reſtleſs in their condition: as a man diſtempered with a Fever, is al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways deſirous to change his place, though it be never ſo ſoft and eaſie, till by his tumbling and toſſing, he hath made it hard indeed: So Fana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticks are never ſatisfied with their con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition, let the times be never ſo good, till they have made them as bad as may be, with their changing: We have lately ſeen that they did as much inju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry both in Church and State by their frantick zeal and curioſity, as an Ape in a Glaſs ſhop, move and remove till they had marr'd all. And how often too, ſince our laſt bleſſed Reformation,
<pb n="147" facs="tcp:58923:75"/>have our old Fanaticks or their ſpawn troubled Authority to ſuppreſs their Conventicles, from riſing and ſeeking a change.</p>
               <p>Moſt wiſely therefore hath <hi>Solomon</hi> given us this ſeaſonable Caution to meddle not with them that are given to change, <hi>viz.</hi> not only, (though chief<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly) to meddle not, or have any hand at all with them in their changing, but alſo (to that end) to have as little ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciety<note n="*" place="margin">Evil com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munication (you know) corrupteth good man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners; have a care there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore of ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king any your familiar friend, but them that truly fear the Lord and the King.</note> with them otherwiſe as in pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence we can, unleſs it be to reprove them; leſt by their good words and fair ſpeeches they at length deceive us, as they themſelves are deceived<note n="o" place="margin">Rom. 16.18. 2 Tim. 3.13.</note>: turn our hearts from fearing the Lord and the King: decoy us into their Facti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, under the pretence of a godly party; and ſo make our folly (in ſtirring up ſtrife and contention) as manifeſt to the world, as their own. Whence <hi>Solomon</hi> alſo telleth us, that it is an ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour for a man to ceaſe from ſtrife: But every fool will be medling<note n="p" place="margin">Pro. 20.3.</note>. The ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect for the cauſe; It is an honour for a man to ceaſe from ſuch Changers and changing, becauſe that cannot be without ſtrife and contention; with
<pb n="148" facs="tcp:58923:76"/>whom to meddle is therefore a great argument of folly, as it is in them to be given to change<note n="q" place="margin">Prov. 10.23.</note>. They are ſuch Sots as well as ſinners, that Changelings themſelves (whom the world counts fools in the deepeſt grain) do ſeem to take their name from them. I know ſome will tell you that Changelings are ſo called, from children being changed by Fairies in the time of Popery; but that at the beſt is but a vulgar error, or an Old Wives ſtory: It is more likely that Change<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lings, (to demonſtrate the greatneſs of their folly and childiſhneſs) do borrow their name from theſe Changers, that are given to change; becauſe they re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſemble them ſo much in natural folly and childiſhneſs. And accordingly the Apoſtle compares thoſe that meddle with them (which is in effect the ſame, as to be given to change) to <hi>Children, toſſed to and fro, and carried about with every wind of Doctrine by the ſlight of men, and cunning craftineſs, whereby they lie in wait to deceive</hi>
                  <note n="r" place="margin">Eph. 4.14.</note> And ſemblably too, St. <hi>James</hi> (to ſhew their weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and great want of wiſdom) com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pares them to Water, (than which there
<pb n="149" facs="tcp:58923:76"/>is nothing leſs apt to keep its bounds) <hi>he that wavereth</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>is like a wave of the Sea, driven with the wind and toſſed</hi>
                  <note n="ſ" place="margin">James 1.6.</note>, yea <hi>a double-minded man</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>is unſtable in all his ways</hi>
                  <note n="t" place="margin">Verſ. 8.</note>.</p>
               <p>Sith then, a man cannot meddle with theſe Changers, without betray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing much weakneſs, folly, and childiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, ye a madneſs in ſtirring up the fire of contention about his ears, till his own peace and honour be conſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med in the flame; we ought in prudence to be ſo much the more wary how we meddle with them any more, eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally, when as they lie in wait to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guile unſtable ſouls, (as the Serpent beguiled <hi>Eve</hi> through his ſubtilty<note n="u" place="margin">2 Cor. 11.3.</note>) that they make them as curſed children as themſelves<note n="w" place="margin">2 Pet. 2.14.</note>. Ye cannot be too wary of them; they will compaſs Sea and Land to make one Proſelyte, and when he is made, they make him (if it were poſſible) twofold more the child of Hell than themſelves<note n="x" place="margin">Mat. 23.15.</note>. Yea, they will uſe all means both fair and foul to win you to their party: ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times they will ſpeak great ſwelling words of vanity<note n="y" place="margin">2 Pet. 2.18.</note>; and ſometimes again they will flatter you with their deceitful tongue<note n="z" place="margin">Pſal. 52.4.</note>. But believe them
<pb n="150" facs="tcp:58923:77"/>not, for it is but to devour you, and make your end as woful as their own<note n="a" place="margin">Prov. 26.25, 28.</note>: They will promiſe you as great ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour and preferment as <hi>Balack</hi> did <hi>Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laam</hi>
                  <note n="b" place="margin">Numb. 22.37.</note>, if you will but joyn with them in defying, and working miſchief a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the True Loyaliſt; but yet (I ſay) believe them not, for it is but to Curſe you with as much ſhame and confuſion, as they are bleſſed with true praiſe that fear the Lord and the King. And finally, if nothing will ſerve the turn, they have one pretence ſtill in reſerve, which they think will never fail them, (their greateſt Decoy to Rebellion) they will tell you, (with much confidence and boaſting) that they are <hi>Cuſtodes Libertatis Angliae,</hi> Keep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers of the Liberty of <hi>England:</hi> and if you will be ſure to meddle, or have a hand with them in their changing, you ſhall not fail to be made partakers thereof, and have as much liberty as you can poſſibly wiſh or deſire. When<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as behold, O ye Fanaticks! even ſome of you your ſelves have ſeen by woful experience, that it is but the eaſilier to overcome you, and bring you under the greater ſlavery and bondage.</p>
               <pb n="151" facs="tcp:58923:77"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>Ye therefore beloved,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> (Saith <hi>He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiod</hi> in his Book <hi>Opera &amp; Dies</hi>) even a Fool will be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe, when by his ſuffering he hath felt his folly. What fools then muſt they needs be, whom expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rience it ſelf cannot teach wiſdom?</note> 
                  <hi>ſeeing ye know theſe things before, beware leſt ye alſo being led away with the er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ror of the wicked, fall from your own ſtedfaſtneſs</hi>
                  <note n="c" place="margin">2 Pet. 3.17.</note>: This caution of the Wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mans, to meddle not with them that are given to change, is a duty (you ſee) of no ſmall concern, when as Gods will is to have it faſtened in our memories with ſo many a precept. We muſt therefore follow what the Wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man again adviſeth us unto, <hi>meddle not with him that flattereth or enticeth with his lips</hi>
                  <note n="d" place="margin">Prov. 20.19.</note>. And the Apoſtles Counſel is no leſs to be obſerved: He doth pour out his very bowels in this reſpect, <hi>Now I beſeech you brethren, mark them which cauſe diviſions and offences, contrary to the Doctrine which ye have learned, and avoid them</hi>
                  <note n="e" place="margin">Rom. 16.17</note>. 'Tis true, Changes, Diviſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons and Offences muſt needs come; God (that changeth not) ſometimes changeth the times and the ſeaſons: he ſometimes removeth Kings, and ſometimes ſetteth up Kings<note n="f" place="margin">Dan. 2.21. Eccleſiaſtes 3.</note>. To what end? for the puniſhment of a ſinful Nation; for the tryal and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bation of the True Loyaliſt; and for the manifeſtation of his own ſupreme
<pb n="152" facs="tcp:58923:78"/>power and authority: yet ye muſt have a ſpecial care that ye be not any Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thors of or in them, for there is a woe pronounced (by our Saviour) unto him through whom they come<note n="g" place="margin">Mat. 18.7. Luke 17.1.</note>.</p>
               <p>O therefore ſtand to your Principles, be ye ſtedfaſt in the faith: let the times change as they will; yet be ſure to have no hand in them: But know the right way of your Salvation, and be un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>movable therein, as conſtant as a Die, which ever falls upon a firm baſis. Gad no more about to change your ways, leſt God bring you again into <hi>Egypt,</hi> and change your glory into ſhame<note n="h" place="margin">Jer. 2.26.</note>. Let not the Papiſts beguile you of your reward, in their voluntary humi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity, and worſhipping of Angels<note n="i" place="margin">Col. 2.18.</note>, nor the Fanaticks, with their Satanical and Pariſaical deluſions: But in as much as they have only a form of godlineſs, and deny the power thereof both in their lives and doctrine, from ſuch turn away. And in all your paſſage through the Waves of this troubleſome World, ſwim ye directly between them both, right down the Silver Stream of Orthodoxneſs and True Loyalty; that ye may not ſplit your felves upon any of thoſe two dange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous
<pb n="153" facs="tcp:58923:78"/>Rocks, the <hi>Scylla</hi> of Popery, and the <hi>Charybdis</hi> of Fanaticiſm; but ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rive ſafely at laſt into the haven of ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting peace.</p>
               <p>And, O that the Papiſts, and Fana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticks themſelves too, would but conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der in this their day, the things that belong unto their peace, (before they be hid from their eyes<note n="k" place="margin">Luk. 19.42.</note>;) then certainly they could never ſo much as deſire a change any more: for when had we the purity of Religion more entire? when was the Nation better ſetled? and the Church more primitively go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verned? when had we more liberty and property? and when did we ſit under our Vines and Figg trees more peace<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ably? <hi>O fortunatos nimium bona ſi ſua nôſſent Anglicolas!</hi> Thou art ſo fortu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate, O <hi>England,</hi> if thou wouldeſt but know it, that many are ſurfeited even with their own happineſs: the Papiſts envy at thy proſperity, and the Fana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticks are ſo glutted with thy temporal bleſſings, that like <hi>Jeſurun</hi> they begin to kick, and forſake the Lord and the King<note n="l" place="margin">Deut. 32.15.</note>. God hath ſo loaded them with his benefits<note n="m" place="margin">Pſa. 68.19.</note>, that they are reſtleſs like ſick folks, and deſire nothing more
<pb n="154" facs="tcp:58923:79"/>than a change, that they may return into <hi>Egypt,</hi> to lighten them again<note n="n" place="margin">Numb. 14.4.</note>.</p>
               <p>But O ye fooliſh people, and unwiſe! What, do ye thus requite the Lord<note n="o" place="margin">Deut. 32.6.</note>? know ye not, that the ſin of ingrati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude doth ſo eminently comprehend all wickedneſs, that it is able to change your Bleſſings into Curſes<note n="p" place="margin">Deut. 28.</note>; your Peace into War; your plenty into pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nury; and your fruitful lands into bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>renneſs<note n="q" place="margin">Pſ. 107.34.</note>?</p>
               <p>O therefore (I ſay again) <hi>conſider</hi> in time, before your change comes<note n="r" place="margin">Job 14.14.</note>, <hi>in this your day,</hi> the ſeaſon of Gods love and mercy<note n="ſ" place="margin">Ezek. 16.8.</note>, <hi>the things that belong unto your eterneal peace:</hi> Be ye heartily ſorry for all the changes that ye have made, or have intended, either in Monarchy, Gods own Government, or in any of his other Laws and Ordinances: and let your minds be changed ſo, as that you can reſolve with duty, never to ſeek a change any more; but for the future be united to the body of True Loyaliſts and Conformiſts, that we may all as Brethren dwell together in unity, and with one heart and one mind demon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate true gratitude and wiſdom, by
<pb n="155" facs="tcp:58923:79"/>giving to God due thanks and praiſe for all his goodneſs and wonderful works that he hath done for this ſtiff necked and undeſerving Kingdom; for ſo ye will be a means, not only to continue his loving kindneſs ſtill unto us, but al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo to procure your own eternal happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and Salvation.</p>
               <p>But however though ſome of them, (God forbid all) whether Papiſts or Fanaticks or both, ſhould be ſo harden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in their ſins, that (notwithſtanding all means and mercies) they will be as far from Converſion and Reformation, as the <hi>Ethiopian</hi> is from changing his skin<note n="t" place="margin">Jer. 13.23.</note>: yet we that are already eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſhed in the preſent truth, let us by no means forget to render unto the Lord due thanks and praiſe for all his favours and benefits<note n="u" place="margin">Pſal. 103.2.</note>. Eſpecially for his late reminding us of our duty, and ingra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiating our peace unto us by little in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terruptions: Be ſure, let us not ceaſe to pray for the peace of <hi>Jeruſalem</hi>
                  <note n="w" place="margin">Pſa. 122.6.</note>, the peace of the whole Kingdom, both Church and State; humbly imploring his Divine Majeſty, that he will always come upon theſe waters of ſtrife, and command the Waves and the Winds
<pb n="156" facs="tcp:58923:80"/>thereof to be huſh and ſtill; that we may ſtill have as great a calm, as there was when Chriſt entred into the Ship of St. <hi>Peter</hi>
                  <note n="x" place="margin">Mark 6.</note>. And finally, for our more aſſured enjoyment of our Halcy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on days, and peaceable ſeaſons, let us be unchangeably reſolved, to <hi>meddle not with them that are given to change;</hi> but expreſs by holy lives and Loyal actions, that our intent is always to <hi>fear the Lord and the King.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Vivat Rex.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>God ſave the King.</p>
               <p>
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</p>
               <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
